<topics>

  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-radium/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-04-19/ed-1/?sp=36&q=Joint+Discoverers+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Radium+Metal</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
        A WONDERFUL WOMAN AND HER HUSBAND WHO ARE JOINT DISCOVERERS OF A WONDERFUL METAL -RADIIM
PROFESSOB AND MME. CURIE AND DAUGHTER SEATED IX THEIR GARDEN
(Photograph by Hurry C Ellis, Paris.)
ably bo beaten in the vicinity of the Pouth P< le,
which is believed to be surrounded by land. No
such severe cold has been found on Arctic seas,
iven in the highest latitude reached. By un
hianned balloons Bent up last winter in Europe
a temperature of 87 below zero was recorded.
With this preface one can partially under
stand a communication recently published in
"The Monthly Weather Review" and "The Na
tional Geographic Magazine." both <>f Washing
ton. R. C. Mossman, meteorologist of the Scot
tish Antarctic expedition, now exploring the re
gion southeastward of Cape Horn, mentions
his preparations for sending up instruments
wit>, kilos, but adds: "There is some possibility
of losing a record by the freezing of the ink, as
we have not tin newly Invented ink containing
tonsol."
As to what "tonsol" is the dictionaries do not
tell. Mr. Mossman is at present inaccessible.
Leading chemists in the metropolis have never
heard <>f it; and this is the waj in which Pro
fessor Willis 1.. Moore, chief of the United
States Weather Bureau in Washington, answers
a query concerning it
We regret th.it there has been .some delay
in making this reply, occasioned by our efforts
to ascertain, if possible, some particulars con
cerning the substance "tonsoL" The only in
formation in the possession of the Weather
Bureau concerning the particular ink mentioned
in Mr Mossman's letter is that con
tained in the letter itself. An Inquiry of chem
ical experts and a search for references to the
substance "tonsol" fail to develop any further
particulars. Dr. Wiley, chief chemist of the
Department of Agriculture, informs u.s that in
very old climates it is customary to add a cer
tain portion of glyc«rol or calcium chloride to
rtiks to secure fluidity, and it i.s possible the term
•"tonsol" may be a trade name for some of these
todies.
RADIUM DISCOVERERS.
Professor and Mme. Curie Are In
deed Helpmeets.
Paris, April 10.
The most striking and interesting personages
It ill' present moment in Paris are Professor
Pierre Curie and his wife, his Invaluable co
«their lives to an astonishingly brilliant series of
experiments in the extraction and isolation 01
radium, the most mysterious and most costly
metal kntwn to the scientific world. M. and
Mme. Curie have provided science with a new
and most powerful weapon. The mineral, which
ha* become the great talk of the day, was dis
covered in 1898 by If. and Mme. Curie, who,
after long and complicated chemical researches,
succeeded in extracting from a ton of the pitch
blende mineral of Joachinistal, in Bohemia, two
decigrams of radium. The operation cost over
which is at the rate of $10.1100 a gram,
or $10,000,000 a kilogram.
To borrow ihe definition <>f Sir William
Crook* s radium possesses the "extraordinary
proportj continuously emitting heat without
combustion, without r-hemical change of any
kitpl anit without anj rhang* 3 in its molecular
structure, which remains spectroscoplcally
Hl'ii:. 1 aftPi- many months of continuous
i,i--i. n Radium salt emits, without
r- pi ii'i< diminutioi of its own •i i l''i'\
NEW YORK TRIBUNE ILLUSTRATED^SUPPLEMENT.
sufficient heat to melt more than its own weight j
of ice every hour. Radium en. its r,i\s of its own
which have the qualities of X rays and of
cat hod ie rays, and is as active in vacuum as in
air. Uranium and thorium throw off analogous
rays, but of an intensity a millionfold less than
the radium rays. The rays "i emanations from
radium penetrate through certain opaque bodies
and make impressions on sensitive films m
closed wooden boxes. For instance, if a coin or
a key or other object be placed in a leather
purse and the purse put ii 'he dark on a sensi
tive plate, and a little radium be placed near at
hand, it will be found that the development of
the plate will produi c photographs of the coin or
key, just as is the case with the Rontgen rays.
The radiations of radium rea< I chemically upon
certain bodies; for instance, they transform
oxygen into ozone, and they change the colors of
glass or porcelain t.. dark violet or brown.
Another extraordinary property of radium is i
to throw off rays not only of heat, but of light
like those of the plow worm or firefly. Indeed, j
th*» li^ht rays of radium are so powerful that it
has been suggested liy French scientists that in
this mysterious metal may some day lie found a
means of lighting cities without loss of energy
or waste of force. The rays radium dash and
explode like minute artillery projectiles upon
sensitive surfaces, and '.heir phosphorescent
properties are astounding. The most puzzling
property of radium is that, as far as has yet
been ascertained, it.- properties of emit) heat
and light are inexhaustible. The great Mys
tery is how and where the ambient forces
needed to produce heat and light are absorbed
by radium. According to the laws of the con
servat'on and correlation of forces, heat, light
end motion are convertible, and neither Profes
«or nor Mine. Curie, nor Sit William Crookes,
nor any of the scientists of France. England or
Germany who have followed in Professor Curie's
footsteps, have yet been able to prove that the
incessant continuity in the emission of rays of
light and heat from radium causes any exhaus
tion, expenditure or diminution of the prop
PROFESSOR AND MMI CURIE AND DAUGHTER.
AViilking in their garden in front of their little cottage at inilly. Fr?n.«»
(Photograph by Harry C. Ellis, Parls.J
erties bo mysteriously stored In apparently fcj,
finite quantities in tail extraordinary metal.
Radium, rr»>r'- has startling effects cpai
the nervous centres of hum;;n being?) and ..-,!nf
animal.". A glass tube containing one or fsij
milligrams of radium \*h'-r. carried f n tha
waistcoat pocket causes a painful wound in tile
flesh that will require six month- Jo heal. A
glass tut"'- containing a few mfllisrrairs
radium when introduced beneath the skin «s? a
mouse near the vertebral column produced «!»at&
by paralysis in three hour*. Tut^s of r^uia
placed in contact with the back of the nerks ef
guinea pigs kill or paralyze the animals ta a
few hours, according to th« length »,f *jpoto its fatal radiations. M Curie say? that d^ari
to man would probably ensue upon '•nfrin? a
room containing a pound of radium, liaf'mm is,
indeed, an unknown quantity. F^nh we***
brings to light startling addition to its mjs
terious properties, which, as far as i* ;-»-t known,
emanate and originate in itself, and nu-e sci
entists to ask the rjuestiosi. "Can it (XMtsltli
that Professor and Mn»*\ Curie have i<. r.i.ttas!
discovered perpetual motion?
Professor Pierre Curie, whom it ha.s be«-n my
good fortune to meet on several a?:or.s, bod
at his little cottage, near tlentniy, and In xtt
laboratories of the >orbonr.<>, v. her- h* work*. ;j
a man of impressive individuality. Th<-re is
Irresistible, fascination in he soft bat pene
trating gTance Oi bis large hazel whicll
seem to emit rays of intelligence akin to those
of the mysterious metal which he and his tal
ented wife have di?:overed. M. Curi-i is forty
years old, tall and well formed. He with the artistic negligence that is often char
acteristic of men of genius. His beard and hair
are luxuriant, and his placid e.xpr-.5.-;kn of
beatitude, together with the pure antique lines
of his head and face, suggest the portraits oJ
Christ as depicted in the paintings of Albert
Diirer. Professor Curi^ disdains worldrj mat
ters and lives high up in th-i clouds, rapt is
the of his mystic radium.
He and hLs wife are by no mear.s in ,;f!2j*r.t
circumstances. Th-y live in a small ottage
with a green lawn and fruit tr^es in the most
inaccessible southern district of Paris, over
looking the fortifications, far away from the
I^itin Quarter, and also a long distance froa
the. intellectual and fashionable centra of tie
capital. Professor Curie is an early riser. At i
oclock in the morning, ufrer having given hi 3
little daughter a lesson ta arithmetic, h^ jurr.fa
on his hieyele and pedals briskly thre* miles to
the l;\borator> of the Sorbonr.^. in the Ku*
Cuvier, near the Jardin dcs Plant-<, to t!:«
laboratory of the Kcole de Physi-iue. i:i th« Rue
T-honiand, behind the Pantheon. It was the
Fatter laboratory that Profet^.jr Curie ft- M le
fore me a small glass test tub- containing a
gra>lsb white powder resemi'lhig table said. You see. this is radium: The pri.fVssflr,
:o illustrate the fact that carrying radiurr. about
produces flesh burns or wounds, good nat ;r<«li7
bared his left arm arid showed me a d^*p *unJ
that had been four months healing-.
The professor i- extremely fond of hi* little
cottage, with lawn and fruit trf-e= and ki?> h»S
garden. It was in his little garden that re
ceived me last Sunday, and presented me to his
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1903-07-19/ed-1/?sp=37&q=Radium+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Metal+Universal+Light+Bringer+Blind</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>UT
J?
V
y
Doctor London placed a box of radium behind a screen and the blind child Bprang excitedly toward it.
He could see the light.
Bptdal Correeponlesee ef The Euno&y Republic
St. Petersburg. June SO. I made a blind
boy see by means of radium, and the fact
Justifies a detailed discussion of the new
element's properties and the hope It holds
out to suffering mankind.
The radium preparation placed at my dis
posal for experimental purposes looked, at
first Eight, Ilka a bit of ground tobacco,
resembling tho same In substance, and
color.
After I had satisfied myself to that effect,
my assistant, a chemist, asked permission
to plato a black bandago o er my eyes.
I -wore the same live or seven minutes,
when he came tow ard me with, a small box
containing tho ery radium I had creiously
examined.
Holding the box before my cohered eyes
at a distance of from four to six and one
half Inches, tho following sensations mani
fested themselves:
My blind-folded right eye had a distinct
perception ot light, growing stronger as
tny assistant advanced upon me, at cen
timeter stages. (Three centimeters equal to
ens Inch.)
It seemed as It my right eye had entered
Into a light Ephere. yet there were no sharp
pontours or outlines.
J'ei.t tho boxed radium was advanced
toward jnS left eye, which up to then had
but scantily profiled by Uie Ught-brlnger
''and Immediately following the light eensa-
j Hon in my right ee became dim. while that
in my left materially Increased.
I asked tho assistant to place the radium,
paste-board cover and olL into a. small
metal match box, whereupon the experi
ments were renewed, the result being al
most similar. The light sphere observed
was but a shade less bright.
Then I placed my hand oor the blind
folded e e and saw as much as before.
Two friends put their hands over mine.
Result the game.
Here, then, was a light-bearer for the
more or less sightless, tho degree being
hardly of any consequence.
Still blindfolded, I asked my assistant to
point the radium toward my forehead.
Then, too. I perceived the light sensation
described: that is. I saw tho radium rays,
not the boxes holding them prisoner.
Some time later a friend called, who has
a peculiar, nervous head.
Wo held the box several Inches away
from the back of his head, his eyss being
blindfolded. According to his description he
experienced the same light sensations that
had astonished me.
At tho time of writing the above experi
ments have been tried on a dozen or more
reliable men and women, with the results
j' noted.
STARTLING DISCOVERIES
HADE IX DARK ROOM.
We next experimented In a dark room,
dispensing, ot course, with the blindfolding
business.
As expected, the same results were had.
Still later a person possessed of one sound
tni one unsound eye was experimented
with. It developed that the light Impres
sions conveyed by radium on the sound eye
'i'iiI'
ill
were stronger than those on the other.
The left eye of another young person In
vestigated Is minus a retina. The radium
rays made no impression whatever on that
eye.
Every optician will tell the reader that a
perfect crystaUIne lens Is necessary to In
sure good sight. Our experiments fIiow that
a good, healthy crystalline lens diminishes
the Impressions of radium rays on the eye.
It seems to repel them.
The question arose: Can a blindfolded
person, or a person In a dark room, per
ceh o articles on which radium ra a are re
flected? Experiments proved that such Is Impossi
ble, for radium rays penetrate the article,
and. In part, ore swallowed up by It.
With respect to the experiment of holding
radium above the line of the eye. It was ob
served that the lower half of the retina
caught the rays; myself and others had
been under the impression that the light
came from above.
We did not know the assistant's position
till later.
We continued experiments In the way that
tho assistant described, with his radium
box, various flgureB, representing numbers,
letters, diagrams and words before tho
blindfolded persons. All these figures were
Instantly recognized. This latter fact still
more strengthened my belief that radium
may he placed in the service of the blind
with most beneficial results.
With this end In view I thought at first
of playing tho radium raj son tho retina di
rect, but that was an error of theory as
well as practice, for, in the first place, not
one retina of sightless persons resembles the
other, and. again, radium rays play havoc
with living tissues. 8o we were forced to
resort to mechanical apparatus.
LIGHT COULD RE INTENSIFIED
OR DIMINISHED.
To this end we tmployed barlum-platln
cjanlde, and holding sime at a certain dis
tance from the box with radium saw It light
up with subdued yellowish-green fluores
cence, the peculiar appearance presented by
certain substances on being viewed by re
flected light.
The light, moreover, could be Intensified or
diminished by moving tho radium box near
er or farther away.
To the apparatus, figures, writing, dia
grams, eta, may be attached, and after It Is
lit up by radium, tho blind can perceive the
meaning cr characters, the only condition
being that the attachments are of nontrans
parent material, black paper, lead, etc.
Our experiments further show that under
such conditions the sightless eye Is easily
educated.
Remember, though, there must be no side
lights, none other but the fluorescence.
The principle, let me add. Is not new. It
Is the same that enables us to' see the stars
at night, and to see them the better the
darker It Is.
Next w txpertmented with a box of ra
dium placed behind the screen, with the re
sult that on the opposite side an intense
light spot appeared.
The several blind people, under my. obser
THE REPUBLIC: SUNDAY. JULY 19. 1003.
r
foffsd
vation wero able to perceive that spot and
to follow its movements. The radium box
described a circle behind the screen and
the blind man Imitated the same with a pen
cil on a sheet of paper.
Letters and whole words were convoyed
to those previously educated In schools for
the blind in the same way.
I therefore maintain that It will be pos
slblo to teach the blind to read and write
by way of radium, also to draw figures,
etc.
Among others I Introduced an 11-year-old
boy to the new method.
In tho first )ear of his life this boy had
become blind, owing to an affectation of
both nerves of vision.
Tet his eies were still capable of receiv
ing a certain amount of light Impressions!
he can distinguish between light and dark
ness BLIND BOX LEARNED TO READ.
After a week of experimenting the blind
boj learned to make out letters that were
radlumgraphed on the screen.
The letters wero about three Inches high
and some three Inches apart.
To-day my little pupil can read words
composed of letters.
That much demonstrated, tho physiologic
al aspects ot radium Ehould be examined.
According to my own observations. Its
Impress on organisms has three different
periods
The first Is more or less latent, at least
I could perceive of no visible changes.
During the necond period the organisms
teem to be In a sort ot Inflamed state, not
always patent to the eye, yet requiring
close examination.
Tho third period Is that ot destruction
more or less farreachlng, according to the
Intensity of the radium-rays employed.
This Indicates that radium-rajs, when we
completely understand them, will lend
themselves to Various medical purposes In
asmuch as a gradual scale of exposure may
be established, the result depending upon
time and tho quantity and quality of the
radium used.
Furthermore, I ascertained that the In
fluence of radium rays on organisms de
pends. In a large measure, on the natuse of
things coming In contact with the metal.
I have not Vet found a thing, organism
or object that Is not. In some way. Influ
enced by an exposure to radium ras. Our
experiments embraced Seed, bacteria, cells
of animal eggs, frogs-spawn, guinea pigs,
rabbits and human beings.
The latter, ns weU as the rest, showed
considerable Irritation under tho rays. We
have reason to believe that certain plant
and animal seed does not develop under
radium rays; leaves lse their healthy, green
color, etc
I subjected the skin ot a, guinea nig, of
a rabbit and a young man to radium rays
and durlhg the first three days observed
no change; on tho fourth dav the skin
looked inflamed, a swelling appeared and
finally an open wound of the kind known
In. medicine as ulcus necrodlum.
rn
Ji.1 .III., In J
This latter hu so far defied all attempts 1
at healing.
WHITE Mien DIED
FOIl LACK OF BREATH.
A most Interesting observation was mads
on a dozen whlto mice, placed In a glass
Jar -Kith liberal provisions. On the top of
the Jar I put a small'box ot radium, en
cased In pasteboard and metal.
The mice enjoyed themselves for twlos
twenty-four hours.
After that they exhibited signs ot 41
tress. lying .listlessly on their back On
tbo fifth day all were dead,.
Investigation proved that every one of
tho-rodents died of paralysis of the breath
ing ctntorB. "?;X
Itadlum'e Influence) on the skin suggests
that It may be a powerful aid of medicine
m curing Biun oiseasea.
Several of my medical friends, are exper
menting on, the lines Indicated, and on
Lupus tho results eo far have been very
encouraging.'
Another Interesting fact: I subjected the
unfmctilled egg cell of a lower animal to
radium rays, .and It began to develop.
In the case of rabbits I observed that
their coat Improved on the Bide subjected
to radium rayft. In short, I am all together
hopeful that radium may do for us many
things heretofore considered Impossible.
Too bad that It Is bo scarce and expensive
as to be without reach for the poor blind
especially.
Perhaps the State will help them, now
that their futuro begins to look bright.
I certainly think that the blind man's
chances for getting back his sight, or ac
quire It, hae unmeasurcably Improved
since the discovery ot radium.
In this respect let no one be discouraged
by reports of experiments that failed.
Those described by the writer were aa
tlrely successful, and the minutes of the
case axe at the disposal of all Interested.
Eye specialists of all nations should at
once begin experimenting with radium.
C. S. LONDIN. M. D.
L AND MRS. HENRY
M1
lYft NORTHEAST
mkvBBBBBmBSB
IISBkw1kwMbbsbsbwwmwmmmbbbWsSkwwwwwwwwwwwwm
mm WPKMrT'1- r:J &BBB L X4CiH-
Hr k fcJiii. trBbIBm i--!-! z itfi m 9BVaS-4ifKHiiBvM
jVjVM XA t Mi .ssBlL 3m JMMBMMPBtalE ,.'MWry i J AHwVHRBHIBnBBHHHHHHHHHHHH
Hl' i -iBiiffMHsiSMiB-? all iF flFi tIi1rw"m"m"m"BiW
-VaW Haa3HtKBiiwaaaaaaaaaaaaal
BnBHLHBiVaVaiVar JPJBBWT'' r IsVAijViSaiVAVAVAVAVl
iVaBBiVAiVftiVaVi t''-W?KB-itiimiBSaBPBKM
MR. A2TD MRS. BIER AND THEIR FAMILY.
No. 1, Lizzie; 2, Tliomas; 3, George; 4, Alice; 5, William; 6, Henry; 7, Mr. Bier; 8, Mrs. Bier; 9, Joseph;
10, Nellie, 11, John; 12, Frank, 13, Edward; 14, Marguerite.
Boeclal Correspondence of The Sunday Republic.
1 Palmyra, Mo., July IS. There Is proba
bly no man better Known or more 'respect
ed In Marion County than ifenry Bier,
who has the distinction of being the fa
ther ot the largest family of llvltg chil
llli. ..,r
mezn
WW KM
BIER ARE PARENTS OF
MISSOURI.
dren in this part of Northeastern Mis
souri. 1U and his wlfo have twelve chil
dren at their table, all In the best of
health, happy and assured of a com
petence for years to come.
When President Roosevelt made his, re- 2
l"l B
!AS MADE
PWi
m
I
LARGEST FAMILY IN
markabla address on race suicide Marion
County people Immediately thought of tha
fine example which Mr. and Mrs. Bier had
given to their neighbors.
This couple have succeeded In becoming
the owners of several hundred acres ot
-sz
H
LIND
SEC.
F
r
lift
fine Marlon County farm land, and arse
now resting content, while their children
are taking their full part In the activities;,
of the community. won
Mr. Bier was bom In Shelby County, it
Missouri, June 17, IMS, being 67 rears old'
at present. His parents were natives of-
Oermany, who brought hint to Palmyra hv
H87.
He was raised on a farm, educated fn
the common schools, and previous to buy
In a grocery In this town in 1S74 worked!!
at shoemaklng. plastering and bricklay--Ing.
After conducting tho grocery for a'
number of years he turned the business'
over to his son Frank, and his daughter -Lizzie.

He was married to Miss Mary Flnnefaa
of Qulncy. I1L. on September 20, 1873.
With most of ttelr children they noW
Jlve on one of the best farms hereabouts.
Fourteen children were born to thtm,r:
twelve of whom are now Uvlng.
Tho picture of this family contains tha
parents and the Uvlng children, as fol t
lows:
Henry Bier, aged 67: Mrs. Mary Bier,
aged 49; John." 23; William, 5; Lizzie, Si f
Thomas. 22; Frank. 20; Margarlte, 13; Hen
ry. 17: Nellie, IS: George, 12; Edward, 10;
AUce. 7; Joseph. 2.
TOLD IN FIGURES.
TTncle Sam's annual Income Is Jjo8.SS7.US.
Russia has fifty-seven warships at Port
Arthur.
Florida's orange and pineapple crops Is es
timated at K. 50O.O0O.
The birth rate among the foreign born In
Massachusetts Is 52 per 1.000. Among the
native-born It Is 17.
Nearly one-half of tha mortality In the
United States Is from diseases of the
lungs, and 73 per cent of It preventable.
The postal receipts for the fiscal year end
ing with June wero J1,60S,SCT. an Increase
over tho previous year of 3125,632.
Thero are 227 lead pencil factories In Ger
many, which employ 2313 persons and ex
port each year 1,611 tons of pencils, worth
$2,000,000.
Mr. Cernegie's gifts to countries other
than the United States are recorded to the
amount of JS.S61.230. making Mr. Carnerl'Vx
total gift to libraries $44,365,950. j
At present there are about sever Iasn
firms engaged In gem-cutting In the t mak
States, with not far from $3,000,000
Invested. There are probably ah'1
skilled lapidaries at work, earning ai
age, r $1,00) apleco a, year.
8jfet,-;a .-xgy 5gafy.
Tf 't.t-
fr-?-.,. tl
V. -J3
.54 Ai,
-y .H
i'
y.y A
jej j. JiSy-.iAj,</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-12-27/ed-1/?sp=29&q=Radium+Effects+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Metal+Experiment</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
RADIUM'S EFFECTS ON ANIMAL LIFE.
The Metal Arrests Growth of Microbes, as Shoivn by Experiments Now
Going On in Paris.
Paris. December 17.
Radium, that precious ni^tul discovered by
the joint research's of Professor Pierre Curie,
of the scientific faculty Of the Sorbonne, and
his wife, and of which only five grams have
ever been obtained, becomes more mysterious
arid phenomenal with each successive scientific
Investigation. It was Mme. Curie who, by her
own experiments, first succeeded In isolating
radium and olkcting it in the form of a pure
salt From ten tons of pitchblende. LroUKht
from Joacbinstal. in Bohemia, two de.i
grams of radium were extracted after a long
and delicate chemical process. The cost of ob
taining radium was estimated last year at
LSO.OOO franca, or MJOO. a gram. This would
be at the rate of 150,0U0.<-HA> francs, or $30,
000.000, a kilogram.
I called upon Mme. Curie at her quaint little
house, near Montsouris Park, the other day.
Her husband had gone to London to attend a
scientific meeting. I asked Mme. Curie if she
had any additional revelations to make regard
ing the extraordinary metal which perplexes
FOUNDATIONS OF THE LOUVRE.
"SKtrsr jrar-a asawatf rs bs-bs
burled out of sight for two hundred years.
and balMes the scientific world and which defies
all the hitherto accepted laws of physics. Mme.
Curie replied that in addition to the exhaustive
paper that her husband read before the Royal
Institution of Great Britain on June 19 last
there had been no further important develop
ments to disclos?. Mme. Curie is a woman of
a purely and thoroughly scientific temperament.
She positively declined to be drawn out into
any expression of opinion or conjecture in re
gard to any of the practical results or benefits
to humanity that may eventually be obtained
from radium. She refused, for instance, to say
whether she thought that radium might some
day stive as a cure or prevention of cancer.
In response to such questions Mme. Curie
simply said: "Why, I do not know. How can I
tell? I am not aware that anything in that di
rection has been actually demonstrated!" Sir
William Ramsay's announcement that radium
gives off a heavy gas, which slowly changes
into helium and then vanishes, was mentioned,
but Mine, Curie, with cast iron devotion to
truth, would not venture upon any assertion
not supported by absolute scientific demonstra
tion. In reply to my question "whether efforts
were being made to procure radium in larger
quantities than heretofore," Mme. Curie replied
"that the Austrian government was taking pos
session of the pitchblende deposits In Bohemia,
which were by no means inexhaustible, and tha
result of this would be that the future cost of
obtaining radium would be very much greater,
than hitherto— perhaps twice as much." This
would put the price of radium at $GO.OOO,OO<> a
kilogram. The fact is of great importance in
connection with the statement made to me last
spring by Professor Curie, who said that the
probability of extracting radium under favorable
conditions from the pitchblende deposits in Col
orado was most promising.
1 asked Mme. Curie what experiments just
now going on In Paris were of the greatest in
terest. The emphatic reply was: 'By all means
those conducted at the Pasteur Institute by BL
J. Danysz, who is investigating the pathogenic
action of rays and emanations emitted by
radium upon various animal tissues and sub
stances."
At the Pasteur Institute, in the Rue Duthot, I
found M. Danysz hard at work in his labora
tory. M. Danysz is a Polish scientist, and han
for the last few years assisted Professor Curie
in many of his experiments with radium. Pro
fessor Curie supplied M. Danysz with titty
milligrams of radium in the bromure form, and
it is with this quantity of the metal that the
investigations at the Pasteur Institute are being
proceeded with. M. Danysz is a wiry little nan
of highly strung, nervous temperament. II.
dark, dreamy eyes have that searching brill
iancy peculiar to abstruse scientists, lie la aa
Indefatigable worker, and derives frequent in
spirations during his laboratory experiments
from fragrant cigarettes containing the purest
Russian tobacco. On the table he had a large
glass jar half filled with soft, powdered sea
weed, containing a dozen mice of different
sizes, varying from two months to two yean i.i
age. The animals and insects subjected to the
radium rays and emanations by M. Dai
comprise rabbits, guinea pigs, caterpillars and
butterflies. Tests have also been made m Its
microbes of charbon.
M. Danysz stated that "the nervous centre 3
of the animals or insects were extremely ten
sitive to the effect of the radium rays or
tions. The intestinal organs were, on the con
trary, only slightly sensitive to the affects of
radium." It will be recollected that the effect
of radium upon the skin was first not!< bj
Professor Curie during his earliest experiments
with the metal. M. Curie, one morning alter
delivering a lecture, put a glass tube contain
ing fifty milligram:; of radian in his waist' oat
pocket. No particular leiwattSß was felt at
the time, but a fortnight afterward his s kiii
at the point corresponding with the wal
pocket became highly Inflamed and painful, i
wound broadened and deepened, and could not
be cured in less than live months. It was this
incident that suggested the epidermic ezp >ri
ments with animals and Insects. It was then
discovered that the action of radium on i..«i
nervous centres produced paralysis or death, ac
cording to the particular organism and depend
ing upon the length of exposure to the i
emanations. A remarkable character!
til- action of radium upon animal! an I Insects
is the period of incubation— twenty day:; In case
of human beings— which baa not yet been satis
factorily explained by scientific resean b, and
which furnishes still another mystery to thosa
f..r which radium li already responsible. Fifty
inlUlnrains of radium in a glusa tut"- placed
for twenty-lour hours In contact with t:i- Skin
of a guinea pig causes the complete destruction
of the epidermis and of the deimis. Th>- skin
was^lercsd with boles, and the tissue protruded
iv hernia fo.in. M. Danysu elated that Uu»
5</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89066489/1904-05-12/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Radium+Liquid+Sunshine</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99065839/1921-08-19/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Radium+Mine+Hospital+Marie+Curie</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>PADIIJIMI ra
ILJI s?- wijL -JjLil
.oh Piaspaisiili j
IO -wxx s v.3, v .wXw urn ir 1 1 i 1
oir rtl, P.'
V
1 W3akid V-P'fSJ
--agll -a- -II
By JOHN DICKINSON SHERMAN, i
ONCERNING Mme. Marie
Curie and her discovery
of radium, her recent
visit to the United States
and the presentation to
her by American ,omen
of a gram of radium In
recognition of her serv
ices to science and hu
manity the reading pub-lie-
is sufficiently in
formed. Everybody knows that she
was made much of by our dignitaries
that tea degrees were conferred upon
her by our universities 'that. Presi
dent Harding himself made the pres
entation to her in the White House
with appropriate words In the pres
ence of a brilliant gathering of nota
bles, and that a tired and happy wom
an finally sailed away with her precious
gram of radium stored in a mahogany
case lined with steel and lead. She
said she was going to take a real rest
ttnA that aha hnnri In Senteniber tQ
I1UU Mil mmv f w S
go back to her work In the 3arie in
stitute In Paris now that she again
has radium to work with. The insti
tute Uiviaes US wurit wvujjvinw
Nnoa Ana haa ti (In wiL the study
of radium and radioactive substances
purely f rOm the viewpoint of the phys
icist; the. other deals with their appli
cation to the treatment of human ail
ments. She will also carry on an ex
tensive Investigation of mesathorium,
another radioactive substance enough
of this was presented to her to bring
the value of the combined gift to $165,
000. But where this American radium
came from and how it was produced
la another story, which may profitably
be told In this connection. It is espe
cially Interesting, Inasmuch as the to
tal world's supply of radium Is esti
mated at only 140 grams (a gram Is
one twenty-eighth of an ounce). The
Illustration by comparison sshows how
small is this amount. The lower sec
tion represents that made by the prin
cipal American radium refinery,, the
dark section that made by ther Amer
ican refineries and the upper layer
that produced abroad. So, though
radium was not produced in the Uni
ted States till 1913, this country now
has made about five times as much as
the rest of the world.
Whue Mme. uurie, Dy aiscuvenus
radium, introduced a new conception
Into the fundamental problems, of ex,
istence, she actually produced very lit
tle radium, since she was denied the
ores with which to work. Moreover,
she gave It all away to the medical
profession of Europe. A very small
portion found its way to New York.
In 1911 the late Joseph M. Flannery
of Pittsburgh, who had made a success
"with vanadium as an alloy for steel,
devoted his attention to the produc
tion of radium. The ores of other
countries being out of the question,
he turned to the carnotite deposits
of southwestern Colorado, Prior to
the World war this carnotite ore had
been shipped to French and German
producers of radium.
Thfr mining' and handling of carno
tite ore In southwestern Colorado Is
attended with difficulties. The region
Is desolate and practically uninhab
ited. Water Is scarce. Flannery had
his troubles. He had to train new
men. He finally established headquar
ters at the only spring of clear water
within 100 miles; here the Standard
Chemical company maintains all the
offices for Its mining work, transporta
tion and supplies. Eighteen miles
away the company built the largest
radium concentration mill in the
world, through "which has- passed the
ore from which has. been refined more
than balf the world's supply of radi
um. Burros carry the ores from the
mines to the mill, and wafer and sup
plies to the miners. i
Mme.' Curie worked on European
ores which contained about one gram
of radium to every five or, six tons.
Ia the Colorado ores there is about
P
8
IBS
Mm
I is? I IEO. s Tni
'ft" i i I y&fea! -I
f m 'AS I 4 Vri
one gram to every 500 tons. More
over, the carnotite miner is a pocket
hunter. Sometimes the ore appears
on the 8-face and along rim rocks;
then extraction Is easy. More fre
quently the ore is found under a heavy
overload of other material; then reg
ular mining tunnels are run and dyna
mite is used to break the rock for
transportation to the surface.' The
pockets vary widely some contain
only a few pounds, while exceptional
pockets have contained 1,800 tons,
First, of course, the Tcoeket must be
found. Prospecting Is done by drill.,
ing in likely spots with Jack hammers
and with diamond drills. Where the
overlay Is not more than 25 feet deep
the Jack hammer, operated, by portable
gasoline compressors and compressed
air, is the cheapest method of wont
ing. Under other conditions the dia
mond drill Is used.
Hamilton Foley writes for the Pan
American Union an Interesting ac
count of the operations of the com
pany and of the production of the
radium presented to Mme. Curie; the
pictures used herewith are among the
illustrations. He says in one piace:
"Let us follow the various opera
tions from the extraction. of the ore
to the nnal recovery of the radium.
At the concentration mill in the wilds
of Colorado 500 tons of ore are re
duced to about 125 tons. In a pow
dered form this quantity is shipped
in 100-pound sacks, by wagon and,
where possible, by motor trucks, the
65 miles to Placervllle,' Colo. Here a
narrow-guage railroad takes It to the
transcontinental railroad at Salida,
Colo. From Salida it travels the 2,300
miles to Canonsburg, Pa., Just outside
of Pittsburgh, .where the company
maintains its concentration plant, No.
2.
"It should be noted that at the mill
In Colorado, and In the operations
pertaining to it, some 300 men. are
necessary to carry through all the de
tailed work. Also, that when the ore
Is taken up by the Colorado mill,
there is only 1 part radium for every
400,000,000 parts of the ore; but when
the ore reaches the mill, at Canons
burg the proportion ia 1 part of radi
um to 100,000,000 parts of the ore.
"The task, ofthe Canonsburg men
is to reduce this mass of ore to less
than a quarter of a ton, and" In such
a way that whatever radium may have
been In the greater mass will be found
in the small residue. This Is done with
regularity and precision, notwithstand
ing that In the elimination of the 100,
000,000 parts of undesirable material
the Canonsburg plant has to use 10,
000 tons of distilled water, 1,000 tons
of coal, and 500 tons of chemicals.
It should be noted in this connection
that whatever small quantity of va
nadium and uranium there may be
In this material Is saved while this
final reduction Is being made.
"The actual recovery of whatever
radium there may be In the tons of ma
terial handled at these two great con
centration plants is made elsewhere.
When the 125 tons of material that
reached Canonsburg from the mill in
the, West have been reduced to 'less
than a quarter of a ton, this residue
is sent to the radium research labor
atories of the company in the form
of radium barium chloride By suc-
cessiye fractional crystallizations, of
the radium chloride and, at a later
stage, of the bromide, most of the
radium Is obtained In a salt contain
ing over 95 per cent of pure radium
bromide. By still further chemical
treatment the bromide is converted
into the sulphate or the' chloride, and
in th therapeutic use of radium these
two salts'flnd the largost use."
Mme. Curie, several years ago by
general request fixed an int'ernatloiial
radium standard. This is deposited
in Paris and the leading cities of "the
-iporld have replicas of i It. So now
$Ihnn, preparations are measured by
t-omparlng the electrical energy 'car
ried by their gamma rays with that
of tire international standard.- While
radium has still many mysteries, it
may be said for the benefit of the
general public that its energy appears
to be given off In three rays, which
are known as the Alpha, Beta and
Gamma rays. It Is stated thaf the
Alpha and Beta rays are-electrical
and that the Gamma ray is rather a
vibration than a ray. The Alpha ray
is 'believed to comprise 85 per cent
of radium's activity; it travels with
about the speed of light 4nd has no
penetrative power. The Beta, ray is
about 10 Der cent of the activity,
travels with about 1-15 the speed of
light and can penetrate about an inch
and one-fifth of lead. The Gamma
ray can penetrate more than three
inches of lead; when It strikes a hard
substance it breaks up Into two rays
corresponding to the Alpha and Beta
rays..
It Is the Gamma ray that is used
in bloodless surgery. The Alpha ray
does not burn. The Beta ray Is kept
from the patient by a screen that alv
sorbs it. The Gamma ray seems to
have the peculiar quality of picking
out "useless or harmful-tissues for its
first attack; it will harm useful tis
sues only after -harmful tissues" have
been burnt away or dissolved. Radi
um is handled in lass tubes incased
in lead containers. Those who handle
It constantly usually get pretty badly
burned sooner or later.- Flesh burned
oy radium cannot be healed it simply
disappears and Is gone. One of Mme.
Curie's hands has been affected and
her general health has been under
mined by intensive wartime work with
radium.
VA gram of radium makes a' small
thimbleful. Its current price Is $120,
000. A gram is divided Into' a thous
and parts, each of which Is called a
milligram and sells for $120.. Physi
cians who use it have from 50 to 250
mlllgrams." The state of New York
has recently purchased 2 grams for
use in the treatment of cancer.
With radium worth $120,000 a thim
bleful, how is it that the' dials of even
cheap watches can be made luminous
by Its use? It's this way: The lum
inous material on the dial is a com
bination of a most minute portion of
real radium and a special zinc sul
phide. These atoms are so small that
it would take hundreds of millions
of them to cover an inch. As each
atom explodes, a projectile too small
to be seen under a microscope flies off
andl strikes a crystal of the zinc ox
ide. The heat' generated by the im
pact makes a flash visible to the eye.
As these explosions occur at the rate
of about 200,000 a second on the watch
dial, their combined flashes make th
dial luminous.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030273/1920-05-30/ed-1/?sp=76&q=Radium+Rarest+Element+Danger</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Radium Becoming
a Household Aid
Rarest Element Adaptable in Scores of Ways
to Eliminate Danger arid Inconvenience
of Groping in the Dark
By DORIS' E.
RADIUM, tho rnrest clement In the
world, la rapidly becoming an r
tlclo of ordlniry housohold use. It
Is the most valuable metal .in tho world
ono gram, which Is ono-twcnty-clghth of
an ounce, costing $120,000 yet It Is used on
more than four million watches nnd on In
numerable 25 cent Indicating tacks. It Is
so powerful that if any ono1 were to. .live In
the same room with one pound of It the
flesh would be torn from his bones. But
there Is not a nound of It in existence, and
If there were It would not exist In such
rorm. Ynt despite Its power nnd value,
children soon will play with its by-products
ns toys, while their elders use It In a hun
dred different ways.
There Is more than uno youngster already
who will not go to sleep nt night without
having his pet bear with radium eyea beside
him. And corners of rocking chnlrs will
shine out warningly nt night, poison bottles
vll' glow In the dark of the medicine cest,
night marksmen will sight their rifles by
the aid of it, mariners will riu'. more safely
because of It and the late returning house
holder will 1)0 able to find his keyhnlo moro
readily in Its light. Motorists, miners, fish
ermen, theatregoers, hospital orderlies, trav
elling salesmen and what Is generally
known as the great public will use this
rarest of substances as casually as they
wind their watches.
In MilU and Mines.
ilow much commercial progress Is to, owe
,o radium can be measured by Its rapidly
'ii'Teaslng use In fnctorles. mills and other
plants. Many mining corporations have
adopted radium danger signals and guiding
arrows. Radium indicators are not affected
by atmospheiii oniiillon.s in i ic ulni
whlch would make gas, oil and electric
lamps useless. As long as there is darkness
radium is visible. And In addition danger
of explosion Is minimized.
The tr.nrlner has already discovered many
invaluable uses for radium. Especially is
this true in tho case of the man nt the
wheel. Electric lights, oil and gas are dis
turbed by sudden motions and by the cut
ting off of current or breaking of contacts,
but when the compass card Is Illuminated by
radium Its visibility is reliable. In the en
gine nom, too, the telegraph control ist
serviceable on foggy nights and In times of
emergency.
But it is the ordinary householder, per
haps, who ivlll find tho greatest happiness
In conveniences made possible by more com
mon use of the mo. valuable substance In
the world. A minute particle of radium
used In a tubful of solution will make thou
sands of articles visible In the dark. Ra
dium may be used in cellars raisin cellars,
Enlist to Save Fruit Crops
balance to help turn It In favoi oi a success
ful harvest by becoming farmerettes. No
experlenco Is necessary. A fairly healthy
body and the will to work are the main In
gredients of rfne perfectly capable farmer
ette. Don't forget to throw In the overalls,
for they are the unofllclal working badge ot
both the male farm helper and the farmer
ette. These young women who want to aid the
short-handed farmer are part of the 6,000
men and women city seasonal workers who
Lave enlisted at tho recruiting headquarters
of the American .Land Service, In tho Lex
ington Theatre, 571 Lexington avenue, with
the Intention of devoting their slack sumlier
time to farm work.
Early vacationers are especially requested
'o emulate tho example of this growing force,
many of whom are already available for
farm emergency labor. The organization is
fast completing Its service camps at pofnts
where labor shortage is greatest and where
city workers aro to be sent so they enn be
FLEISCHMAN.
booze collars or Just ordinary cellars. Fur
niture that has ft habit of standing Just in
tho path in a dark room can havo u little
radium tack on it and bo signal danger to
unwary shins. Press buttons for lights or
bells nro Illuminated with a dab of radium,
Telephones can bo Illuminated, and countless
other things for which tho householder Is
always groping In tho dark.
.What tho sportsmen will do with radium
is especially Interesting. Fishermen have
found that n radium bait Is especially effec
tive. Radium sighted rides nnd pistols
make It possible to shoot with accuracy In
tho durk. Motorists have discovered sev
eral ufles for radium, including tho Illumi
nating of gusoleno gauges, timepieces,
speedometers and other things. The motor
cyclo speedometer Illuminated with radium
Is practically the only one that Is possible
to rend nt night, slnco a motorcyclo does
not curry Instrument lights. As to air
plane Instruments, practlcnlly nil of them
during tho war were Illuminated with
radium.
Radium Uied in War.
Radium received Its greatest impetus as a
commerchU nnd generally useful article dur
ing tho war. The popularity of radium
Illuminated watches needs no mentioning
Its usefulness to army surgeons Is a chapter
In Itself. RndlUm is used in the treatment
for cancer, tumors nnd other diseases It
also Is'establlshed that the curative propert.,
of radium was recognized even before ra
dium Itself was known to bo tho source nf
the cure. Those great baths of Europe to
which people from all over the world Hooked
to gain relief from nil sorts of miseries were
In reality radium baths, for It is now known
that spring waters contain radium and that
to this fact Is due a great part or then
curative properties.
Predictions as to tho future usage ot
radium border on the fairy tale, for In spite
of the fact that it costs more than $3,000,
000 an ounce and there Is less than a pound
of It in the world, the marvellous 'property
of radium makes this small quantity stretch
limltlessly In usefulness. For not only Is
the radium Itself used, but the radium
emanations possess all the radio- activities
of radium, although without Its permanence
So great Is the power of radium that ac
cording to Sir Oliver Lodge "the power
emitted during the dlsappenranco of a grain
would be enough tfi raise the temperature
of a ton of water from tho freezing to the
boiling point. But this would take about a
year'
He' also says "once an hour ono out of
30.000,000 atoms goes off with violence," and
the speed of this is ho great that a particle
could travel 3,000 miles In one-quarter ol
u second. If we could utilize all the energy
that is inherent in radium there would
probably be no more use for coal, electricity
or any of tho other heaters or energizers
ucd in this world.
distributed to the neighboring farmers. But
in the meantime, which means right now,
scores are being placed each week by direct
correspondence or personal Interview at the
recruiting headquarters.
And In this respect It is also "up to the
farmers" to get In touch with the American
Land Service at once. Tho organization has
a long list of people who are ready to go as
soon as called on. These recruits have teen
carefully selected and their recommendations
Investigated.
Most of these workers are sent to Northern
New Jersey, adjacent New England and the
small fruit growing, codnties of Westihes
tor, Putnam and Dutchess in New York,
where the situation ean be summed up by
quoting a statement made the other day by
ono of the farmers of this labor-bereft sec
tion: "Tho fruit Industry will go down and out
unless wo get outside help and get It
quick!"</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063539/1910-03-25/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Edison+Puzzled+Radium</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1913-10-26/ed-1/?sp=57&q=Miracles+Medicine+Radium+Gamma+Rays</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Leading Physicians and
Surgeons of the World
Report a Surprising
Number of Cases of
Cancerous Growths x
Cured, Stomach and
Liver Trouble Relieved,
and Even Arterial
Hardening Checked A
WREN radium was originally
discovered public Interest
was greatly excite by the
merely curious properties of this
substance -Its power of emitting In
visible rays which penetrated solid
substances, of rendering various
bodies phosphorescent, taking photo
graphs In the dark, of expending en
ergy without apparent loss and so
forth.
Then came the discovery that ra
dium possessed certain curative
powers. The first results were not
very convincing.' and popular inter
est waned.
Now, we learn suddenly, that
physicians and scientists have for
several years been patiently con
ducting experiments which finally
prove that in radium we possess the
most wonderful curative agent In
disease ever discovered.
Radium has cqred many malignant
growths which''were hitherto hope
less. It has brought back destroyed
body cells to life, It has exercised a
beneficial effect in diseases of the
liver and lntestlner?. nnd It Is now
even said to bafillng disease, hardening of the ar
teries'.
In the early days of radium the
effects of treatment were very con*
tradlctory. Sometimes a marked
aggravation of the disease was ob
cerved, sometimes the radium pro
duced serious Injury on healthy tis
sue. But in many cases there was a
surprising and unaccountable cure
of a malignant gTowth.
The reasons of this uncertainty
are now understood. Radium emits
three kinds of rays," which have very
different properties. It also emits
emanations, but that is another
story. The three kinds of rays arS
called alpha, bets and gamma rays,
after the first three letters of the
Greek alphabet.
The most distinguished scientists
In the world, including Madame
Curie, the discoverer of radium, Sir
William Crookes, Sir William Ram
say, Professors Soddy and Ruther
ford as well as many physicians and
surgeons have been absorbed in the
task of studying these three kinds
of rays and establishing the differ
ences between them.
The alpha rays are the shortest,
having a length of about an -Inch!
They have a destructive effect on
healthy tissue. That -was why, In
early experiments, radium often
caused such Injury. The beta ravs
came next in length. They are about
an inch nnd a half long. They have
a stimulating effect on cell growth.
They are, therefore, very dangerous
when applied to cancers and abnor
mal growths, but they are useful in
other ways.
The gamma rays are the longer,
having a length of three Inches or
over. These are the rays that have
effected marvellous cures of can
cerous growths. They check the de
velopment of abnormal cells and
gradually re-establish a normal cell
balance.
The alpha rays are stopped by
glass, aluminum and other metals.
The beta rays are stopped by lead,
hut tho gamma rays penetrate lead.
A thin sheet of lead will, therefore,
protect the tissues against tho in
jurious alpha and beta rays. These
rays are also eliminated by holding
the radium at rbout two inches. Fil
tration through lead requires many
more applications than distance fil
tration, aB the lead cauEes a loss
e\en of much of the gamma rays.
Radium also produces a kind of
gns, known as an emanation, which
fills a receptacle In which the metal
9 kept. This gas causes bodies with
which It comes in contact to become
radio-active for a limited time. This
f 11 rnishes a basis for another kind
medical treatment. The radio
may be Induced In water,
hich is then drunk and exercises a
valuable curative effect in many in
tractable internal diseases. The
radio-activity may also be trans
erred to solid substances and used
In the treatment of abnormal
Srowth As fhe usg of the
costly radium is minimized by
this method it becomes an important
economy in treatment
The alpha rays are charged with
particles of positive electrlcitv, the
u-hn/A?'6 W,th negative electrlcitv
charged'af\TamenPrr?ntly DOt
radium ray. thro?
flc"B^hrgrMwh"0
ith an Instrument called tho
The" bnamhC0He U 13 posslb,e to watch
the bombardment of countless t n
fhp?S produced b>" radium. When
these are put under the influence of
let thrJS-m*finet, U 18 ')0sslbhe
j.i?V.hi'^bZ
tPriHdaai1Pbaartr|nVf hah6 a 8tr?D^ haC"
lenciaai action when thev ar?
ir*"?"? contact with
disease germs. This is why radium
"hen held too near, destrovs healthv
"SnshS 3'hYhen a th,n sheet of
it eld hetween the radium and
appeal1'th6 bacterlc,dal action dis
cutrat,Vfi effect of radium on
gnafi growths is not due to its
ThteHth or eerm-killing power.
Thhl the opinion of Dr. Robert
0tuer hlgh authorities. In
teHrin/i ?a"&nant growths the bac
tericidal action of the alpha ravs
rp?fit bS *!ln?inafed lo secure good
Their curative value la at
tributed to some Imperfectly under
stood power of restoring the bal
ance of normal cell growth.
The gamma rays have a decided
effect in checking life. When mea>
worms were radlurnized they went
on living as meal worms indefinitely,
veritable Methuselahs," while their
sisters and brothers, unradiumized,
progressed for generations, complet
ing cycles of beetles, eggs and meal
worms over and over again.
There are many ways of applying
radium. One method, shown in the
large illustration at the head of this
P^fu' c?nsists in preparing a paste
with radium bromide and spreading
it upon a metal plate having a long
handle. The operator, wearing a
rubber glave. applies this to the
tumor. The alpha and beta rays may
be eliminated by keeping this at a
distance of about two inches or by
interposing a sheet of lead.
The length of application varies
witn the case. Dr. Abbe speaks of a
case where he applted radium for
thirty minutes to a malignant growth
and it began to retrograde in ten
days. In another case he applied It
for twenty-four horn's.
Two other methods of application
consist in placing the radium in a
leaden tube, open at one end. and In
spreading it on a cloth which is at
tached to the surface ro ne treated.
Sulfate of radium injected into th?
Scientist in the Radium Institute, London, the Chief Centre
of Radium Therapy, Using a Scale to Weigh the
Millionth Part of a Gram of Radium.
veins increases blood production, im
proves the digestive functions, stim
ulates the liver and strengthens the
nervous system. Radiuinized water
has a similar effect.
A piece of radium placed against
the head of a blind person, or the
head of an ordinary person in the
dark, will i-ause him to see light in
which solid objects may be distin
guished.
It is from Ix>ndon th.".t the definite
announcement of the efficiency of
radium in curing malignant growths
has come, although Americans have
had a large share in the achievement.
Sir Frederick Treves, the noted
6urgeon, who made his reputation
by treating the late King Edward,
announced recently at the Radium
Institute in Ixmdon that the emana
tions of radium could be used in
place of the original substance. The
Radium Institute is a philanthropic
institution founded by Sir Ernest
Casael for treatment with this ma
terial. It possesses more radium
than auy other institution.
"Radium gives off this emanation
constantly," said Sir F. Treves.
"The amount of the emanation de
pends on the amount of radium used.
The emanation practically never
weakens. The radio-activity of the
piece of radium from which it exudes
is inextinguishable."
As a matter of fact, It has been
estimated that an atom of radium
sheds one-half its radio-activity in
2,500 years. The emanation prob
ably lasts for something approximat
ing that time, although its duration
l'j.a3 not yet been calculated.
Radium emanations contained in
sealed metal applicators are now
sent out to doctors tnroughout Eng
land for_patlents who cannot obtain
radium or go to the Institute. A
gram of radium costs $100,000, but
the emanation is given almost for
nothing.
At the Radium Institute many
cureB of inoperable cancers or ma
lignant tumors "were announced.
One woman had an enormous sar
coma of tho collarbone. She had
been informed by surgeons that tho
only remedy was removal of the en
tire right arm and shoulder. A tube
containing 116 milligrams of radium
was imbedded In the tumor for
twelve hours on two cojisecutlve
days. "Within a month alf signs of
tho growth had disappeared. Now,
after tho lapse of six months, there
is no recurrence.
A school teacher, aged thirty-five,
Copyright. 1913,
How Radium Is Used in the Treatment of a Malignant Tumor. The Radium
Bromide Is Spread Upon the Metal Disc Which Is Held by the Surgeon with
a Rubber Glove. The Alpha Rays (Indicated by the G-reek Letter for "A")
in Lighter Circle Around the Disc, Reach an Inch and Would Do Harm if
They Touched the Tissues. The Beta Rays (Indicated by the Greek Letter
for "B"), Shown in the Lighter and Darker Circles, Would Be Equally
Harmful, as They Stimijlate Growth.* The Gamma Rays (Indicated by the
Greek Letter for "G") Shown in Both Circles and Beyond, with a Range of
Three Inches or More, Have a Destructive Effect on the Tumor, and Must
Alone Be Permitted to Reach It. The Distinctive Signs of These Three
Kinds of Rays Are the First Three Letters of the Greek Alphabet.
radium. The tube is placed in., a
porcelain receptacle containing a
gallon of water, which becomes ra
diumlzed. The patient takes three
glasses of this water a day.
At the Middlesex Hospital, in Lon
don, a great institution for the treat
ment of cancer patients, reports
show twenty-five cases of cancer
cured by radium. Sir Alfred Pearce
Gould, senior surgeon of this hos
Dital, says:
"By the use of gamma rays in
cancer of the breast 1 have seen foul
ulcers cleaned; some ulcers have
healed up entirely; I have repeated
ly seen small secondary nodules in
the skin and fascia disappear; I
have had several cases where larger
and deeper secondary growths in
volving muscles?, ribs, rib cartilages
or sternum have disappeared, and in
other cases such growths have re
mained qtiiescen! and stationary for
such long periods that I could only
think the radiations bad at least an
inhibitory effect on the growth."
Dr. Robert Abbe, seuior surgeon of
St. Luke's Hospital, New York, one
of the most noted operators of the
metropolis, before the recent Inter
national Congress of Medicine in
London described an amazing series
of cures of malignant growths by
means of radium.
"During ten years," said Dr. Abbe,
Diagram of a Cancer Treated by Dr. Robert Abbe, of New
York, with Radium. The White Dots on Black Ground
Show the Cancer Cells Degenerated Under the
Influence of Radium.
From the Medical Ilecord, Xerr York.
had an inoperable cuycmoma of the
thyroid gland of the neck. After
three series of treatments with ra
dium the enlargement and hardening
of the thyroid disappeared. The pa
tient has now returned to work.
Most striking results have been
obtained from drinking radiumized
water. Out of 100 per cont of ad
vanced rheumatism cases -10 per
cent showed marked improvement,
30 per cent derived benefit, and the
remaining 30 per cent remained un
changed.
Walter A. Brady, the seventy-year
old clerk of Part V, Supreme Court
of New York, reports that he has
been cured of, a hopeless case of
hardening of the arteries by ra
diumized water. He was told that
there was no prospect of a cure.
Threo months ago he began tak
ing a preparation of radiumized
water put up by a Berlin physician.
"The results havo been amazing."
says Mr. Brady. "From an artei lal
pressure of 230 pounds, which is a
terrible one, my pressure has been
reduccd to 150 pounds, not far above
normal, and I feel twenty years
younger. My regular physician has
been keeping my chart, and ho is as
enthusiastic as I am."
The apparatus used consists of a
tiny tube containing a particle of
"I have been able to study the effi
ciency of these specimens of Madame
Curie's radium on more than 75ft in
dividual cases in private, including
250 epitheliomas of all parts; 180
carcinomas of the tongue, throat,
oesophagus, breasr, intestines and
other visceral organs; aO sarcomas
of the skin, parotid gland, bones, etc..
besides goitres, tumors of the liver
and mediastinum and a variety of
naevi, moles, papilloma, etc."
In all cases where he ha/l not ob
tained beneficial results "Dr. Abbo
said it. was due to error in using
the radium. There were three types
of results (1) destruction of tissues
too closely in contuct (2) stimulation
and harmful results, and (3) effi
cient retrograde degeneration of
malignant growths, with lasting
benefits amounting at times to a sur
gical cure.
Since he had understood that the
gamma rays were the cause of the
degeneration of tumors Dr. Abbe
said he had never failed to .obtain
beneficial results.
Here is an example of one ot Dr.
Abbe's many ca.ses:
"A young man had the upper three
inches of the right humerus entirely
replaced by a myeloid tumor ex
panding in lemon shape. Under co
caine anaesthesia a portion removed
by the Star Company. Groat Britain Rights Reserved.
showed mixed giant-cell and spindle
cei! sarcoma. I embedded in the
mass four tubes of radium (total 150
milligrams) for three days, so as to
irrad-ra-te and cross-fire It. During
the eight weeks following gritty bone
began to form in the soft tumors,
and then a bony shell formed. Dur
ing six months a marked increase in
bone and simultaneous shrinkage
has occurred. Notwithstanding some
central necrosis of the soft tissue, it
bids fair to recover Its bone solidity
and strength."
So wonderful was the regrowth of
normal tissue previously destroyed
by a tumor that Dr. Abbe put for
ward a theory that radium has the
power of restoring the balance of life
forces:
"In what does the beneficent ac
tion of radium reside? .This ques
tlon, with many others, still awaits
solution. We know only that we
have a subtle force, which, as far as
we discern, is a stream of rays
charged with negative electricity
with intense penetrating power,
capable of traversing stone, human
flesh, or solid steel with facility,
which plays upon the vital cells
(animal or vegetable) and alters
their rate of growth or kills them
altogether.
"What the vlt^l spark is in a liv
ing thing no one knows. It has been
surmised that life itself may only be
an embodiment of electric force. It
has been supposed by some that a
living cell continues its normal ca
reer owing to a balance established
within it between positive and nega
tive eleqtric force, and that an ag
gregate mass of colls in the body,
such as constitutes a tumor, may
result from their erratic growth
owing to a loss of balance of elec
tric equilibrium. May it not be rea
sonable to suppose that a mild ap
plication of radium emitting its dis
tinctive rays is thereby capable of
restoring the electric equilibrium,
while on the other hand a prolonged
and intense application carries the
balance to a destructive terminal
tion?
?"Consider for a moment that re
markable case you have seen of the
tumor of the eyelid. It had displaced
the normal skin and mucous mem
brane, and grown In bulk many
times the size of tissues that had
been lost in It. There was no sem
blance of an eyelid in the. mass
whose tuberous growth rose in
heaped-up masses on the skin, and
within, and on the edge.
"A cross section would have
shown no vestige of former tissues
which were destroyed or lost in the
mass. Yet, when retrograde was fin
ished under radium action, behold
the normal skin structure, the nor
mal glands and eyelashes! The orig
inal cells were not destroyed. There
was a reassembling out of the con
glomerate diseased mass. Whence,
then, came the diseased cells? This
can be answered only by the as
sumption that an intercellular Invis
ible and ultramicroscopic system of
particles had existed with a life of
their own, constituting a network
holding the visible cells together.
This system, then, had itself taken
on an erratic growth and become a
sarcoma mass, engulfing the regu
lar occupants of the ground."
Dr. Joseph Mulr, of New York, has
elucidated a theory held by many
physicians now that the curative
properties of natoi'al waters, hith
erto attributed to the minerals they
contained, are really due to their
radio-active qualities. Whenever these
spring waters have been examined,
they have been found to be radio
active.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053157/1914-03-04/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Wonder+Workings+Medical+Radium+Experiments</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>United States Has
Now a Radium
Institute.
BY MEDICAL WORLD
Scientists Are Busy
Conducting Novel
Experiments.
1
R
i ADIUM. radium—more radium!
This is the latest cry of the
surgeon, for the curative pow
er of radium, especially for
cancerous growths, is now exciting the
medical world. But radium is ex
tremely scarce and wonderfully valua
ble. Gold can scarcely be called a
precious metal in comparison. Gold is
worth but $20 an ounce, while a simi
lar quantity of radium would com
mand the vast sum of $4,000,000.
What is more, there is every proba
bility of the price of radium rising
higher if some of the beneficent work
it has already done proves to be last
ing. Reference is made to what it has
accomplished so far in battling with
sinister cancer and to what it has
wrought toward a return to health in
lesser maladies.
Radium fetches today at least $120,
000 a gram, and the world over during
the last year probably not more than
a total of sixteen grains were extract
ed from the hundreds of tons of raw
material worked for that purpose. Of
this amount about three-fourths had its
origin in the United States, and yet
today relatively little of this new found
curutive agent is in the possession of
American hospitals, physicians and
laboratories. Foreigners draw the vast
bulk of the mother substance from
the mines in this country.
How to produce more radium is ono
of the burning questions of the day,
and this country is particularly inter
ested in conserving its resources in
this direction and producing radium
for home consumption. Secretary of
the Interior Lane proposes to with
draw all lands of the public domain
believed to contain radium that their
precious deposits may be secured for
the public good and not become the
subject of private speculation.
He has urged the passage of a joint
congressional resolution empowering
the president to make the withdrawals.
By the terms of the proposed résolu
Photo by American Press Association.
MARIS CURIE, DIBCOVERQlt OF RA
D1UM, IM HER LABORATORY.
tlon the secretary of the interior would
be authorized "to conduct exporations
and researches with a view to deter
mining the practicability of develop
ing from such ores a supply of radium
and to provide for the mining and
treatment of radium bearing ores in
such manner as would best secure a
supply of radium for the use of the
government of the United States and
the hospitals of this country."
Secretary Lane points out that there
are only two grains of radium in the
United States at present and says:
"Radium is fouiid in ores carrying
oranium and vanadium, which are
used extensively in the arts, and proc
esses by which it is extracted are se
cret A process has been invented by
the chemists in our bureau of mines
which promises, from the laboratory
experiments thus far made, to be suc
cessful. Under the endowment of two
Americans, a building is now being
erected in Denver (which, with its
equipment will be opened for work in
the coming February), in which an
effort will be made to prove the com
mercial possibility of this American
process. If successful this process will
be given to the world, and all of the
radium secured over and above a small
minimum will be the property of the
United States and will be put into the
bands of the United States public
health service for public use.
"Under all these circumstances, it
seems to me that the only prudent
course that the United States can fol
low is to withdraw such of its lands
as are supiiosed to contain radium
from public entry. This will guard
agalnBt these lands being taken up by
those who would not put them to their
highest and most beneficial use."
The building being erected in Den
ver referred to by Secretary Lane is
that of the American National Radium
institute, which has been incorporated
and endowed by Dr. Howard Kelly of
Baltimore and Dr. James Douglas of
Aew York city, together with, as an
incorporator and president. Dr. Charles
L. Parsons of the United States bu
reau of mines and chief of the division
of mineral technology. The institute
is co-operating with the bureau of
mines. It was Dr. Kelly who treated
Representative Bremner of New Jersey.
Dr. Kelly has expressed himself as not
believing that radium will eradicate
cancer, at least in the near future, but
he is satisfied that it will be an excel
lent helpmate for surgery and that In
some cases radium, as it is now ap
plied. may suffice to bring about cures.
The American National Radium In
stitute, if the hopes of its organizers
be realized, will be richer in radium
than any other institute of the sort.
The Radium institute of Vienna owns
about two and one-half grams of radi
PIECES OF BADIUH BEARING ORE.
um salts, obtained well nigh exclu
sively from the famous pitchblende of
the mines at Joachimstbal. In Paris
Mme. Curie's laboratory boasts some
thing like one gram of radium, and
this will be transferred to the new
Radium institute, and the Radium in
stitute in London bas at its disposi
tion somewhere between one and two
grams of radium chloride. And yet
wonders have been worked already
with these extremely small quantities.
For instance, the Loudon Radium in
stitute treated during a period of near
ly sixteen un nths a total of 61U pa
tients. Out of these fifty-three were
apparently cured, twenty-eight were
declared cured and 245 were pronounc
ed improved. There were, however,
seventy sufferers not improved, eighty
eight abandoned the treatment, and flf
ty-flve died. At the time of the report
the remaining forty-one cases had been
too recently treated for the announce
ment of definite results.
The patients were afflicted with a
large number of diseases, but the ma
jority of them were suffering from ul
cers, tumors, cancers and oilier ma
lignant maladies, and iu the light of
recent information it is probable that
of the 245 "improved" many might
have been classed among the "cured"
or "apparently cured" had the resi
dent physicians had at their disposi
tion a larger quantity of radium.
It was Mme. Marie Curie who, in con
junction with her husband, Professor
Curle, since dead, discovered radium
In 1888. She is now at the head of the
Radium institute at Paris.
The discovery of radium led to the
finding of thirty-eight radio-active bod
ies. Some disappear so soon that they
cannot be examined; others can last a
billion years, in spite of all efforts,
such ab beating it to 1,500 degrees of
warmth and cooling it to minus 180
degrees, Mme. Curie says she has not
NEW BADICM INSTITUTE AT PARIS.
been able yet to break up radium into
other component elements. She is still
trying.
The experiments of scientists with
radium brings us to one of the most
interesting aspects of the vital ques
tion of supply. The physicist knows
that uranium, the parent of radium,
disintegrates in 12,000,000.000 years
and during this incomprehensible pe
riod of time produces, through various
intermediate substances, the precious
mineral we now seek. What the wiz
ard of chemistry is now trying to do
is to convert uranium into radium
within an interval of only mouths
If he can do this—and there are ex
perts that believe it possible—then, in
stead of having to wait for the ages to
work this metamorphosis, man may
transmute uranium into radium and
produce in much larger quantities this
marvelous healing agency.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024827/1918-09-08/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Radium+Paint+Scarce</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>RADIUM
MAY
SOON
New Yorks Latest Successes-Pretty Girls-Class Costumes
OWN JASS ORCHESTRA
Change of Program Wednesday and Thursdays.
BE MORE SCARCE!
Everything New But the Pretty Girls
IN
REV EW WANT ADS BRING
RESULTS.
A shortage of radium was forecast
t-.y Dr. Richard B. Sloore of the United
.States bureau of mines in an address
I he deiivc red at Cripple Creek, Colo,
Wednesday, before the annual meet
!in of the American Institute of Min
ing Engineers. Radium is largely be-'
i in-, use J on the faces of watches and
clocks and other similar purposes, the
TWO SHOWS EVERY NIGHT, 7 AND 9.
i
(Including War Tax)
LOWER FLOOR, SGc; BALCONY, 35c
1 w,
tiffirt
113 jr. r-i S
Give the
miners
a Chance to
ia of
MR. BUSINESS MAN
go to the booth when you come to work in the morning. Then send your clerlc3
to the polling places during the morning.
MR, PROFESSIONAL MAN
don't wait until mid-day before voting. Take advantage of the early morning
when the polls are net rushed.
MR. AND MRS. CLERK
ask your employer to release you early in the day so you can vole. Then get
ycur bullet in the box as soon as possible.
i.'iRZ. HOUSEWIFE
when your breakfast dishes are washed and the house is dusted, go to the pells.
Dor.'t wait till afternoon. If possible go with your husband, or son, or daughter, wher.
they Ipave early in the morning.
EVERYONE
remember the boys in the mines. Make the work a3 fasy for the election offi
cers S3 possible. The rush hours at the polls are from 4 to 6 o'clock p. m. Get your
vols in before that time.
REi'viEMULR THE BOYS ON DAY SHIFT
clear the polling places bctcrc 4 p. m.io the day shift can vote.
V iJ tij jiJf JUL I j
ote Early
WARREN DISTRICT SUTTER CLUB
sj caker said, according to Associated
j I rrss reports.
j "It is a great pity that our supply of
radium is being disseminated in this
'manner." said Dr. Moore. "Hut as the
physicians and surgeons of the country i
re not pun basing enough radium to
make the industry a financial sucees-i,
it is n itnra'. that the manufacturers
.should take other means of creating a
duiia:i(l. The day is n! far distant,
i:i my j'idsmnt When we shall gr atly
rr-ret ti:e radium that has been lost
i?; this way.
"liixdir.m has a most decided useful
ness at the present time. Nine instru
m n;s used on :iirplan"s have dials
made iumincus with radium paint; it
is emphned in th same manner for
compasses and gunsiuhts. The tfi'i
clenry of niht firing, with both nia
(tiir.r1 t:nns and enillery has been
greatly increased by the use of these,
1 niiKii's si:,-!;;s. Oih'T use cannot he
r" i;-i. at the resc.it time, in pub
lic papers.
"It Is 'iilficu't to estimate the ex-i
!t a-.:cun; .f radium i?i existence at'
ti e nt time, probably it is some
wh'T" around three ozs. of radium ele
mnt. Consid'.rahly more than half
the amount of radium now in existence
has com,, troin Colorado and f'ah
cartiotite ores. t
"S'x ye;.r.; ago, the c njanc-'rrs (if iho
bureau of mines estimated that at the'
current rate of production the depos-'
its niiht l:n.t, iiinimr rcinlly, ten or
twelve years. At the present time it'
vry tii'.-'i't ;to ii.t nrc Most
r.f t'! (ieptioit arc owned by live op
einsin; ra(ii;-.i companies. The pro
i( t:'i.n has i.u raised ery greatly
i;i' the v.ar, and I mi very douht
J"-'Vr v cr,:i r -"m upon our
r tv c i s to yield cnmnierci il
cu.m:!'!".-, of its tor core t'.nn six or
sctt! vi" o":cr. It is n-.y judg
n.' n; th ir f'le fields will no' produce
i'"'" Ki.'i au.liUnnal grams of
tadium element at the most if that,
mil"1- T'Mi otild abo'it double the
v.r.rlfi's prpsor.t supply, but, on ac
t'itt rf rim v-r?rr uso of radium In
cviirrr trrtmT.t. such ait amount. t,'
It; r'-irfiti-lllv, would be
'n.i'l in prrrortim to tli probable
(i 'ii:ir.d.
j.r, v-Ui ;2 t!- (!i. :l'-l.
pf ta-ii.ii I; to pro-
r r.MiM'i't.'r.'. Mi -otiuriuin i.; an
xcllriit su' il 1 in ma.iy wavs. Ilr.
hiiif 1 pr;1i d is uvu h sdiorter than j
'hat ot i ,'i'ii'i'".. !i"ii first pt par'-lj
i iii'lnl! in'-rc ip-s In ;ictlvil.;
i :.i,innm ;ind lien begins i
io 1":." it;-, in i ily. A II. r 'ripening' i
1'iv 1 i':ir al: I in:; pif"p:ii'l
i' i i:i l.i- i I i' r I'li.iiinii,;: p;iint just
is f !tr :".:tl- as ra-iinnj. Its usful-!
in -s lor bUih purpose will iut lor
CENTR</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1915-03-23/ed-1/seq-20/#date1=1756&index=1&rows=20&words=discovered+radium+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+discovered+radium%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>CURIE,
Mme. Curie, the world's most dis
tinguished woman scientist, is using
her scientific knowledge for the bene
fit of the wounded soldiers.
The woman who discovered radium
is now working in a military hospital
near the French battle line, where
she has a complete- radiographic
equipment She is said to be one of
the hardest working nurses now at
the "front."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1960-11-27/ed-1/seq-367/#date1=1756&index=2&rows=20&words=discovered+radium+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+discovered+radium%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>"Madame Curie."
1943. Well-acted, beautifully produced
love story of the famous woman scientist
who discovered radium and her husband.
Greer Garson, Walter Pidgeon, Margaret
O'Brien. Narration by James Hilton.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1911-12-29/ed-1/seq-5/#date1=1756&index=4&rows=20&words=discovered+radium+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+discovered+radium%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Prof. Wasserman, Paris, claims
to have discovered cure 'for can
cer by treating tlis'ease with se
lenium and eosin. Selenium was
discovered by Mme. Curie, who
also discovered radium 'and Prof.
Langevjn.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063760/1921-07-13/ed-1/seq-9/#date1=1756&index=8&rows=20&words=discovered+radium+Who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+discovered+radium%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Who. discovered radium?
Mine. Curie in Paris in 1902.</text>
      </result> 
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86058226/1920-08-13/ed-1/seq-3/#date1=1756&index=11&rows=20&words=discovered+radium+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+discovered+radium%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Mme. Curie.
It is reported that Mme. Curie,
who discovered radium, contem
plates settling in the United
States, where she will have greater
opportunities for carrying on her
experiments. One of Mme. Curie's
most recent dicoveries concerns the
employment of a gas obtained from
radium in substitution for tht
actual radium itself.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-queen-victoria/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84022355/1837-08-01/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Queen+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text> The pacUe: t hip Koa
coe, Dtiivrd at Now York, brings l.or.duii papcrr
to Juno 23rd, and Liverpool lo thu d 1th.
The papers arc filled with doqiimmit ami pto
cecdiugs ennncctrd with the decenni of the King.
The interment of his remains vvns to tnliu place on
the O'.h of July. I'or two or three davr previous,
the body was tn lie in Unto al Windsor. The
Court went into mourning on the Ulih.
Princess Victoiin wag proclaimed tiucnii on the
20:li, ami on '.he 21sl thu oaths of nllcgiancu weie
token by the two houses of Parliament. Alltliingn
appeared to Im proceeding quietly, nnd public mnii
ii'cstotions of loyally to the new Sovrcign were ev
ery where (lispla)cd.
News had been received fioni New Vo.K, hy the
Mediator '.o .liiuc -nil.
There had been two more faitutes in Liverpool
of homes connected with the American trnde.
Al Manchester it is stated that there tire -10 000
handj out ofemploy, nnd most
of tho large eatnh-
lishtnontri nro working only half lime. Al Wignn,
which is not a large plnro, there ntc -1000 weavers
totally unable lo get work.
King William IV. was boinon the '21 si of Au
gust, 1 705. lie was colifeqiierilly, nt Iho time of
his dcrith, nlnioM 7VJ yearn old. The Morning
Chronicle of the 20ih occupies livo columns with u
history of his life and reign. Me was proclaimed
King on the VlSih of June. 1630,- two doys nfter
the decease of Ccorgo IV. He entered the Nuvy
nt the ago of 13, nml was in several engage inputs',
in nil of which ho behaved well, lie ruse gradual
ly to the rank of Admiral, vvns a Lieut, of a sloop
of war, commanded in tho West Indies, Nova
.Scotia, dp. Me h"d n lago fumily hy Mrs Jor
dan, all of which have been r.niply provided for;
but 'lis conduct towards tlm mother of his chihlicri
could never he accounted for, ns she died abroad, in
want.The Queen ("Victoria) in her message to Par
liament staled it was the intention of (lovetuiiicnt
shortly to dissolve Parliament, and therefore bhe
deemed it not ndvisablo to preretu any new mcas
urcs for consideration.
Lords liroilfliani. .Molhimrmv (Itrv n..,l 'V.
lingloii.mndf! loyal speeches eulogistic of the char-
nctur ol inn inlo iMnjestv, arid nil of them with the
oxecption or Wellington. Fpoke in n cumilimcntu- I
ry tiiBiiner of the jiovv fcovcreinr.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016924/1840-03-28/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Albert+married+Queen+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MAURI AGE OF THE QUEEN.
The marriige of Quen Victoria and
Prince Albert was solemnized on the 10th
of February ,at the Chapel Royal, St. James's.
The day was inauspicious, a heavy rain full
ing, but immense multitudes assembled to
caie upon the procession.
Ia St. James's Park, the area in front of
Buckingham Palace, and ;he avenue leading
from thence to the garden entrance of St.
James's, were densely thronged before eight
o'clock, and the rain which fell after that
time caused no sensible diminution of the
crowds, for as far as the endeavor of one bo
'y of the eager visiters gave way, their
places were filled by the fresh numbers
which were every minute arriving.
BUCKINGHAM PALACE.
Her Royal Highness the Duchess of Kent,
and the twelve bridesmaids, were in attend
ance upon her Majesty at an early hour.
The Princess Sophia Matilda of Gloucester,
the Duchess of Cambridge, the IYinc.211
Mary, and the Princess Augusta of Cam
bridge, the Duchess of Gloucester, and the
Princess Augusta also arrived early at the
Palace, and were admitted to her Majesty's
private apartments.
THE ROYAL BRIDE'S PROCESSION
began to move through the triumphal arch
at 12 o'clock. The cheers of the men and
the women's fond and audible aspirations of
sympathy continued, until the royal salute
of 21 guns announced that the Queen was
entering her carriage. When she appeared
amongst them beyond the precincts of the
Palace, she was hailed with acclamations of
love and loyalty, which seemed to effect her
so much that tears might better express the in
tensity of her feelings, than even the winning
smiles she wore as she repressed her emo
tions, lite cries of "God bless her which
burst upon her ear from every side, evident
ly affected her.
The procession passed on to the garden
entrance of
ST. JAMES'S PALACE,
by which her Majesty proceeded, up the
grand stair-case, to the Queen's Closet or
Privy Council Chamber, immediately behind
the throne room where she remained till the
order of the procession was arranged in
front of the throne, of which her Majesty
received notice from the Lord Chamberlain.
Prince Albert's portion of the procession
moved first, preceded by the Lord and Dep
uty Chamberlain, who conducted his royal
highness to the chapel, where he remained
on the right hand side, or left of the altar.
The Lord Chamberlain and Deputy Cham
berlain, then returned to ber Majesty, and
harm; taken, their prescribed positions, her
Majesty's procession advanced, preceded by
music, and guided by the omcers of the earl
marshal.
At half past 9, when he entered the chap
el, there were comparatively few seats
ocenpied' in the gallery, and none in the
pews below.
In the Ambassador's gallery, facing the
altar, among the first arrivals, were the
American Minister and Mrs. Stephenson,
the Turkish Ambassador, the Princess Es
tehazy, and Mrs. Van ds Weyhr, Count
and Countess Bjornstjerno, the Sweedish Am
bassador, Russian AinbassadorCount Sebas
tiani;a numberof others arrived in rapid suc
cession, and the south gallery soon presented
a very magnificen t display of cosily diamonds,
stars, and decorations. At 10 o'clock one
of the bands marching into the Palace yard
passed the chapel window playing "Haste to
the Wedding," and while a smile mautled ou
the faces of the ladies, the Archbishop of Can
terbury most appropriately entered the chap
el, and proceeeded up to the altar.
In the lower pew, on the right of the al
tar, were the Duke of Devonshire, with
magnificent nuptial favors, depending from
either shoulder, the Duke of Bedford, the Duke
of Sutherland, and the Ladies Sutherland,
Marquis of Westminister, the Duke of Wel
lington, who also wore long bows of white
satin ribbon, his Waterloo medal, and carried
his Field Marshal's baton. His Grace appear
ed to form an object of such interest and curi
osity to those assembled in the Chapel.
At eteven o'clock the choristers preceded
by Sir George Smart, took their seats in the
organ gallery, and shortly afterwards the
Archbishops of Canterbury and York, assist
ed by the Bishop of Llandaff, Dean of the
Chapel, took their places on the right of the
communion table.
The second pew on the riht of the alter
was appropriated to the Queen Dowager
and suite.
The Queen Dowager entered immediately
afterwards, and took her seat on the right
of the state chair appropriated to Prince
Albert all the spectators rose on her en
trance, and her Majesty courtsied at this
mark ol respect.
At half past twelve the folding doors of
the entrance of the Chapel were thrown
open, and immediately afterward the drums
and trumpts in tiie distance announced the
approach of
TIIE PROCESSION OF TIIE BRIDE
GROOM.
Ou entering the chapel the drums and
trumpets filed off without the door, and the
procession advancing, his Royal Highness
was conducted to the seat provided for him
on the leu hand of the altar. Ilia support
ers, the Duke of Saxe Coburg and Gotha,
and the hereditary I'rince with the officers
of their suite, occupied seats near Prince
Allert.
His Serene Ifichnest wort a field mar
shal's uniform, with large rosettes of white
satin on his shoulders. There was a flush
on hit brow as he entered the chapel, while
his manlv and dignified bcarine, and the
cordial nnd unaffected manner with which
he greeted those of the Peers and Peeresses
around him, with whom he had been previ
ously acquaintM, won all hearts, and many
oi inose around us eitrwr wnti their hps or
heart pronounced that Prince Albert was
consort worthy of Queen Victoria.
The Iord Chamberlain and Vice Cliam
lerlain, preceded by drums and trumpets,
having returned to attend her Majesty.
I ler Majesty then proceeded to die chapel.
Her Majesty wore a magnificent lace robe
nnd veil of the most exquisite workmanship.
The only ornament on her head was a wreath
of orange flowers, and a small diamond pin,
by which the nuptial veil was fastened to her
hair. Her train was of white satin, with a
deep fringe of lace, and she looked the per
sonification of dignity, gentleness and love,
as she advanced up the aisle of the altar.
Trince Albert met her majesty at the haut
pas and conducted her to her seat on the
right hand side of the altar.
Immediately wound her Majesty's chair,
were her twelve maids of honor, attired in
virgin white, while in the centre sat her Ma-
i'esty, "the leading star in every eye."
Vincc Albert standing on her right, and her
Royal Highness the Duchess of Kent, on her
left. A little further to the left stood the
Duke of Sussex, the Duke of Cambridge,
Lord Melbourne, the Lord Chancellor, and
the other great officers of State.
The Archbishop of Canterbury liaving ad
vanced to the rails, her Majesty and Prince
Albert approached him, and the service com
menced. When his Grace came to the words
Albert, wilt thou have this woman to thy
wedded wife, to live together after God's or
dinance in the holy estate of matrimony t
Wilt thou love her, comfort her, honor, and
keep her in sickness and in health and, for
sake all others, keep thee only unto her, so
long as ye both shall live!"
His serene highness, in a firm tone, replied
"I will."
And when he said
Victoria, wilt thou have Albert to be thy
wedded husband, to live together after God's
ordinance in the holy estate of matrimony t
Wilt thou obey him and serve him, love,
honor, and keep bim in sickness and in
health; and, forsaking all others, keep thee
only unto him, so long as ye shall both live?
Her Majesty looked up affectionately in
Prince Albert's face, and replied, loud enough
to be heard in every part of the Chanel
"I will."
The Archbishop then said
Who giveth this woman to be married to
this man?
i His royal highness the Duke of Sussex ad
vanced, and took her Majesty's hand, which
he placed in that of the Prince.
The service then proceeded.
Prince Albert then placed the ring on her
finger, repeating
With this ring I thee wed, with my body
I thee worship, and with all my worldly
goods I thee endow; in the name of the Fa
ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost-Amen.
The Archbishop then concluded the ser
vice.
While the service was proceeding, her Ma
jesty was observed to look frequently at
France Albeit, wao was standing at ber side.
In fact she scarcely ever took her eyes off i
him. till she left the chapel.
Im service ha ving concluded the several
members of the royal family who had occu
pied places around the al target uraed to take
up their positions in. the procession, un
passing her Majesty, they all paid their con
gratulations; and the Duke of Suwex, after
shaking her by the hand: in a manner which
appeared to have little ceremony, but with
cordiality in it, affectionately kissed her
cheek. After all had passed, with the excep
tion of the royal bride and bridegroom, her
Majesty stepped hastily across to the other
side ol the altar, where the Queen Dowager
was standing and kissed her.
Prince Albert then took her Majesty s
hand and the royal pair left the chapel, all
the spectators standing..
After the ceremonv, the procession return
ed through the suite of apartments, her Ma
jesty an herillustrious consort walking hand
in hand, and acknowledged with gracious
smiles the cheers with which the walls of
the ancient Palace now re-echoed, for it must
be observed that the procession passed on
ks way to the Chapel.
THE ATTESTATION.
On reaching the throne room, the form of
attestation took place,when her Majesty and
Prince Albert signed the marriage register,
which was attested by the members of the
royal family and officers of state present.
A splendid table had been prepared for the
purpose, and this part of the ceremony, pre
sented one of the most auspicious spectacles
of the day.
Having remained a short time in the Roy
al closet, Her Majesty and the Prince re
turned in the same carriage from the Roval
Garden of St- Jame's to Buckingham Palace,
and the generous greeting which burst from
me crowds, whose cumbers the pelting rain
had not diminished, seemed to be in a great
measure addressed ti the ear of Prince Al-
Deri, who acknowledged tne kindness evi
dently with deep feeling.
WEDDING BREAKFAST.
A wadding repast was prepared, at which
several of the illustrious participators in the
previous ceremony, ami the officers of the
household and ministers of state were pres
ent. It is needess to say that the taste and
ingenuity of the confectioners and table
deckers were prominently displayed at the
festival; a splendid wedding cake forming a
prominent object of attraction.
After partaking of a sumptuous liejuene,
the royal bridal party set out for Windsor,
attended by the military, on the road they
were greeted by assembled thousands with
the same affection nnd cord ia! its with tlie in
habitants of lite metropolis.
</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85025180/1840-08-01/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Edward+Prince+Queen+son+sons+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Arrival of the British Queen!
The Steamer British Queen, Captain
Roberts, arrived at Now York on Saturday
morning, having made the passage m eix:
teen days and a half. She brings London
papat3 to July 1st, inclusivo the day of her
sailing.
On the 23d or Jilnc.Mr. Fitzroy Celley,
moved leavo to bring in a' bill to abolish thef
punishment of death except in case of mur
der and high trcaBonf Ilo ptefaccd the mo-,
tion with a long and eloquent statement of
the arguments for the measure.
Attempt to assassinate the Queen. On
the aftornoon of Wednesday the 10th of
Juno as the Queen and Princo Albert wore
taking their evening rido. near Buckingham
Palace, a young man named Edward Ox
ford, formerly atposiboy to a beerhouse, tir
ed a pistol into tho carriage in which they
were sitting. They left tho palace at six
nVlnnlc. it annears Irom tho account ill the
London papeis, in an open phtBton, with
out-riders, for the purpose of taking nn air
ing in Hjdc Park, which has of lato been
their usual custom. Tho party procoedod
1 i i
in tho directipn of Constitution Hill, and
linvinir nnlem-d the road lcaililltT 10 it and
Hyde Park Comer, continued their course
a
On the arrival of the. phicton about one
hundred and fifiv yards up the' road, the
renort of fire arms was heard to proceed
fiotn the right hand side, near the palings of
the Green Park, exactly opposite to me oacu
of the mansion of Lady Gordon.
The Prince, who, it would seem had
heard the whistling or the ball, turned his
head in tho direction from whence the re
port came; and her majesty at the samo in
stant rose up in her carriage, but Prince
Albert as suddenly pulled her down by his
side. The man then drew from bohind him
a second pistol, which ho discharged aftrr
tho carriago. which proceeding at tho ordi
nary pace, had by that lima passed him a
little. The reports of both pistols were ve
ry loud, and at the discharge or tho second
several of tho female spectators screamed
loudly. Several petsons rushed towards
the perpetrator of tho outrage, and ho was
immediately s,iezed.
On Monday tho 22d June, Edward Ox
ford was put upon his trial at the contral
criminal court, when tho indictment was
read to him, and he pleaded not guilty.
The trial was set down for the Oth of July
Addresses congratulating tho Queen and her
contort on her escape from assassination
have been presented by the universities of
Oxford and Cambridge, by the Bank of
Enefand and other public institutions, by
several of tho nobility and most of the towns
of the kini'dom
Attempts arc made in tho public prints to
tuin the attack upon the life of tho Queeu
to political account. Connel, in a toner
:,i,-r-rr p )w npyrlniiof Ireland., oayg.
agent of greater vidians than himself."
Ono London print states; In looking at
me Hiuiemuiuo which aro now Uutoro the
public respecting this diabolical affair, wo
aro bound to say, that tltiy toll tremendous
ly against mat portion of rabid Tories
whom we might fittingly denominate Han
overians.' A coirespondent of another
writes from u quarter likely to bo well
infonnod, I loarn that further evidence has
been obtained of a Seerel Society and that
some vital disclosures have been'mado con
necting it with Hanover. This is terrible
but I ha;e no i-cason to doubt its truth.
FRANCE.
Tho Princo da Joinvillo left Paris oh
I uesday wcok for Toulon, and will embark
or bl. Helena, for iwJpuroaa or bringing
to I-rauco Napoleon's remains early July.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1901-01-23/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Queen+QUEEN+VICTORIA</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The news was received with the greatest sorrow at Balmoral, Windsor -and Eton, where
Queen Victoria was regarded in a specially personal manner by the inhabitants.
Princess Beatrice telegraphed the tidings to former Empress Eugenie at Farnsborough.
An incident characteristic of the Queen's solicitude for others occurred two; days ago,
when, in one of the intervals of consciousness, she summoned strength to suggest to her dressers
'who had been acting as nurses to take the opportunity of getting some fresh air. Monday she
asked that her little Pomeranian spaniel be brought*to her bedroom.
It was thought that the Queen was dying about 9 in the morning, arid carriages were
sent to Osborne Cottage and the rectory to bring all the Princes and Princesses and the Bishop
of Winchester to her bedside. It seemed then very near the end, but when things looked the
worst the Queen had one of the rallies due to her wonderful constitution, opened her eyes and rec
ognized the Prince of Wales, the Princesses and Emperor William. She asked to see one of her
faithful servants, a member of the household. He hastened to the room, but before he got there
the Queen had passed into a fitful sleep.
Four o'clock marked the beginning of the end. Again the family were summoned, and this
time the relapse was not followed by recovery.
The Prince of Wales was very much affected when the doctors at last informed him that
his mother had breathed her last. Emperor William, himself deeply affected, did his best to min
ister comfort to his sorrow-stricken uncle, whose new dignity he was the first to. acknowledge.
From all parts of the world there are still pouring into Cowes messages of condolence. They
come from crowned heads, millionaires, tradesmen and paupers, and are variously addressed to the
Prince of Wales and the King of England.
Emperor William's arrangements are not settled. His yacht will arrive here to-day (Wed
nesday), but it is believed that he will not depart until after the funeral. Several other royal per
sonages are likely to be present at the function.
The record of the last days of the reign of Victoria is not easy to tell. Forseveral weeks the
Queen had been failing. On Monday week she summoned Lord Roberts and asked him some
very searching questions regarding, the war in South Africa. OnTuesday she went for,a drive, but
was visibly affected. On Wednesday she suffered a paralytic stroke, accompanied by intense phy
sical weakness. It was her first illness in all her eighty-one years and she would, not admit it.
Then her condition grew so serious that, against her. wishes, the family were summoned. When
they arrived her reason had practically succumbed to paralysis and weakness.
The events of the last days, described in the bulletins, are too fresh to neetl repetition. At
the lodge gates the watchers waited nervously.. Suddenly along the drive from the house came a
horseman who Queen is dead" as he dashed through the crowds..
Then down the hillside rushed a myriad of messengers, passing the fateful bulletin from
one to another. Soon the surrounding country knew that a King ruled over Great Britain. The
local inhabitants walked as if in a dream through the streets of Cowes, but they did not hesitate
4o stop to drink the health of the new monarch. VV'-V. -IU
The end of this career, never equaled by any woman 'in the world's history, came in
a simply furnished room in Osborne House. This most respected of women, living or dead, lay in
a great four-posted bed and made a shrunken atom whose aged face and figure were a cruel
mockery of the fair girl who in 1837 began to rule over England.
Around her were gathered almost every descendant of her line. Well within view of her
dying eyes there hung a portrait of the Prince Consort. It was he who designed the room and
every part of the castle. In scarcely audible words the white-haired Bishop, of Winchester prayed
beside her as he had often prayed with his sovereign, for he was her, chaplain at Windsor. With
bowed heads the imperious ruler of the German empire and the man who is now King of Eng
land, the woman who has succeeded to the title of Queen, the Princes and Princesses and those of
less than royal designation, listened to the Bishop's prayer.
Six o'clock passed. The Bishop continued his intercession. One of the younger children
asked a question in shrill, childish treble and was immediately silenced. The women "of this royal
family sobbed faintly and the men shuffled uneasily.
At exactly half-past 6 Sir James Reid held up his head and the people then knew that.
England had lost her Queen. The Bishop pronounced the benediction.
The Queen passed away quite peacefully. She suffered no pain. Those who '^vere now
mourning went to their rooms. A few minutes later the inevitable element, of materialism stepped
into this pathetic chapter of international history, for the court ladies went busily to work order
ing their mourning from London.
The wheels cf the world were jarred when the announcement came, but in this palace at
Osborne everything pursued the usual course. Down in the kitchen they were cooking a huge din-
ner for. an assemblage the like of which has, seldom been-r-knownanEnglaiid.andtlladitinerprep-*:
arations proceeded just as if nothing had occurred.
The body of Queen Victoria was embalmed and probably will be taken to Windsor on Sat
urday. The coffin arrived last evening from London.
COWES, Isle of Wight, Jan. 23.— Queen Victoria is dead; and Edward VII reigns. v
The greatest event in the memory of this generation, the most stupendous change
in existing conditions that could possibly* be imagined, took place quietly, almost
gently, upon the eve of the anniversary of the death of the Queen's father, the Duke of
Peacemlly and Without rain the Kdyal In
valid at Osborne Relinquishes Her
O f J T T T -I
rlola Upon Laic.
VICTORIA'S REIGN ENDS
AND EDWARD VII IS KING
rial, formula: "The Queen Is dead. Lons
v<» the Kins-'*
Victoria's Jast words were: "My son."
It was a most dramatic scene there' In
the death chamber. The aged Queen,
roused into momentary consciousness,
realized death was at hand. She recog
nized the German Emperor and the Prince
of Wales and sevAal others of Jier weep
ing family.. .Those who were nearest her
heard a whispered good-by and a fond
reference." to -her eldest son.
As the breathing of the Queen died
away and the end came— when it became
certain" death" had taken "her to himself
the officials in the bedchamber turned
from the bedside to the Prince and sol
emnly declared the words of the Immemo-
»_
COWES, Jan. 23 (special cablegram to
the New York j Evening Journal).— Queen
LAST 'WORDS
1 OF THE QUEEN
of the nlKhtly* nRfcltues were in evidence.
The. St. James,- Prince's and other prom
inent-restaurants, have- already discarded
alluring colors for somber black.
Americans who" have passed through
great national calamities may remember
ihe-crape-covered buTTdlng." but" they" can
111 conceive since the death of Lincoln any
such of gloom' as Mas already
fallen upon the*"Unite'd Kingdom. "Mar 1
borough House, so long the home of the
new monarch -Buckingham Palace, where
Queen Victoria made her last stay in Lon
don, "and St. James Palace! the residence
of; so many- former monarchs. were all
black and deserted. Sentries in black over
coat Si kept .silent; vl&ll before the- closed
gates i and bolted dpors. The population
therefore slowly .'dispersed- as- the njgljt
wore on. Shortly, before: midnight an of
ficial announcement .-was issued calling
Parliament. ,to .meet:- at 4 o'clock. this
(Wednesday) afternoon to enable members
of the House of Lords and House of Com
mons to take the oath of allegiance to
King Edward VII.
Telegrams. pouring, in from all parts of
the.'Continent.re-echo,..the deen feeling of
sorrow .pervading a!l .classes. These show
that everywhere bells have been tolled
and publlcperformances' v an'd prirale func
tions suspended.
In Dublin the expressions of regret. were
universal,: The bells of St; Patrick's Cath
edral were tolled.' Earl Cadogan, the Lora
Lieutenant, was absent from Dublin yes
terday, but it- Is expected he will. -return
immediately to preside at a., meeting of
the, 'Irish Prlty Council to proclaim the
new King.
The. Privy, Council will, meet In London
to-day; and the proclamation of the King
will occur thereafter at all places required
by custom.* The" King "win come to Lon
don to preside over the council.
Parliament Is Summoned to Enable Mem
bers to Take the Oath of Allegiance
to King Edward.
-jyr ONDON, -Jaiv.^23. 1:01 a., m.—
ra Absolute .slleitce -reigned' to--.
m night in the vicinity of Buck-
J3 Ingham' Palace and Marlbor
H ough .'Hctisc. A small bill,
'J/Lm^^ signed "Balfour." was posted
outside* announcing the*"de-~
mlse of -the* Queen. -Every
where to-night the 'topic of^ conversation
was what would happen under the' new
reign. 'Much interest is evinced in what
way the enormous fortune of the Queen
will be distributed, the general notion be
ing'that" OSborne" House would- 'go' .to
Princess Beatrice. and that she and Prince
Christian would come Into a considerable
portion of Victoria's wealth.
The probability that King Edward will
take up a practically permanent residence
in Buckingham Palace .-was fl much can
vassed. This Is a question that comes very
close home to Londoners: J Queen Victo
ria's preference for Balmoral Castle and
Osborne -House has been, a" complaint ot
long standing In the metropolis, andjt is
hoped 'that .the new- reign will see a
change in this respect. The presence of
the court in London would give a.bright
ness and *jjayety which have long been
absent.
I Not until Queen -Victoria has been laid
to rest; beside. the Prince Consort at Frog
more :wlU the^theaters or music halls.re
open. Moreover, business will come to a
practical standjttlll. The music in all the
halls and, public places has ceased. Fash
ionable resorts, were 'empty, and .very few
IfONDON," Jan. 23.-^-The /coronation of 'the' Xing, who /will'' assume the title of Edward VU, will
not take place for six months, thougIi hewiU taks the bath; to-morrow. The following semi-official an
nouncement has been mad^in the Westminster Gazette: i
"We understand that the privy counciJ, at which th'e^K^ig.will kakethe oath of accession, will not
be held at Osborne^ but at London, and that his Majesty will -start at once for tie capital." t .V
VOLUME LXXXIX-NO. 34.
SAN FRAiieisCO, WEDNESDAY, JANUARY "S!3, 1901;
PRICE FIVE CENTS.
THES LATE QUEEN (VICTORIA;
The San Francisco Call</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82015679/1901-01-21/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Queen+QUEEN+VICTORIA</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>VICTORIA
Family Summoned to the Bedside in Osborne
House at 3 o'clock This Morning.
Last Night There Was a
Final Collapse, and
a Few
IN A COMATOSE CONDITION AT 8 A, M.
London Momentarily Expecting Announce
ment of Her Majesty's Death.
Prince of Wales and the German Emperor Hastening
to the Isle of Wight Incidents of the Kaiser's
Arrival Sunday Scenes.
LONDON, Jan. 21, 8 a. ra.
Oueen Victoria is believed to be
near ber end. Last evening- her
Majesty's condition became serious
and she was thought to be dying".
This morning- at 3 o'clock all
members of the royal family were
summoned. She was then in a
comatose condition. Following-are
the latest bulletins from Cowes,
Isle of Wight:
"5:15 a. m. The members of
the royal family are still gathered
in a room adjoining- the Queen's
bed chamber. Her Majesty is un
-conscious, and the end is expected
at any moment.
7:50 a. m. The Queen is still
alive, but all hopes are gone."
EN ROUTE TO COWES.
LONDON, Jan. 21, 8:25 .a m
A special train left the Victoria
station for Osborne at 8 o'clock
this morning with Emperor Wil
liam, the Prince of Wales, the
Duke of York and the Duke of Con
naught aboard.
The Exchange Telegraph Com
pany says the Queen was reported
to be unconscious and sinking by
the members of the royal family,
who lelt London by special train
for Osborne this morning.
STOU1 TOLD UV UULLETIXS.
DUpatoh from Cowes that Indicated
the Unit Wn Appronchlng.
LONDON, Jan. 31, 6 a. m. The following
tulletins received since midnight Indicate
the alarming condition of Queen Victoria:
"Osborne House, Isle of Wight. Jan. 21,
12:15 a. m. The offlci-il bulletin issued at
midnight fays that Queen Victoria's con
dition late las: evening1 became more seri
ous, -with Increasing weakness and dimin
ished power of taking nourishment. The
change verged on total collapse."
The Daily chronicle received the follow
ing li??nit:h from Cowes, dated Jan. 21,
12:41 a. ra.: "The Queen is reported to b3
kinking fat. The rhetor of Whlpplngham
was surnmor...! at midnight, and he has
Ju;t arrivcvl Jn ore of the Queen's car
riages."
COWES. Jan. 21. 2 a. m. Her Majesty's
physicians hope she may rally by 5 o'clock
this (Mun y) morning. If she does It is
expected be will li'e through the day.
If she do rot, all hope will be abandoned.
Immediately on the occurrence of the
Queen's collapse- at about D o'clock last
evening a mosug.j was sent to London
summoning the Prince of Wales and Em
Pror "William. The Prince of Wales was
In such a condition of health that It was
utterly impibi? ur him to leave Lon
don at that hour, bet it is hoped he will
start for Osborne House at 8 o'clock this
morning.
The Press .W-LU n at London re
ceived the following dispatch from Cowes,
dated 2 a. re. "Tho Queer. Is in a comatose
condition and is regarded as passing
away."
"Cowes, Jan 21 3 a. m. The worst is
expected at any moment and the members
of the royal family f re now assembled in
the Queen' bed chamber."
COWES, Jan. 21, 3:13 a. m. Everybody is
up la Osborne House and terrible anxiety
Prva!es all quarters, If the Queen Uvea
until Tuesday she will surprise her doctors,
ARELY ALIV
Serious Change, Verging on
Hope Was Abandoned 1
Hours Later.
who have been fearing that she will not be
able to survive beyond 5 o'clock this morn
ing. The latest bulletin, with its fateful
news, was issued too late to become com
mon knowledge hereabouts. The exclusive
Information of the Associated Press, ob
tained an hour earlier, is still less a matter
of public knowledge."
COWES, Jan. 21, 4 a. m. No official bul
letin has been Issued since midnight.
Doubts are expressed as to whether the
Prince of Wales and Emperor William will
arrive here before the end. An enormous
crowd of newspaper reporters and others,
with carriages, bicycles and lanterns, has
collected at the lodge gates, waiting in In
tense excitement to convey the news, mo
mentarily expected, that the Queen ha3
breathed her last."
"-TAT-DSBORXE HOUSE.
Few Details of the Queen's Illness Ob
tainable V Touching Scene.
cowes, isle of wight. Jan. 21, mid
nightYesterday afternoon at 4:30 o'clock
Drs. James Reid and R. Douglas Powell,
the Queen's physicians, issued the following
bulletin from Osborne House:
i
"Her Majesty's strength has been fairly
maintained throughout the day. Although
no fresh developments" have now taken
place the symptoms continue to causa
anxiety."
Later in the evening grave rumors were
in circulation as to the Queen's condition,
and they were verified this morning. A
collapse, or what the physicians feared
was a collapse, occurred unexpectedly
about 10 o'clock last night. Arrangements
were hurriedly made to provide special
telephonic and telegraphic facilities. De
tails were not obtainable at that hour; but
It was asserted that the Queen's condition
was chiefly due to a severe sinking spell
and Increase of paralytic symptoms. It is
understood the physicians resorted to ar
tificial methods to prolong life, such as
are used only in cases of persons In ex
tremis. The Associated Press learns that the
paralysis Is chiefly evident In the face,
one side of which appears to have lost
al! nerve and muscular power. At 6
o'clock last evening the malady had not
reached the vital organs, although It had
nearly caused an almost total loss of the
power of speech. What was so much
feared was that the brain might be at
tacked. REFUSED TO SEE ANYONE.
Keenly sensitive of her affliction and
appearance, the Queen has absolutely re
fused to sec anyone but her nurses and
doctors; and It Is understood the Prince
of Wales Is the only exception to this
rule and that his Interview with the Qucn
lasted but a few moments. Hence., tho
exact nature of the malady Is known only
to a very few; and It is the royal wish
that the public should not be informed of
the existence of paralysis. Arrangements
have been made with a local undertaker to
hav3 all the preliminaries to burial In
case of an emergency.
At 12:23 a. m. So far as her lramediato
safety Is concerned, her Majesty's ex
treme weakness causes almost more alarm
than the paralysis. Much difficulty has
been experienced In administering nourish
ment for she appears quite unable to
masilcate. To this weakness are piobably
due the long spells of unconsciousness
through which she has been passing al
though It is almost Impossible to dlstln.
guiah those from the Insidious encroach
ments of paralysis. For more than a week
the court attendants have had hard work
to prevent her from sleeping at the wrong
time. The last time fhe drove out the
villagers were astounded to hear the clear
treble of the son of the Princess of Bat
tenberg trilling out popular sons from
the royal carriage. Tfcs explanation tj
that he was singing to keep his grand
mother' awake. Now and again die dozed,
waking to tell the boy to continue his
chant which to the uninitiated onlooker
contained a world of patnos.
Emperor William, the Prince of Wales
and the Duke of York are all expected to
arrive at Osborne House to-day (Monday).
The only additional royal personage who
arrived yesterday was the Princess Vic
toria of Schleswig-Holstein, who arrived
during the afternoon.
A SUNDAY INCIDENT.
Yesterday at Osborne, hedged- around
with Intense secrecy, began with a touch
ing scene. Amid the bright sunshine, in
marked contrast to the gloomy skies of
Saturday, there drove out from the palace
grounds a carriage containing wreaths for
the tomb of Prince Henry of Battenberg
In the little church at Whlpplnham, about
ten minutes ride from the royal residence.
Then followed carriages containing the
Princess of Wales, the Princess of Batten
berg, Princess Louise and others, all
dressed In the deepest black. The face of
the Princess of Wales showed signs of the
anxiety she was undergoing The annual
memorial service for Prince Henry, al
ways a sad occasion, was more than usu
ally sorrowful, for the shadow of a still
greater bereavement was uppermost In all
minds. The Princess of Wales and the
the Princess of Battenberg sobbed bitterly,
and there was scarcely one of those royal
beads bent in prayer that did not shake
with a grief which could not be sup
pressed. The departure of the Prince of Wales for
Lcndon, shortly after 12 o'clock to meet
Emperor William was Quietly accom
plished. The Queen had been informed of
the Kaiser's coming and had signified her
desire that the prince should go to meet
him. Rather against his will, the man who
for the moment was practically the King
of England, obeyed his mother's wishes.
It was rumored that the Queen wanted the
Emperor to postpone his visit to Osborne
House, as she did not wish to receive him
in her present condition. Apparently in her
lucid moments, she believed that she would
be able to conquer the dread disease which
had fastened Itself upon her.
"HOW IS SHE?" THEY ASKED.
During the afternoon the long, hilly road
to the palace grounds was crowded with
people particularly young men and wom
en arrayed In their Sunday garb, dotting
the landscape with vivid patches of color.
The local gentry, after church service,
wrote their names in the visitors' book at
the lodge, which contains no signature
that would mean anything to the world
outside of the Isle of Wight. Inquiries
of importance all came by telegram and
these were legion. Hundreds of people,
all sorts and conditions of men, clergy
men predominating, flooded Cowes "with
telegrams asking for the latest news. A
swarm of country people, among them cor
respondents from all quarters, mingled
ceaselessly In the throng that converged
towards the lodge gates. Their inquiries
generally took the form of a timid "How
is she?" addressed to the policeman who
barred all comers, and an Inquirer who
had been answered would be immediately
surrounded by others less bold who sought
the news.
SCENES IN LONDON.
Day of Anxiety and Suspense Arrival
of the German Emperor.
LONDON, Jan. 21. Throughout the
United Kingdom yesterday was a Sunday
of anxiety and suspense. No one In Eng
land, outside the circle of the court, knew
the real condition of the Queen or the
nature of her disease. The bulletins threw
but little light on the universal question
whether death was Imminent. The Lon
don newspapers have not learned that her
Majesty had suffered a shock of paralysis.
Extra editions of the Sunday papers con
tained no Information, but there were
many of the official bulletins and they were
eagerly sought. There were small gather
ings In the vicinity of Buckingham Palace
and Marlborough House, as well as other
centers where the bulletins were posted.
Crowds assembled to witness the arrival
of Emperor William. Apart from such
incidents, however, the customary quiet of
a London Sunday was not disturbed. The
most alarming reports of the day came
In the form of telegrams from the
princesses at Osborne House. The coming
of Emperor William and the news that
King Leopold was about starting for Lon
don Inspired fears that death was at hand.
On the other hand, the fact that the Prince
of Wales was able to leave Osborne House
had an encouraging effect.
Emperor William and the Duke of Con
naught, who, with their suites, left Berlin
at 6 o'clock last evening for England by
special train, arrived at Flushing at 8:20
o'clock this morning and embarked on a
special steamer for Port Victoria, The
government had arranged to send the fast
cruiser Minerva to bring Emperor William,
but he embarked on a mail packet before
rje learned of the plans, being accompanied
by the Duke of Connaught. The steamer
had a rough passage and on entering
Sheerness harbor she went by the war-
ships without any ceremonies. Admiral
Kennedy and Count Von Mirbach, of the
German embassy, received the Emperor and
escorted him to a special waiting room.
THRONG AT THE STATION.
Two hours before his Majesty's train was
due in London people began to gather
nbout Charing Cross station. The crowd
included not only the usual hangers-on, but
many fashionable people and hundreds of
Germans, anxious to see the Emperor on
his first appearance In London for years.
(CONTINUED ON PAGI3 COL. 4.7
BY ALL
ISO OTHER SOVEREIGN WAS AS GRA
CIOUS AS QUEEN' VICTORIA.
And IVone Ever So Endeared Herself
to the People of All Ln n tl na
Her IJritannic Majesty.
COMMENT OF LONDON PAPERS
TRIBUTES TO THE WOMAN WHO DID
SO MUCH FOR THE WOULD.
Her Long: Reign Rcvferrcd and Her
Catholic Urbanity Pointed Oat as
ail Example to Be Followed.
EMPEROR WILLIAM'S ACTION
-4-
CITED AS 'EVIDENCE OF THE SYM
PATHY OF THE GERMAN PEOPLE.
Mrs. May Wrlßht ScTrnll'a Impression
of the Qacen Other Tributes to
the Dyinc Ilaler.
LONDON, Jan. 21. The bulletin Issued at
midnight was too late to become known In
London, except to a very few. If when the
metropolis awakes the Queen is still living-,
her people must recognize that there is
really no hope. This morning's newspa
pers have thrown off all pretense of any
possibility of recovery and they sadly ad
mit that the end may come at any moment.
"While there is life there Is hope," they
say, and the Queen's constitution is mar
velously strong; but it Is Idle to deny that
the danger Is extreme. Therefore the pa
pers proceed to review her Majesty's long
and Illustrious reign as though she were
no more and to dilate upon the wonderful
influence she wielded In European politics
for so many years.
We all know," says the Dally Mall,
"that there is danger of losing perhaps
the greatest personal force of our times."
The Dally News recalls the fact that
even Bismarck, who detested feminine In
terference in politics, formed an estimate
of the Queen, after a personal interview
with her, which bordered on the idolatrous,
and it adds: "This Is one of the most
striking tributes ever paid to a great char
acter." It is worthy- of note that even to-day
the London papers do not mention by even
the most veiled allusion the fact that the
Queen has had a paralytic stroke. Pages
are devoted to the mournful scenes at
Osborne House and to descriptions of oc
currences here, as well as to telegrams
from the colonies and foreign countries
testifying to the sympathy everywhere
evoked. According to the Daily Telegraph
Emperor William, who has expressed a de
sire to be received at Osborne House, not
as Emperor but as grandson, said on hear
ing of the Queen's illness: "I am my
grandmother's eldest grandson, and my
mother is unable from Illness to hasten to
her bedside."
PRAISE FOR THE KAISER.
A bright spot in the universal gloom was
the unexpectedly prompt sympathy dis
played by Emperor William in giving up
important engagements to come to the
'deathbed of his grandmother. "This," says
the Daily Mall, "is calculated to endear
his name to every Englishman; and we
feel at such an hour what true sympathy
means."
The Times says: "There is but one senti
ment to-day in the hearts of English
speaking people throughout the world.
Their eyes are turned in keen anxiety to
the sick-bed where lies the venerable
sovereign who commands not merely the
loyalty but the personal affection of count
less millions. It needs no great medical
knowledge to understand the meaning of
the latest bulletin. We must admit, how
ever, that all our hopes and fears are alike
based upon very Imperfect knowledge. We
can only await the. result and bear the
painful suspense with such calmness and
fortitude as we are able to summon to
our aid. History affords but few examples
of rulers who have won the deep personal
affection and regard enjoyed by our be
loved Queen. Even among those not of
our blood or speech, even among those
who have little that Is kind to say of the
British people, there are unstinted praise
and warm regard for the British Queen.
Were we more like her, were our official
and individual relations with foreigners
carried on with more of her catholic urban
ity and graciousness, who knows but that
we, too, would win something of the
kindly regard testified to-day In every
foreign capital?"
Referring to the presence of the Kaiser,
the Times says: "His presence Is Ger
many's homage to those very human feel
ings and sympathies so uniformly displayed
by the Queen. As such it will be under
Stood here and be all the more honored
and appreciated because it involves a cer
tain lofty disregard of mere politics. As
such we do not doubt it will be understood
in all other countries and it will be watched
with respectful sympathy." Similar testl
mony to Emperor William's touching action
find place In almost all the editorials.
RESPECTEP BT ALL.
The Standard says: "If the Queen were
aware of the German Emperor's arrival the
circumstance could hardly fall to bring
seme satisfaction to her mind. It Is a con
solation. In this hour of national distress,
to listen to the universal chorus of re
spectful esteem which her Majesty's ill
ness has evoked abroad. In the United
States the progress of the patient has
been watched as anxiously as in London,
and the bitterest critics of England have
only words of respect for England's
Queen."
The Morning Post says: "Out of the
most reverent and profound respect for
our sovereign we must stand silent for
the sorrow which holds us. The love and
admiration of her subjects are, unhappily,
of no avail. Ncthij la thers Czxli Cyr,
LOVED
when sorrow is heavy on us, will have so
sweet an effect on the minds of the Queen's
subjects throughout the world as the ar
rival of Emperor William."
The Dally Telegraph says: "A precious
and beloved existence hovers at last upon
the brink of the ere at mystery. A life
of lives Is drooplns toward the valley of
the shadow, and the empire awaits in Its
silence and its sorrow. But beyond the
empire are the unexampled sympathy, con
cern and wonderful homage of mankind.
Emperor William, above all, has expressed
this wonderful feeling, not in word, but In
act. with a truth and fervor of natural
affection which England will never forget.
It Is one of the saddest circumstances of
the hour that Empress Frederick Is not
able to be present. Therefore Emperor
William's presence is doubly dutiful and
at Osborne House It will be doubly dear."
Proceeding to refer in detail to the sym
pathy displayed ln all parts of the globe,
the Dally Telegraph says: ""For the Amer
ican people the character and domestic
example of the Queen have been a conse
cration of the Anglo-Saxon ideal. They
have been regarded as hardly less the pos
session of the United States than of our
selves, and they have gone far to restore
the moral unity of the race and to heal
the worst effects of Its political separa
tion." Shock to Irishmen.
DUBLIN, Jan. 21. A deep and very pain
ful sensation followed tho receipt of the
alarming news from Osborne House. The
newspapers yesterday published frequent
editions and their offices were besieged all
day by anxious inquirers. The shock to
the Irish people was all the greater be
cause Queen Victoria, on her visit to Ire
land last April, gave many Instances of
surprising vitality, and she was understood
to have been greatly benefited by the tour.
The city wore an unwonted aspect of
gloom, the streets being swept with con
tinued gusts of rain and wind. The Na
tionalists have been generous In their ex
pressions of sympathy and the Nationalist
press, on the whole, is respectfully silent.
Only the Dublin Evening Telegraph offers
an exception, by making the Queen's ill
ness the text of an attack upon the South
African policy of the British government.
Duke of Cambridge at Paris.
PARIS, Jan. 20. The Duke of Cambridge,
who arrived here last evening on his way
to the Riverla, received a telegram asking
him to return at once. He was preparing
to start when another dispatch reached
him this evening of a more favorable char
acter and he decided to wait further ad
vices before returning to England. When
seen at the Hotel Bristol by the cor
respondent of the Associated Press his
demeanor intimated that he thought the
outlook was more hopeful.
Pope Leo's Message.
ROME, Jan. 21. The Pope yesterday tele
graphed Cardinal Vaughan ln London, to
express to the British royal family the
feeling of sorrow which all Christendom
shared with England regarding the illness
of Queen Victoria, adding: "The liberal
reign of the Queen, which has permitted
the Catholic Church still to Increase in
the United Kingdom will leave an In
delible trace upon all Christian hearts.
3IRS. SEW ALL MET THE Ql'EEX.
Victoria Received, the International
Council of "Women ln 1899.
Mrs. May Wright Sewa.ll was seen at her
residence on North Pennsylvania street
yesterday afternoon by a Journal reporter
and asked what her impression of Queen
Victoria vras when she met her at the time
the Queen received the Council of Women.
She said: "When the Council of Women
was received by Queen Victoria she looked
happy and contented. She was a very comfortable-looking
woman and was certainly
in vigorous health at that time. About her
face there was one thing which weall re
marked about and that was the absence of
the frown which Is always In her pictures.
She had a very pleasing countenance. Her
pictures with this exception are very good
lfkenesses.
"It was on July 6, 1S99, when she received
us at Windsor Castle. The Queen was
very gracious in her reception, although
extremely dignified. That was the first
body of women she had ever received with
the exception of those who wen engaged
In nursing. The general impression that
we all had when we were in her presence
was that she was certainly a queen In
every sense of tho; word. I can hardly
say that she was Intellectual-looking, al
though she was quite an accomplished mu
sician, artist and sculptress. But she
made you feel that she was made to rule
by her general bearing and dignity. Queen
Victoria's great strength of character is
the most notable expression her features
Indicated. Although small in stature she
did not appear as small as she is.
"Queen Victoria was very conservative In
all of her views. She was opposed to wom
en's progressive organizations in general.
It surprised many of the people when she
received us. She was even opposed to
women entering the medical colleges of
England.
"One cannot overestimate her character
ln the direction of a domestic woman
With all of her state affairs she never lost
sight of her family. She did not believe
in divorces and the influence of her char
acter has given an entirely new tone to
court life In England. Her subjects appre
ciate this fact and to talk to Englishmen
Is to know that they honor her. It Is the
predominating quality of Queen Victoria to
love her domestic life. Through all of
her life she has always done her duty.
This Transvaal war has done much to
break down her health. She has suffered
more than many people Imagine. The
Queen looked forward to ending her reign
ln peace, but she was compelled to accept
the views of her statesmen. There is no
doubt that the ties between subject and
sovereign were unusually strong In her
case.
Churchill May Retarn Ironie.
MINNEAPOLIS, Minn., Jan. 20. Winston
Spencer Churchill, English war correspond
ent and lecturer, who lias been In Minne
apolis for the past few days, is greatly
concerned ever the reports of the Queen's
falling health. "In the event of the
Queen's demise," he said, "the natural se
quence would be the dissolving of Parlia
ment. Whether this Is done in accordance
with a statute or is a matter of precedent
I cannot say. However, those in Great
Britain who know what this would mean
I am sure would not desire such a thing.
There Is absolutely no question but what
the Conservatives would again be in power
if another general election were ordered,
but knowing the facts as I do I will say
that In my opinion Parliament will not
be dissolved. Whatever comes, I know
that the continued policy of the govern
ment Is assured." s
Hr. Churchill left at 7::0 o'clock this
evenlr.3 fcr Winnipeg. If the Quetn dlto
r3 v:lll rttcra to Ürn3 ct cue:.
READY TO
Prince of Wales in London Sunday Awaiting
News That Will Make Him Sovereign.
Returned from Cowes Yesterday to Receive Emperor
William, and Slept in Marlborough House
Within Reach of the Cabinet.
TOO ILL TO OBEY
Daily Routine of His
Likes and Dislikes,
Shooting His Favorite Recreation Brief Sketch of the
Man Who Will Soon Be Known as Edward
VII and Rule Great Britain.
LONDON", Jan. 21. The Prince of Wales,
the future Kins Edward VII, slept in Marl
borough House last night, within reach of
the officials whose business it la to attend
to the formalities Incident to a change of
rulers. The fact that the prince returned
from Cowes at 4 o'clock last evening led
many people to suppose that the Queen's
condition was not critical, but a summons
from Osborne House, requesting the prince
to return to Cowes, dispelled all favorable
hopes. The prince met the Emperor of
Germany at the railway station here and
both will go to the Isle of Wight this
morning, if the former U able. The prince
would have obeyed the summons last night,
hut he was not well. The fact that he was
so seriously indisposed as to be unable to
go to tha bedside of his stricken mother ha?
given rise to another grave portent. Ap
prehensions, however, are not warranted,
for the prince has a strong constitution,
lie was so worried, tired and ex
hausted last evening that he could
not' respond immediately to the
summons from Osborne House. The
most he could do was to promise that
he would leaver London at 8 o'clock this
morning, if possible.
When the Prince of Wales arrived at Vic
toria Station, London, at 4 o'clock, with
Sir Francis Knollys attending, several hun
dred people were there to greet him. But
there was no demonstration beyond a re
spectful raising of hats. The Earl of Clar
endon, and the Earl of Pembroke received
the prince. When they Inquired regarding
the Queen's condition he replied: "You
see they have let me come away."
INTERVIEW WITH THE PIIIXCE.
First Time Ills Itoynl Highness 11m
Talked for Publication.
Special Correspondence Associated Trees.
LONDON, Friday, Jan. 11. Following is
the substance of an interview with th
Prince of Waleä which is to appear shortly
In a London magazine. There is every rea
son to believe It is perfectly ganulne, and
it Is understood to be the first interview In
which his Ttoyal Highness has been di
rectly quoted:
A correspondent who had been privileged
to meet the Prince of Wales on more than
one occasion had an interview with Eng
land's future King, at Marlborough House,
his Royal Highness' London residence,
some time ago. The prince talked with
great frankness concerning himself and
Ids views on various subjects. If any on
ever deserved the appellation of "a buy
man," the prince docs, and there are few
city merchants or business men who work
harder than he does, and even the London
public has no Idea of the quantity of work
ho gets through in the course of a day.
It is only by following a most method
ical arrangement that he is able to do so
much as he does in the time. As a matter
of fact, all his engagements are mad-?
eeks and sometimes months ahead, and
every hour, almost every minute, is mapped
cut for him.
When the correspondent was ushered into
his study at Marlborough' House the prince
was seated at an old-fashioned pedestal
writing desk, the fac simile of the ono
used by his father, the late prince consort,
which was piled high with papers and docu
ments of all descriptions. Jle wore a black
rrorning coat and vest, dark gray trouser.
square-fronted collar, with a white-spotted
black bow tie and patent-leather shoo,
and ln his fingers he held the inevitable
cigar. Hl3 greeting was kind In the ex
treme. It was merely like an elderly busi
ness man smiling a kindly welcome to
seme young and daring intruder.
"Well, what do you want me to say?"
was his Royal Highness' query as soon as
the preliminary greeting was over.
The correspondent launched forth his
questions, beginning with inquiries about
the numerous public dinners which the
pnnce attended, and alluding to the pub
lished statement that the prince held the
record for obtaining the largest sum of
money ever collected at one banquet.
"Yes, that's quite correct. I certainly
hold the record in that respect," said th
prince. "And presiding at dinners, etc.,
for the benefit of charities, especially Ma
ecnlc ones, is almost a pleasure to me.
cr.ly p-rt vrM;h I Co net 111:3 atut
BECCD
KING
A LATE SUMMONS
Royal Highness, His
as Told by Himself.
the proceedings Is If the dinner drags
itself out to a considerable length. That
I do not like, and when dining in private
at home the meal seldom lasts more thaa
an hour."
"I have read many times ln reports of
dinners, etc., at which your Royal High
ness has been present." said the corre
spondent, "that you were continually smil
ing during the proceedings and seem to Da
enjoying yourself very much."
"Yes," replied the prince, a shade of
weariness creeping into his eyes, "that Is
where I act. If only you know how terri
bly bored I am by the' inordinate length of
lome of these dinners and the speeches an 1
how I am all the time longing to get
away, you would be really sorry for mc.
Eut, there I must not tay too muih on
that subject."
"With regard to horse racing and bet
ting, your royal highness?"
"I think racing Is the finest fport In tho
world, and I only regret that It should b
harmed by the amount of. betting which
goes on. Personally, I am strongly adven?a
to the practice and I always ute what in
fluence I possess to discountenance It
amongst my personal friends, especially
when it Is made a regular practice of and
the stakes are large."
"There are many people who thlnl that
your royal highness has a very easy Ufa
of It, and that the hardest duties which
you have to perform are attending state
functions."
"Now, here is some information for you,"
said the prince. "Do you know that I my
self see every letter which is addressed to
me and in the majority of instances dlctata
the reply? When the mall arrives in th
morning it is opened by my secretary.
staff and sorted into three groupsletter i
from personal friends and relatives, tho-a
friends and relatives, thoa
ite affairs and. thirdly, beg.
nd petitions and I makcyi'.
bearing on state
ging letters ani
my business to make myself aware of th
contents cf each. This of iteif Is no light
task, when you take into consideration tha
fact that each morning's mail consists of
some hundreds of letters. So, that thosa
who say mine Is an idle life malign mc."
Asked his opinion on South African af
fairs, he smilingly shook his head and re
fused to be drawn out; but he said that hi
should always remember with the deepest
affection and regard the heroic conduct of
the troops In the campaign.
"One more question." said th cor
respondent. "What is your royal hlghnrss's
favorite recreation?"
"Shooting," he replied unhestitatlngly.
"There Is nothing I like better than a g.!
day's hunt. It seems the. only thing which
takes me out of myself and makes ma
forget the cares and responsibilities of my
position."
There was one more remark that th
prince made which will be of Interest as It
txars on the America's cup. for, although
hto royal hlchric?s ha not taken so much
interest ln yacht racing since the Rritannla
he cpenly confesses that "there arc fer
things which I weuld like bttr than to
see the America's cup come home again."
ai.ih:iit EnwAHD's m:i:it.
Ilrlrf Sketch of the 1.1 fc of the Future
KInjr of Grrnt Ilrltain.
Albert Edward, known for more than
half a century as the Prince of Wales, anl
now about to be summoned to the thron
of the mightiest empire in all history, over
which he will reign ns Edward VI I, wa
hern on Nov. 3, 111. The second chill
and the eldest son of Queen Victoria. h:
advent into the world was frreeted with
great rejoicing. As the frst ehlll of tfc
icyal couple (now the Empress r?owacr
or Germany) had proved to 1? a girl. th
Rritlsh nation was naturally nnxlaus that
the second should be a boy. When th?
Queen's confinement was rx poet cd Prlr.n
Albert sent hi. couriers In hot haste from
Ruchirgham Palace to the various 01?
ratarfes of chuch and state, wTose pres
ence at the expected birth of an heir n
dman!etl by ruyal etiquette. They gath
ered together in the ante-room close tjr
the Queen's bed chamber. Amorg thorn
wtre archbishops and blhop. arrayed In
;lk shovel hats and gorgtous ppron, mem
btrs of the Cabinet, headed by the prirra
roister, nurses and doctors by the score.
Tor four hours this motley assemblage
awaited the event. Their patience was
rewarded. When it was announced that th
he pes and vh hes of a nation had bet a
fuinUe-d. and thai a boy had been born,
there was universal gratulat! Prelate
ar.d statesmen embraced one another with
uncontrolled effusiveness. Cannons from
the ground without thur.dervd- the rri
to il the rurrcusür-r dLtricts.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1900-04-03/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Queen+QUEEN+VICTORIA</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>HE present visit of Queen Victoria
sto Ireland is- the fourth since her
accession to the throne in l&fr. She
was 42 years old at the time of her
last visit, now she is almost 81. It
Is officially announced that her visit
this time is in recoenltlon of the
skill and valor of her officers and soldiers
in the present Boer campaign. General
Robert**— "Fighting Bobs"— now in chief
command, is an Irisnman and- takes his
title of Lord Waterford from his birth
place. Generals Kitchener' French, Kelly-
Kenny and White are all Irishmen and
her Majesty wants to pluck a shamrock
from the soil that gave them birth. The
heroism displayed by the Connaught
Rangers, the Inneskilling Dragoons, the
Dublin and the Irish. Fusiliers at the
crossing of the Tugela and Modder Riv
ers and storming of Kimberley and Bloem
fontein touched, the heart of the Queen
as no other event since the charge of the
Light Brigade at Balaklava in the Cri
mean war. Instead of "hanging men and
women for the wearing of the green" the
Queen directed that her brave Irish sol
diers should be privileged to wear the
shamrock on St. Patrick's day. For the
first time in history the Irish flag waved
over the Mansion House in London. The
nobility and officials of the crown, fol
lowing the example of her Majesty, out
hibernlcised the Hibernians in celebrating
Ireland's national festival.
In recent cablegrams we are told that
"the Queen has ordertd a court garden
party to be held in Dublin In the second
week in April when she will be present.
The Mistress of the Kobes has ordered
for her Majesty a unique gown of Mer
onac velvet with designs in shamrocks
and a sunshade of Irish silk, ornamented
with sreen silk shamrocks, with five of
the four-leafed variety at the top." If
the weather should turn out as unpropl
tlous as in the years 1553 and IS6I when the
Queen was in Dublin she will need an
umbrella rather than a sunshade whose
shamrocks would be likely to run Into six
or seven leafed variety through the action
of drenchtng rain. During her previous
visits to Ireland Queen Victoria was ac
companied by her devoted and dearly be
loved husband, the Prince Cousort. Now
she goes as a widowed sovereign, and
many .1 spot she is likely to revisit will
remind her of the deceased Prince. Her
llrst visit to Ireland was In August. IS4D,
when, with Prince Albert and her four
children, on her royal yacht the Victoria
and Albert, she lirst landed at the cove
of Cork. In honor of this event the name
of cove was changed by her Majesty's
command Into Queenstown just as Dun
leavy was transformed into Kingstown
when George IV visited Dublin. The royal
yacht steamed up the beautiful River Lee
to the city of Cork amid the plaudits of
countless thousands. The Queen was
overwhelmed with the enthusiastic recep
tion she met with in a part of Ireland
which she was told teemed with disloy
alty.
lvfore the Queen left England, the
London Times. Punch and other great
journals predicted direful disaster to the
royal party at the hands of disaffected
Irishmen. According to them, the royal
visitors would surely be mobbed and
would be lucky if they escaped with their
lives. The Queen, with the proverbial
pluck of the Brunswick family, proceeded
on her journey despite the awful predic
tions of alarmists. The same newspapers
and the same type of bell wethers are
shouting danger ahead to-day. Scotland
Yard, we are told, is in a terrible state
of alarm and commotion. Between 'JOOO
and 10.000 policemen, including 1500 plain
clothes detectives, will watch out for the
safety of her Majesty in Dublin. Already
several regiments of cavalry and infantry
have been forwarded to strike terror Into
the hearts of the Fenians who may be
lurking in the neighlwrhood. All the
Queen's officers and all the Queen's men,
especially those of Scotland Yard, •will
pa.^s sleepless nights until she is safely
back on English. soil. It was not on Irish
soil that Queen Victoria heretofore in
curred any danger or suffered any insult;
It was in h«>r own capital— London— and
not far from her own palace. Edward
Oxford, a potboy of 17. in IS4O fired two
shots at her as she was driving up Con
stitution Hill with Prince Albert. Two
years after a man named John Francis
attempted her life in the same manner
and in the same place. A hunchback
named Bean pointed a pistol at Queen
Victoria as she was leaving Buckingham
Palace, but it was knocked from his nand
before he could pull the trigger. A third
attempt upon her life was made on Con
stitution Hill in IS4'.» and in ISSO. Robert
Pate, an ex-lieutenant of hussars, in ISSO
struck her on the face with a walking
stick near the residence of the Duke of
Cambridge. This does not complete the
list, but it is sufHclent to show that it is
in London and not in Dublin that Queen
Victoria requires protection.
Of course, the Queen, in ISGI as in 1900.
would not undertake such a journey with
out due precaution for her personal
safety. Her Ministers saw to it that the
coast was clear and her military escort
suttlclently strong-. Lord Clarendon, then
Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, wrote to Lord
John Uussell, Premier of Kngland that
"Agitation in Ireland Is extinct; repeal is
forgotten; seditious associations are clos
ed up; the priests are frightened and the
people are tranquil. Everything tends,"
said he. "to secure for the Queen an en
thusiastic reception and the one draw
back, which is the general distress of all
classes, has Its advantages, for it will
enable the Queen to do what is kind and
considerate to those who are suffering."
This last sentence is a lurid commentary
on England's methods In dealing with
Ireland. It is on the principle of "Do evil
that good may come from it." Knock a
fellow down that you may show how good
you are by extending a hand to help him
up. Queen Victoria soon discovered that
no matter how disaffected the majority of
Irishmen were tney do not assault nor
insult women. A poet of the time well
expressed the feelings of the Queen:
A thousand anxious cares I had,
A thousand doubts and fears-
Would Ireland meet me wildly slad
Or darkly drowned In tears?
Both fears alike I now reject;
One day has testified
Enouch to Irish self-respect
And Irish manly pride.
In Cork. "Waterford. Dublin and Belfast,
which she visited on this trip, sailing from
place to place on her royal yacht, she was
greeted with marked enthusiasm.
When the royal party sailed Into Water
ford harbor they saw near the entrance
Duncannon Fort, historic as the last stop
ping place In Ireland of unfortunate Klngr
James 11, the last of the Stuarts'. After
his defeat by William, Prince of Orange,
at the battle of the Boyne he abandoned
his brave Irish soldiers and took to his
heels. This was the King who early in
the light, when he saw the Irish soldiers
prevailing against the red coats, cried out,
"Oh, spare my English subjects!" It is
said that the Irish officers were so dis
gusted at his poltroonery that they ex
pressed a desire to exchange commanders
and fight the battle over again. King
James fled to France with the maledic
tions of the Irish upon his miserable head.
If disaffection lurked in Dublin it did
not show Its head during the four days'
celebration over the royal visit. On his
return' to Windsor Castle Prince Albert
wrote to his friend and mentor. Baron
Stockmar: "Our Irish tour has gone off
well beyond all expectations. Of the en
thusiasm that greeted us from all quar
ters you can form no conception." In this
connection it -should be remembered that
at the time Ireland was but Just emerging
THE STORY OF QUEEN VICTORIA'S
PREVIOUS TRIPS TO IRELAND
THE SAN FKAJN CI SCO U A J^L, TUESDAY, ARRLL 3, 1900.
throughout the .Union.
It will be perceived from the specimens of the
whole lot of amendments offered that if all our re
formers had their way we should soon have something
like a new constitution. We may therefore be satisfied
in the knowledge that it is not so easy to amend it as
to propose an amendment. It is better that some
needed reforms should wait than that our whole well
ordered system should be thrown into confusion by
constitution tinkering at every session of Congress.
CAPE NOME
</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86069180/1899-11-25/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Queen+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>VIC'S PEACEFUL REIQN.
The inherent tendency of English
writers and American toadies to
misrepresent facts and falsify his
tory in their efforts to justify Eng
lish rapacity and cruelty is prover
bial. Every war is claimed to be
an unavoidable emergency in the
march of civilization and liberty
and it is sought to give the impres
sion that England prefers ana
strives for peace, that her good
Queen abhors and opposes war, and
since the jubilee celebration of her
coronation she has been lauded as
the kind-hearted monarch whose
reign of sixty-two years has been
period of peace and progress to
England and mankind. The echo
is taken up by our Anglomaniacs;
and on each recurring birthday an
niversary of the good Queen Amer
icans are regaled with praises in
verse and prose of "Queen Victoria'
Long and Peaceful Reign."
Of course, as usual in everything
English, the facts of history are
ignored, even misstated, to suit the
purpose in view: for it is a fact
that the reign of Queen Victoria
instead of being one of peace, has
been a period of war and prepara
tions for war during the entire
sixty-two years, costing England
thousands of lives and millions o:
money, besides the enormous de
struction of lives and property and
cost entailed upon other people
tribes and nations have been deci
mated, some exterminated, if not in
actual warfare, as a result of Eng
lish rule. -The peace of the worTd
has been almost continuously dis
turbed, its commerce aud progress
hampered, its sense of justice
shocked and its humane instincts'
horrified during all the long reign
of Queen Victoria since 1837.
Though all done in the name of
civilization and liberty, it has really
retarded the one and destroyed the
other as far as possible. A brief
resume of England's wars since
1837, and reflection on their imtne
diate and subsequent results, fully
demonstrate this truth. Wherever
English arms have triumphed na
tional and individual liberty have
been crushed, by extermination if
necessary, and all foreign commerce
excluded the right to live and
prosper being denied to all save the
English except where powerful
nations have forced a relaxation of
England's arbitrary and selfish
regime.
England's wars during Queen
"Victoria's reign of peace, 1837 to
1899, cover a period of thirty-six of
the sixty-two years, and have cost
England for actual war expend!
tures $1,395,000,000 and 123,000
soldiers killed in action besides the
thousands who died of wounds and
disease and those crippled and dis
abled, The losses of property to
individuals and the nation as a
whole are beyond estimate.
The wars of England during
Queen Victoria's peaceful reign
were;
1837-1838 Rebellion in Canada.
1840-1842 Chinese "opium" war.
1840 Egyptian ports bombarded.
1842 First Afghan war.
1848 Sinde war.
1843 Mahratta war.
1845 First Sikh war.
1848 Second Sikh war.
1860-1868 Kaffir war.
1862 Burmese war.
1863-1856 Crimean war.
1853-1867 War with Persia.-1856-1857
Indian mutiny.
1856-1860 Second Chinese war.
1862 Maori war.
183 Aahautee expedition,
o 1867-1868 AbjwinUn war.
1873 Ah an tee war.
1878 1880 Second Afghani war.
1879 Zuln war.
1 880 First Trautvaal war.
1S82 Soudan war.
1885 Burtnab annexed.
886 -1898 Kitchener in tht Soudan.
Second Transvaal war.
IRISH AMERICAN, 326 West Green Street
Queen Victoria was crowned, has
been at war almost continuously
since, is at tver in various parts of
Africa now, with war clouds hover
ing elsewhere, and the only certain
legacy she will leave to her beloved
empire is war and causes leading to
war after she closes her long reign.
Queen Victoria's peaceful reign does
npt seem to mean that peace for
which men yearn and pray for,
which lightens the burdens, eases
the tasks, makes smooth the paths
of life, blesses and prospers nations
and tends to that peace eternal when
life's journey is over.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn00065127/1897-07-02/ed-1/?sp=3&q=QUEEN+Queen+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>HONOR THEIR QUEEN.
(LOYAL CRITON3 SHOW LOVE
FOR QUEEN VICTORIA.
•Clieers Hlialre the Ground as She
Passes in the Diamond Jubilee Pa
rade— lJcopie from All Parts of the
•Earth Help Celebrate.
'Wonderful Sight in London.
"The crowning feature of the official cel
ebration of the sixtieth anniversary of the
coro^jUou of Victoria as Queen of the
UtyHi Kingdom of Great Britain and
IrJJfMus come and gone, anil ail Lon
doKi Vagpgra tula ting itself upon the eoiu
ple.V ^uc ciss of one of the greatest popu
lar demonstrations of modern times. A
-relig-lous sorvice of brevity and simplicity,
41 royal pageant of unprecedented bril
liancy, a mighty outburst of patriotism
.and evidence of personal love—these were
the principal characteristics of the great
est day that London has ever seen.
The most stupendous pageant in his
tory, a eoncnur.se of 'the millions from
•the ends of the earth, gathered to do hon
or to the fjuceu and to add to the_ glory of
Jier diamond jubilee parade, has tilled its
jpart without a hitcli and without a flaw
in all tiie marvelous effect. Most impres
sive, perhaps, of all the sights of the great
-day was the mighty multitude of ieoi:e
—'spectators packed almost to the point of
.suffocation into every available niche of
-.the six-mile route of the great
parade.
Eight million souls, representing every
•civilized and almost every savage nation
•on the l'ace of the globe, shouldered and
•elbowed at every point of vantage, and
•the aged queen as she was borne amid
,,.±he throng was given homage such as
L'uu-:10''1 nor Caesar received from
VHl.aiyiiads of the olden time. The pro
•CMSPM'H itself was the greatest, most mag
-iiiiic1'.':t, that ever passed between the
Tanks of admiring multitudes. It moved
in three sections, consolidating as the di
vision moved into Picadilly, while—fitting
•order of parade—the colonists of Eng
land's mighty empire led the van.
The procession moved from. Bucking
ham Palace nearly on time. The roar of
•cheers that marked its course up Consti
tution Hill told the beginning of the story
of the queen among her people, while the
artillery in Hyde Park, by a royal salute
•of sixty guns, thundered the fact to wait
ing thousands elsewhere. The queen had
actually started.
The procession was practically in three
•sections as far as St. Paul's, though, the
"two last, en route to the cathedral, were
consolidated as they moved into Picadilly.
The •••cores of troops and companies
•were literally too numerous to mention ex
cept as a brilliant whole. It seemed like
j^Wthing so much as some stream of bur
sold flowing between dark banks
'in-m beings gathered to witness its
?o a land of light.
Then the first part of the sovereign's
•escort rode into view, the Second Life
•Guards. As their well-known brilliant
•uniforms appeared the whisper ran elec
trically: "She's coming." The guards
•were soon succeeded by Hie escort of
British and foreign princes. Many faces
•were known, recognized and cheered.
'This brilliant escort was composed of the
^flower of Europe's thrones. Following
•the princes came the Guard of Honor. A
•cheer broke forth that seenled to shake
•the ground, renewed again and again, as
5her majesty's carriage approached. The
•carriage in which her majesty rode now
-came abreast. It was built about a quar
ter of a century ago. The body was dark
•claret, lined with vermilllon, the mold
ings outlined with beads of brass. Be
•side her majesty rode the Princess of
Wales, opposite her majesty, her royal
Jhighness Princess Christian. On the left
-of her majesty rode his royal highness,
-the Duke of Cambridge, on the right, his
aroyal highness, the Prince of Wales, who
•was followed by the Duke of Connaught,
-the general oflicer commanding.
Services at St. Pant's
5i"he great bells of St. Paul's broke out
in 'happy chorus as the queen's carriage
Jrted from Temple bar and only ceased
•fliier majesty's carriage stopped in front
©/the steps of the cathedral. With the
estopping of the queen's carriage the pic
"ture was complete and the swelling hymn
that had risen on the summer air from
.-five choristers of her majesty's chapel roy
-al, Westminster Abbey and St. Paul's
-ceased its grand harmonies in one long
-drawn soft "amen." The service was
.aoout to begin. The bishop of London, in
lull canonicals, read a short Collect, af
~ter which, as her majesty sat with bowed
.head, the archbbishop of Canterbury an
nounced the benediction. Then, amidst
vthe further ringing of bells, tho national
--antlicm was sung, and the queen drove on
•into other scenes.
As her majesty entered the gates of
tfhe palace at 2 o'clock a distant gun in
.Hyde Park announced to so much of the
world as was not before t'he gates that
the great procession was over. The event
*6o long prepared had passed into'history.
1 SIXTY YEARS 3
•m
,0 4
A QUEEN.
TVictoria
HE celebration of the sixtieth anni
versary of the accession of Queen
to the throne of Great Brit
ain anl Ireland makes pertinent a review
the career of this great and venerable
Jfraler. this good queen and mother, whose
~tiife has been an example and an inspira
tion to her people.
The story of the sixty years of Vic
toria's reign cannot be briefly tokl. Its
•theater has been the world its actors, in
principal and auxiliary parts, the ma
jority of the human race. And yet the
personal history of the queen has been
-singularly uneventful. It is only when
-one reaches out to the peoples and coun
tries, with which her government has had
relations, and considers the duration and
^importance of those relations that one be
fgins to realize the vast influence Queen
•Victoria has exercised over so many hun
dreds of millions of people.
Only three of Queen Victoria's prode
-ceesors ruled over fifty years. These
were Henry III, fifty-six years Edward
III, fifty years six months, and George
3IL her grandfather, fifty-nine years. But
"during the last ten years of the tetter's
life his mind was weak and the virtual
sovereign was the prince regent.
Sketch of Her Career.
Victoria Alexandrina, Queen of Great
'Britain and Ireland and Empress of India,
•was born at Kensington Palace, London,
[llay 24, 1S19. Her father was Edward,
Way your
whom you have been
and equal 1 »ws,
It. And 1 pray
By the President
M'KINLEY CONGRATULATES QUEEN VICTORIA.
rittFSTDENT M'KINLKY sent the following personal letter to Queen Victoria,
Pwhleh was delivered to her b" Mr. "Whltelawr ljeid, special envoy:
Tn upr Mnipstv Victoria, Queen of Gr^at Britain and Ireland and Empress of India.
ftSat and Xood Frleau—In the name and on behalf of the people of the Edited Ftate*
FreMot Uieir slncnrc felicitations upon the sixtieth anniversary ot your maje ly-s accession
x8f xpre£ th^sonUment Mf my fellow cltliens In wlshlnc for your P'orto'hei prnlonsat'on
nf n. vMitn illustrious and wwked by ad
vane in sclonco, arts and popular
life be irolouifcd and peace, honor and prosperity bies3
been called to rnlo. May liberty flourish through"^
aud your government continue strong lu the anectlons of all
Oodto havo your walo&ty In His holy keeping. Vourgood frier
lent: JOHN SHKltHUN, secretary ot state. WILLIAM
Duke of Kent, fourth son of King George
III, and her mother was Victoria Mary
Louisa, daughter of Francis, Duke of
Saxe-Cohurg-Saalfeld,
and a sister of the
late King Leopold of Belgium.
Before the present Queen-empress had
completed her first year her father diied,
leaving the care and training of the young
princess to the Duchess of Kent, and so
far as the adage, "How the twig is bent,
the tree's inclined," is true, the training
given the Princess Victoria must have
been both good and wise. She was edu
cated under her mother's watchful eyes
and was grounded not alone in intellec
tual pursuits but on moral and religious
principles.
On attaining her eighteenth year a
grand ball was given In her honor at
Buckingham Palace and for the first time,
having reached her majority, she took
rank of her mother. Within a month her
uncle, King William IV, died and as he
left no issue, the crown devolved upon
Victoria.
The following day, June 21, 1S3G, dhe
was publicly proclaimed queen, but it was
not until June 28 of the following year
that she was crovrasd at Westminster.
From the beginning she endeared her
self to her people. She bore her dig
nities gracefully and manifested a sound
judgment in dealing with affairs of state.
A new sense of royalty and admiration
arose in the minds of the English people,
for, it must be said, that the record of
the House of Hanover, to whidh Victoria
belongs, was very bad before her time,
the kingly members of it when not corrupt
being stupid.
In 1840 Queen Victoria was married to
her cousin, Prince Albert of Saxe-Coburg-
1
THE QUEEN'S PROCESSION PASSING THE NATIONAL GALLERY.
IUM
under just
lu the anectlons of all who live under
friend.
M'KINLEY.
ter was established in the public heart has changed all this. Heir relations as
and his death was deeply mourned in the
court and in the nation.
Up to the year 18G1 the life of Queen
Victoria had been one of unbroken, tran
quil happiness. Her mother, to whom
she was deeply attached, was spared to
enjoy a peaceful old tfge. Her husband
was to her all that a devoted and loving
companion could be, and their nine chil
dren were growing up, healthy, happy and
dutiful. All that the world could grant,
of wealth and honor, were hers, and her
eldest daughter had been happily married
to the heir of on* of the most powerful
kingdoms of Europe, Frederick of Prus
sia, a prince whose amiable virtues and
intelligence added luster to his brilliant
rank. In May, 1S61, the queen lost her
mother, and in December caine a far
greater blow in the death of the Prince
Consort. The queen met her bereavement
with that vehemence of grief 6o often
manifested by those who have a life of
unruffled happiness suddenly interrupted
by a greait sorrow. Her loss so preyed up
on her mind that for a number of years
she lived in absolute retirement, avoiding
as far as possible all public and social
duties, indulging her melancholy to the
fullest extent This spectacle of incon
solable grief amid the gorgeous surround
ings of royalty produced a great effect
upon the English people, and gave the
queen a hold upon their affections which
nothing else, perhaps, could have done
and which remains to-day unchanged and
unbroken.
Becomes Kmpresa India.
For fifteen years after t'he death of her
husband the queen did not appear before
Parliament. In 1S76 she again appeared
VICTORIA, SIXTY YEAKS A QUEEN.
Gotha. The union was one of love and
not of state policy and a happy and model
union it proved. The English people did
not take kindly to it at first. Although
Prince Albert was a man of rare mental
gifts as well as personal attractions, he
failed in the beginning to impress his
worth upon the subjects of hds queen.
They disliked him because he was not an
Englishman. In Parliament the wise
heads wrangled over the question of his
naturalization, quarreled over his allow
ance, his place next to the queen, and
over the bill to constitute him regent in
case of the queen's death. They would
not give him the title of Prince Consort
until 1857. Four years after this Prince
Albert died, Dec. 14, 1861, but by this
time the nobleness of the man's charac-
at the opening of that body, but did not
attempt to read her speech as she had
done in the earlier years. In April, 17SG,
an act of Parliament authorized her ma
jesty to assume the title of Empress of
India. 'In 1887 the jubilee of her reign
was celebrated with much rejoicing, with
processions, speeches and flags galore. A
new coinage was adopted at the mint to
commemorate the year. All the poten
tates, governments and great men of Eu
rope showered gifts and congratulations
upon the fortunato queen.
If the queen has set herself strenuously
to any one task in her life it has been to
maintain the purity of her court. Before
her time the English court was not gen
erally immaculate and the same was true
of the continental courts. But the aueen
I
I
wife and mother were a noble example of
what true womanhood should be, and the
very purity of her life shamed others into
patterning after her. On the subject of
court etiquette Queen Victoria is the.
most exacting sovereign in Europe. She
1
mixes AL.BEIIT.
insists upon the observance of every min
ute detail of ceremony, and the conse
quence is tl^at every one who cornea into
dontact with her baa to be thoroughly
drilled in the observance of "forms." As
to her personal appearnnoe the queen has
herself sadd that she Is "rather small for
a queen," f*r she is but 4 feet 10 inches
in height. But, despite that, she is, on'
occasions,
a
nity.
woman of extraordinary dig­
Attempts Upon Hsr Life.
Although the queen, from the time of
her succession to the throne, has enjoyed
to the fullest extent the respect and af
fection of her subjects, no less than five
attempts, all, fortunately, unsuccessful,
have been made to assassinate her—the
first in June, 1810, by a crazy lad named
Oxford another lit May, 1S42, by John
Francis, who was sentenced to be hang
ed for the offense, but the sentence was
commuted to transportation for life. The
third was in July of the same year by one
J. W. Beam, whose only punishment was
eighteen months in prison the,fourth in
1849 by William Hamilton, aa Irish-man,
who was transported for seven years the
fifth in April, 1882, by Roderick McLean,
a Scotchman, who was ordered to be con
fined during her majesty's pleasure, and
is, we believe, still in prison.
The queen is very wealthy, in fact, the
wealthiest woman to all the world. Dur
ing the sixty years that she has been on
the throne she has been able to save from
her civil list and the revenues of the
Duchy of Lancaster sums, which, with in
terest added', now amount to close upon
$100,000,000. She inherited from her hus
band property which is now valued at
§25,000,000, and from time to time sub
jects die who leave her all or nearly all
their property. It is estimated that her
fortune to-day amounts to $150,000,000.
The Queen's Family.
Of the queen's nine children seven sur
vive. These are Victoria, Dowager Em,
press of Germany and mother of Kaisei
William II Albert Edward. Prince ol
Wales Alfred, Duke of Saxe-Coburgi
I-Ielena, Princess Christian of Sehleswig
Holstein Louise, Marchioness of Lome
Arthur, Duke of Con naught and Beatrice,
whose husband, Prince Henry of Batten
berg, died of fever during the Ashante*
war, in 1896. The Princess Alice, Dueh.
ess of Hesse-Darmstadt, died in 1878, and
the Duke of Albany in 1SS4.
A list of her grandchildren and jrreat
grand children would fill half a column.
By marriage into t'he great reigning fam
ilies her descendants will sit npon many
of -the leading thrones in Europe. Her
grandson, Emperor William of Germany,
is the most powerful monarch on the con
tinent, with the possible exception of the
Czar, and the latter is married to her
granddaughter, Princess Alix of Hesse.
Another granddaughter is Crtfwii Princess
of Roumainia, her son Alfred is ruler of
Saxe-Coburg, and a grandson is Grand
Duke of Hesse-Darmstadt.
If a man hates to do a thing, It should
not be Ms duty.
SENATE AND HOUSE.
WORK OF OUR NATIONAL LAW
MAKERS.
</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85047084/1897-06-22/ed-1/?sp=1&q=QUEEN+Queen+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>QUEEN VICTORIA
for Sixty Years She Has RnM
Over tie British Empire.
CIVILIZATIOH HAS ADVANCED
Beneficial Effect of Her In
fluence Upon England.
Progress a Distinguishing Fea
ture Development of
the Nation.
For 60 year's Queen Victoria has
reigned over the British Empire. At 20
minutes after 2 o'clock on the morning
of June 20, 1837, William IV. died at
Windsor Castle. At 11 o'clock the same
morning the young Queen met the
members of the Privy Council at Ken
sington Palace, and, after subscribing
to the customary oaths, received from
them their oaths of allegiance. The
death of the King was not wholly un
expected. His short illness developed
dangerous phases, and it was soon
thought that he could not survive, yet
it was almost without warning that
the Princess Alexandrina Victoria,
from being an unexperienced girl,
whose 18 years of life had been passed
in almost obscurity, came to occupy the
throne of England, and to assume at
once the responsibilities of the head of
a nation, with simplicity and dignity.
The manner in which she received
the news of the death of her uncle,
William IV., and in which, a few hours
later, she conducted the first meeting
of her Council won for her instant re
spect and admiration. She was almost
unknown personnlly to the members
of the Cabinet and Privy Council. She
had rarely been seen by the populace.
The unsettled condition of the society
of the court had. perhaps, justified her
mother, the Duchess of Kent, in allow
ing her to pass her life hitherto in se
clusion. Certainl, England has never
had occasion to regret that her life had
been so passed.
The coronation of the Queen took
place a year later. It is graphically de
scribed in a published life of Dean
Stanley as follows:
"At 10:30 o'clock a gun announced
that she was at the abbey door, and in
about a quarter of an hour the proces
sion appeared from under the 'organ,
advancing up the purple approach to
the chancel every one leaning over
and in they came. First, the great
Dukes, struggling with their enormous
trains; then etc., and the
Queen, with her vast crimson train,
outspread by eight ladies, all in white,
followed by the great ladies of the
court in enormous crimson trains, and
the smaller ladies with delicate sky
blue trains trailing along the dark
floor. When she came within the full
view of the gorgeous abbey she paused,
as if for breath, and clasped her hands.
The orchestra broke out into the most
tremendous crash of music I ever
heard. I was glad when they said
unto me: "Let us go into the house of
the Lord." t
"Every one literally gasped for
breath from the intense interest and
the rails of the gallery visibly trem
bled in one's hand from the trembling
of the spectators. I never saw any
thing like it. Tears would have been
a relief. One felt that the Queen must
sink into the earth under the trem
bling awe. Put at last she moved on to
her place bv the altar, and (as I heard
from mv cousins, who had a place close
bv) threw herself on her knees, buried
her face in her hands and evidently
nraved fervently. For the first part the
silence was so great that at my ex
treme point I could hear quite distinct
lv the tremulous but articulate voice
o'f theArchbishop: afterward it was
quite inaudible. The great drawbacks
were the feeble responses to the serv
ice and the feebleness of the acclama
tions hardlv any at all at the recog
nition and only tolerable at the coro
nation. That was the crisis j of the
ceremonv and the most striking part.
The very moment the crown touched
her head the guns went off. the trum
pets betran and the shouts. She was
perfectly Immovable like a statue.
The Duchess of Kent burst into tears
and her lady had to put on her coronet
for her. The anointing was very beau
tiful from the cloth of gold: the hom
age, also, from the magnificent cluster
in theverv center."
Already she had endeared herself in
the hearts of her subjects. Constitu
tional England was not slow to per
v.oir ruler was not a whim
sical Queen, that she sought only the
SA
PRINCESS HELENA,
PRINCE ARTHUR,
Schleswig-Holstein. Born May 23, 184G. Duke of Connaught. Born May 1, 1S30.
PRINCESS VICTORIA (Royal).
Dowager Empress of Germany.
Born Nov. 21, 1840.
PRINCE ALFRED,
Duke of Edinburgh. Born Aug. 6, 1844.
1837
if 5
ALBERT EDWARD,
Prince of Wales. Born Nov. 9, 1841.
1897
QUEEN VICTORIA AND HER CHILDREN
Ik
.n.t ':tr
0
-0
0-
V'P
'fa
Km
hn Km 1
PRINCESS LOUISE,
Marchioness of Lome. Born
March 18, 1S4S.
PRINCESS BEATRICE,
Battenburg. Born April 14, 1S5'
PRINCE LEOPOLD.
PRINCESS ALICE,
Duke of Albany. Born April 7, 1853. Hesse-Darmstadt. Born April 25, 1843.
aggrandizement of her Kingdom. She
had been confronted with serious prob
lems upon her ascension to the throne.
There had been political and social un
rest. Educational and religious fac
tions had been at variance with each
other. Many of her subjects were al
most without representation, the con
dition of the laboring classes was piti
ful. England was just recovering from
the effect of "personal" ruling, and
some of the statesmen of the time
were fearful of the result of having an
"almost infant Queen" deal with these
great problems.
From the first the Queen displayed
rare judgment, and, although she ac
cepted the advice of her ministers, was
not wholly dependent upon their coun
sel. This trait has characterized her
whole reign. Her deen interests in the
welfare of her subjects, her strong re
ligious nature had an immediate effect
upon the court, and the influence of her
example Ji? been felt (Turing her whole
reign. Under the constitution, per
haps, it has been her gracious exam
j pie more than an absolute dictation of
I policy that has influenced the change
i in the condition of not only the Eng
i lish-born inhabitants of Great Britain,
but of British subjects in whatever re
mote colony they may reside. The
change cannot be summed up in the
presentation of columns of figures.
Early in the Queen's reign, in 1842,
began the legislation for the ameliora
tion of the condition of the working
class. Previous to that time there were
nearlv a million nauDers in the United
j Kingdom and fully 60,000 inmates of
prisons. The public at large was aware
of these facts, but there seemed no
help for the condition. Wages were
at almost starvation rates and a high
protective tariff maintained the price
of corn almost beyond the purchasing
reach of the workingman. When his
days of usefulness were over the poor
house awaited him, or else he was sup
ported by his children, who, like him
self, were brought up with scarcely no
education, were thrust at a tender age
into the fields or the mines and as
sumed the cares which never left them.
Should one of them rebel there was al
ways the force of arms to silence the
demands for lightening the burdens.
The special act of Parliament, which
served to change these conditions, was
an act which prohibited the employ
ment of women and girls in mines and
collieries. It was owing to the efforts
of Lord Ashley, later known as the
Earl of Shaftesbury, that the attention
of Parliament was first called to the
subject, and a commission appointed
to investigate. During his whole life
time the Earl of Shaftesbury devoted
his energies to benefiting the working
class. He secured the passage of an
act reducing the hours of work for chil
dren in the factories and extending the
number of hours during which they
should be under Instruction.
Legislation favoring the working
class has continued during the Queen's
reign. Compulsory education met with,
opposition, because it was considered
that it interfered with individual
rights. The workingman possessed
few rights, and he clung to the few
with stubborn persistency. The results
have fully justified the interference.
The nearly ten million of British sub
jects who have embarked from their
native land during the last 60 years
have been fully equipped to compete
with the representatives of whatever
nationalities with whom tbey have
since been associated.
One of the -most radical changes
which was made in England's policy
was the abolition of the corn duties.
As early as 1842 the measure was over
whelmingly defeated in the House of
Commons by a Vote of over four to one.
Yet It was scarcely four years later
that the Government declared Itself In
favor of the abolition of the duties.
The Queen opened Parliament in per
son, in 1846, and in the speech from the
throne Parliament was recommended
to consider whether the principle of
the repeal of prohibitive and the re
laxation of protective duties, which
had been presented from time to time,
might not be more extensively applied.
This was the result of years of agi
tation on the part of men who, because
of their benevolent dispositions and
their researches Into the economic con
dition of the country, were convinced
that the 'social problem could never be
solved until the price of food was re
duced to meet the purchasing power of
wages. Mr. Richard Cobden was the
real leader of the movement, and his
chief companion was Mr. Bright. With
them were associated many of the
leading orators of the day, who de
voted themselves to the work of se
curing the repeal of the corn laws. A
league was formed, and the whole
country entered into the agitation. In
1845 the "potato rot" affected the
chief article of food in Ireland, and,
confronted by famine, even the Prime
Minister urged the abolition of the
corn duties.
At the time of the death of William
IV. there was strife between the two
factions in Canada. The million odd
inhabitants threatened the disruption
of the Government. Lower Canada was
formed almost entirely of French, and
any legislation that appeared to favor
either one of the divisions was regard
ed with jealousy by the other. One
man after another had tried to recon
struct the Canadian governmental
scheme, and had failed. It was even
proposed suspending the constitution
of Lower Canada Misrule had destroy
ed authority until Lord Durham was
sent out, and assumed control. His
policy in Canada subjected him to se
vere criticism, and he was shortly re
called. But he had thoroughly Investi
gated the condition of affairs in pan
ada, and immediately upon his return
to England he recommended that the
colonists should themselves possess as
much as possible of the government
of the colony, that autonomy should be
allowed the judiciary as well as in the
execution of law, and that the home
government should interfere only in
the relations of the colony with the
mother country. Lord Durham's rec
ommendations were gradually adopted,
and the Dominion of Canada of today,
with its population of six millions, and
Its loyalty to the home government is
the result. The same policy of auton
omy has been pursued in Australia as
well. The population of Canada and
Australia combined In 1837 was scarce
ly a million and a quarter. Today it is
nearly eleven millions. Since Queen
Victoria ascended the throne 80,000
square miles of territory have been ad
ded to the possessions of the British
Empire in India, and in Africa 1,000,
000 square miles.
During the reign science has made
wonderful advances. The industrial
arts and literature have developed.
Steam navigation had already been suc
cessfully tried. Many lines of railway
were opened during the year 1838. It
was also in this year that the act of
transmitting the mails by rail was
passed, a locomotive attained a speed
of 37 miles an hour during this year,
and transatlantic voyages were made
by steamboats. In the same year Pro
fessor Morse went to England to obtain
a patent for his invention of conveying
messages a short distance by tele
graph. Today there is not a quarter of
the globe that cannot be reached by
steam navigation, by railway or by
telegraph. England is in easy commu
nication with all her colonies, and be</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042461/1897-06-20/ed-1/?sp=20&q=QUEEN+Queen+VICTORIA</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>AS WOMAN
AND QUEEN
Victoria Has Won World
Wide Fame
A CORRESPONDENT'S TRIBUTE
KIND WORDS BESTOWED BY
BRITAIN'S RULER
Knows by Name Every Member of
Her Household From Drawing-
Room to Kitchen
Bpectol Correspondence to The Herald.
IjONDON, June 6.—Only those to
whom the honor of personal contact wit h
her majesty has been accorded can ade
quately realize how great in her good
ness, how commanding is her intellect,
and, with all her simplicity of heart and
sweetness of manner, how immeasurably
superior Is our beloved queen. That she
herself is the last to know this but makes
her power the more complete, for her
majesty Is the essence of an unaffected
and natural warmth of feeling which
reaches all hearts, and of which she her
self is the least conscious. Many an eye
has moistened at the queen's kind words,
when I am sure her majesty has felt sur
prised why those before her were so
much touched. Those who are await
ing an interview for the first time often
speak of their nervousness, and express
a wish that the "ordeal" (as some are too
apt to call it) were over; but It needs a
very few minutes' only to dispel their
nervousness, and there are few, if any,
who have ever left the queen's presence
without regret that the interview could
not be prolonged, and also with a warm
desire to be received again.
The moment her majesty enters the
room those who are awaiting her feel
that, beyond the presence ot a great sov
ereign, a true friend has come to them—
one in whom they can trust; one whose
kindness of heart and sense of Justice
will never fail them, and further and
more intimate knowledge of the queen
and of her life but intensifies and Justi
fies their first impression.
There is a natural dignity In her man
ner which probably has never been
equaled, and it has nothing of that chill
ing influence too often diffused by those
whose "dignity" is a mere assumption,
and not, as with our queen, the outward
and visible sign of inward grace. She has
a heart which never forgets; no matter
how long the interval may be, she re
members and inquires after all connected
with those to whom she is speaking.
There is not a servant In her several
households of whom she does not know
something, whom she is not, on
occasion, quickly and sincerely inter
ested.
The sympathy of her majesty in all ac
cidents, misfortunes and personal griefs
is too widely known to need remark here,
but I may add that the solicitude of the
queen which is made public bears no
proportion to the ever-active sympathy
she feels ar.d testifies to in private, and
which is of daily, almost hourly, occur
rence.
Amid affairs of slate, family interest::
and the numberless and incessant calls
upon her time and attention, the queen
always has a kind' thought and a kind
•word for those who need, either, and
in all the domestic relations of her life—
as daughter, wife and mother—she has
set the most touching as well as the
most exemplary of examples.
By this train of thought I am brough:
to the queen as a mother, and surely
there cannot be a mother's' heart among
us that will not warm up towards her
who has so truly been a mother to her
people, as she has Indeed been a be
loved and honored mother to her own
ohlldren.
From the outset our queen recognized
the immense factor for good of our
English family life, and in the carrying
out of this principle the prince consort
and herself devoted themselves to the
personal superintendence of their chil
dren, making of their palace a simple
"home"—in many ways far simpler than
those of numbers of her subjects—and
spending in the nursery what spare mo
ments they could steal from their royal
duties, to play with their children, some
times like children themselves, and- to
show an interest, as real as it was help
ful, in ail the pursuits and' occupations
of the young princes and princesses,
More than one story has been told of
Prince Albert being surprised on "all
fours," with one or two children on his
back, for whom he was turning himself
into a horse; of the others running to
the queen, us to the poorest and sim
plest of cottage mothers, as indeed her
grandchildren and great-granchlldren
do now.
The published photographs of the
queen, with the infant princes and prin
cesses, speak for themselves to those
who have eyes to see, for there is
"mother" in every line of her face and
figure as she sits or stand* protectingry
n?ar the little child.
No poor person, no hospital, no char
ity, no suffering soul, where the appli
cation was a deserving one, ever ap
pealed to the Queen in vain.
The world at large is tempted occa
sionally to think in a vague manner tha:
royal charity is one of the easiest of
acts, that princes and princesses ran
"give anything they please" by a stroke
of the pen; that, in fact, they "ought
always to give;" and these opinions are
repeated with many variations.
Verily, In this case do "fools rush in
where angels fear to tread," for those
who spealr In this manner have no
knowledge, and not the slightest con
ception, of the manifold difficulties
QUEEN VICTORIA'S JUBILEE
which surround the throne an* royal
family in the giving of alms and the
support of charitable institutions.
The exact contrary to these opinions
is the truth, for, notwithstanding that
there Is no known fortune sufficiently
large to satisfy a tithe of the applica
tions by which all whose names are offi
cially or publicly known are inundated
In these days, the Queen has set th;
noblest example, not only in the larg?
sums of m->ney she annually expends in
charity, but far more efficacious assist
ance she causes personally to be ren
dered, where advice, superintendents
and good sense are far more needed than
a mere monetary subscription.
Quietly and unobtrusively, she and'her
family have often saved, helped and
forwarded many a charity which would
otherwise have had to close Its doors:
and, indeed, to the far-seeing policy of
the Queen and noble husband in the mat
ter cf the government of charitable in
stitutions is due their present condition
of excellence, the increased' facilities' for
helping all deservng cases, and the stil'
wider aid and support now given to.
charity in this country by all these abl.
to do so.
Little children feel- their mothers' In
fluence without knowing it; we older
children can recognize this royal influ
ence now, and let us hope that on this
great and glorious oo aslon every man
and woman in Great Britain will my,
"God bless the Queen" for the motherly
love with which she has so long nour
ished, cherished and watched over her
people.
Side by side with the true womanll
ne?» for which the Queen is so justly
loved is that Intellectual power, almost
masculine in its strength, which has so
often won not only her ministers' ad
miration and deference, but that of aii
the most learned and able men who have
ever come in contact with her.
Whether we look on our Queen
young girl she was when ehe inherited
the heavy responsibilities ar.d immense
power which arc inseparable from the
crown of England—whether as a young
wife, mother, and, alas! now as a Widow
—we cannot only find no fault, but not
even an error in judgment, I may almost
pay; for, however high party feelir.g
may have run, however difficult at va
rious times, both internal and foreign
policy may have become, even those
most opposed to the views of the Queen
and her ministers at the period have
ihvays known that Victoria. Queen and
Empress, with ail her gentleness of feel
ing, had a stern sense of justice, an un
swerving will to resist all wrong, at.d
that, above all else, she was a constitu
tional monarch, and would, to the let
ter, adhere to her coronation oath, nj
matter how far her own personal feel
ing? ml&ht unavoidably run in another
direction.
Subsequent events have more than
once proved how entirely the Queen:
judgment was the best when she had
nevertheless felt it her duty to defer
to the wishes of her ministers, and al
low a contrary action to be taken.
There is probably no one now living
whose Intimate knowledge of all th:
political events of the last seventy years
is so consecutive and so complete as that
of the Queen. The clearness and activ
ity of her mind have always been, and
are now, most remarkable. Her mem
ory Is even more so, for few persons can
approach her without very soon discov
ering that the Queen knows quite as
much, and often mote, on the subject
I
under discussion that he whose special
business it is. At the same time, her
majesty Is ever ready to gain Informa
tion, and Is most graciously and con
siderately pleased to listen to anything
which is worth repetition.
There Is not a trace in her of (hat af
fectation of knowledge which is occa
sionally to be found in less gifted per
sons; her talent is as spontaneous as it is
solid and exact. In the lighter accom
plishments of life she also excels;; sh:
Is a good linguist, an able musician and
artist, and many a "poor body's" heart
has been gladdened by seme warm
Queen Victoria's Girlhood
"comfort" made by the Queen's own
deft fingers.
It has been said that "to the greatest
minds the simplest things are great,"
and It may truthfully be added that
nothing which is worthy is too small
of the Queen's appreciation; all that is
great in life, in art, in literature, in
science, has her most able nnd intelli
gent comprehension and praise.
In a more marked and detailed form
than is at present possible, future his-
torlans will bring more forcibly to light
the directing influence her purity of
LOS ANGELES HERALD t SUNDAY MORNING. JUNE 90, 1897
A COLLECTION OP ROYAL PORTRAITS
THE PRINCE OF WALES AS HE APPEARED AT VARIOUS AGES
mind, her accurate learning, and her
power for good have had on her country
and people. One whose own loyalty to
all that is right Is so steadfast, Inspires
loyalty in others. Small wonder, then,
that our Queen should be so univer
sally beloved, for her watchword
through life has been "duty." Through
good and through 111 she has performed
It, and no sovereign In history hat
ever had so bright and unsullied a rec
ord. She has suffered deeply, but her
people's love, as she herself has so path
etically told them, has comforted her.
May we, her people, one and all, rise
up now ar.d again and assure her with
all our hearts and minds how loyally
•.ve feel for her, how deeply we rever
ence her, and how fervently we_ pray
God to "bless and comfort the Queen."
AMERICANS AND THE JUBILEE
LONDON", June IC—The most difficult
problem that has been set the keen and
energetic American citizens of London
for a long time is how to properly cele-
brate the Queen's Diamond Jubilee. Ail
sorts of ingenious and tasteful project*
have, therefore, been broached, among
them the suggestion of a huge American
subscription to the Prince of Wales'
hospital fundi Another scheme was to
present a characteristic American con
tribution to the Zoo or to the British
Museum, or add to the statuary In Hyde
Park, or make Her Majesty some strik-,
Ing and original gift, and try to get an
act of Parliament passed for Its accept
ance. Not a single one of these pro
posals, however, but was open to un
favorable criticism on the other side of
the Atlantic, where some people are
found who, lacking the expansion of
views obtained by living abroad, can- j
not understand that esteem for another
country does not cast out theilove of j
one's own land.
After months of careful deliberation
the Americans in London, many of whom
have lived here so long as to feel almost 1
like loyal subjects, have decided on tw
methods of honoring the Jubilee. Th?
schemes are entirely separate, but many
prominent Americans are co-workers Ir
both. The principal effort originates
Iwith the American society, ant) will take
the shape of an illuminated address to I
the Queen. The second project is the
result of different endeavors and will
probably effect the endowment of a num
ber of beds in the principal hospitals,
the Idea being to give to visitors from
across the Atlantic, who may be af
flicted or Injured l while In England, a
special haven of refuge.
At the last meeting of the American
Society It was unanimously decided to'
appoint a committee which should hn\
full power to draw up an ad
dress to be signed by all the
representative resident Americans
In Great Britain, and presented to her
majesty on the day chosen tocelebrat;
the record reign. The body selected Is
composed of the general commute?,
numbering twenty-one members, prom
inent among whom are Mr. Benjamin
Franklin Stevens, Mr. Moncure D. Con
way, Mr. H. S. Wellcome, Colonel J. L.
Taylor, Mr. Newton Crane, Mr. J. Mor
gan Richards, Mr. D. C. Haldeman and
Mr. Frederic C. Van Duzer. The ex
offlclo members ot this committee are
his excellency, the American ambassa
dor, the secretary of the United States
embassy, the American military attache,
the American consul-general, and the
American naval attache.
The American society in London, to
give It Is full name, was founded to keep
up the patriotic spirit in Americans
abroad, and to promote friendly feelings
between the inhabitants of England an J
the United States. With very few ex
ceptions ,the organization ie not only
a thoroughly representative body, but it
has a membership roll made up of nearly
all the most prominent Americans who
make their home in the United Kingdom.
The desire to appropriately aid In the
celebrations of the diamond Jubilee Is a
general one, and the committee now ap
pointed may be trusted to do its work
not only conscientiously but enthusias
tically. As to the manner of presenta
tion, the most favored proposal Is that
the new ambassador, Mr. John Hay,
ehould offer her majesty the scroll, ex
pressing in a few words American appre
ciation of the glories ot a beneficent
reign and offering assurance of a re
spectful affection and sincere congrat
ulations.
It Is certain that the project of sub
mitting such an address to the Queen
will receive the warmest official sym
pathy, and there Is little doubt of tho
presentation being made by Mr. Hay In
his official capacity. It was learned
from Mr, Henry White, the secretary
of the embassy, that the other project
referred to, the endowment of a number
of beds In the principal hospitals, was
being heartily supported.
BIRD OF LETTERS
ABC. ABC, ABC!''
The parrot cried, proud as could be.
We birds who know letters
Are surely your betters,"
He called to the birds In the tree.
But the birds In the tree-top at play
Al! chirped In the jolllest way,
"We don't know ABCi,
But we're quite at our ease
In these higher branches," said they.
—H. L. Brldgman in June St. Nicholas.

He Asked Her to Sing
He asked her to sing, for his heart was
astir
For all the sweet solace that sods might
oonfer;
He asked her to alng, then he writhed in a
flt,
For how could he guess that she never
I would quit. —Chloago Record.
FLAGS OF
ALL NATIONS
Grandest Naval Review
Ever Seen
REPRESENTATIVE WARSHIPS
FROM EVEBY IMPORTANT KING
DOM IN THE WORLD
Will Gather to Do Honor to England's
Queen —The TJ. S. S. Brooklyn
Will Hoist "Old Glory"
Special Correspondence to The Herald.
LONDON, Eng., June B.—Unless all
plans miscarry, the naval review on the
occasion of the queen's Jubilee will sur
pass in greatness and charm any marlr.6
event which has taken place since the
old Vikings cruised in the vicinity of
North America. Every nation of the
world which possesses any claim to be
ing a naval power will be represented by
a war vessel of sufficient size to evidence
the appreciation of England's power and
the sterling worth of her queen.
In addition to the visiting craft, Ens
land's navy will be represented as H
never has been before on a single occa
sion. No one who does not consult the
records of the admiralty has an ade
quate idea of the real strength of Eng
land on the sea. It lsan actual fact that
she numbers her vessels of war by tha
hundred and that the most powerful
fighting machines that float fly her
Hag. National prejudices in other coun
tries may provoke a denial of this state
ment, but cold facts prove it to be true.
Therefore It Is small winder that the
English people are looking forward to
the naval review in the light of a spec
tacle that, lllce Katisha's elbow, will be
worth coming miles to see. It has been
definitely settled that Spain will be rep
resented by a warship. The cable tells
us that the United States will send here
her crack cruiser, the Brooklyn. The
German empire will be represented by
the Koenlg YVilheim., carrying the flatf
of his royal highness, the prince of Prus
sia. The lilies of France will fly at the
masthead of one of the visitors. An Iron
clad carrying a rear admiral's flag Is
to represent the Netherlands. Sweden
has signified her intention of sending a
man-of-war.
So far as England herself la con
cerned, the ships that will take part In
the review will go Into commission June
15th. Chatham will contribute about
forty ships for the purpose.
Two of the militia artillery brigade,
representing Scotland and Ireland, are
now In camp, as are nearly two thous
and officers and men of the militia In
fantry battalion. It has been Anally de
cided that the Honorable Artillery com
pany shall, on June 22, be posted at the
Mansion House, while the Fourth Royal
Fusiliers will be placed at Temple Bar,
the entrance of the city.
Among many other suggestions re
cently made with a view to celebrate in
fitting fashion the diamond Jubilee may
be mentioned one for organizing on an
elaborate scale a river pageant on the
week of the royal commemoration.
Moreover, It would seem that some steps
have already been taken towards the
realization of this project by loyal river
side Inhabitants, but it may be well at
or.cc to dismiss, as In the highest degree
improbable, the Idea of anything In the
hature of a "royal" procession on- the
Thames.
Nevertheless, a notion that something
lof this .kind might perhaps be carrlel
I out has lately got abroad, and falsj
hopes have been raised as to the posel
billty of the past glories of Father
Thames as a medium for state pageant*
being revived. It appears that certain,
residents in Windsor and some of the
riverside towns that He between th*>
royal borough and Kingston, expressed
a desire that a scheme of this nature be
carriedi out between the two places
named.
Quite recently a letter was addressed
to tha lord mayor asking him whether.
In the event of a 'state procession" be
ing decided upon, he would be Inclined
to advocate that the proposed pageant
be extended as far as Westminster. His
lordship, It is understood, replied that
the matter was one in reference to which
the Thames conservators should be ap
proached.
Queen Victoria's "Coronation Roll"
The "Coronation Roll" 1» wonderfully
and curiously complete. It eete down
every detail with minuteness and elabo
ration. The "Coronation Roll" of Queen
Victoria Is like the rolls of all herprede
cessors since the time of Richard ll—a
huge, bulky roll of parchment. It li
what the lawyers would call a deed pol
as distinguished from an Indenture. It
has its preambles and recitals and itaob
llgatlon, all of which are quaintly set ou
in stilted phrases on a series of pieces of
sheepskin, each, fifteen Inches wide, fas
tened together by loose stitches, until the
whole attains the length of nearly 100
lineal feet. It can be perused only by
unrolling from one end or the other, and
Is bo unwieldy that the seeker for any
information of which the precise loca
tion is unknown must invoice tho aid of
no end of manual assistance to attain It
The script Is In the highest style of the
scrivener's art, and is an excellent ex
ample of the engrossment that is atll
considered necessary in England for
wills and deeds, whloh, as there la no
general system of publicly recording such
instruments, are kept in "Btrong boxes"
under lock and key. Speaking generally
the result, ac a whole, is over 100 square
feet of solid reading in one breath, and In
a language that Is a mixture of lege
mediaeval and court phrases, but eao
line gives one a glimpse not to be ha
otherwise of the Intricacy, dignity as
significance of the coronation oeremongj,</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053942/1876-03-23/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Queen+Victoria+Empress+India</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Queen Victoria to be an Empress.
IjOndon. Jlarch Z6. Alter an anuria
ted debate in the house of commons the
Royal Titles bill, making Queen Victoria
empress of India, passed its third reading,
The vote was 209 for the bill and 134
agginst.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84027008/1866-08-10/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Queen+Victoria</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Tho ??ew York News thus aptos
up tile royal matrimonial comjjilica
tions, ip which tlx; Queen of/;?ng
'.and linds herself involved in the
present condition of a.flairs in Europe!
4:. Queen. Victoria's eldest son
the Prince of Walis-is married to a
daughter'of'.the King of Denmark,
who has been deprived of*'-a largo
portion of his territories by. the Kiug
of Prussia, father of the husband of
tho Queen's eldest daughter; and
this mutilation of Denmark was ef?
fected,- nominally, in the interest of
the Duke of Augusfceuburg, whose
younger brother, Princo Christian,
j has been married to the Queen's
I third daughter, the Princess Helena.
2. The Queen's first co.isin, the
King of Hanover, has beeu deprived
of his kingdom by the same'King of
Prussia, in whose army the Queen's
sou-in-law, tho Prince of Prussia, is
a commanding officer. The King of
Hanover is married to a cousin of ?the
.Duke of Saxe-AJteiiburg, who voted
against Austria in the Federal Diet,
whilst Hanover voted against Prusaia.
o. Prince Alexander, of Hesi*e, who
commands the Federal army raised to
I oppose the Kin*g of Prussia, is bro?
ther to Prince Louis, the husband ol
the Pri uceas Alice, the Queen's se
coud daughter.
j 4. The Duke of Saxe-Coburg
i Gotha-I rince'Albert's lirother, uni
brother-in-law to the Queen-hold;
command, in tho King of JP russia';
army that invaded Hanover, whicl
kingdom, by the way, until thc acc?s
sion of Queen Victoria, formed dur
ing five reigns part ol tho territory o
the Kings of England.
The Queen's second son. lin
Duke of Edinburgh, (Prince Alfred,
is the ne phew of the same Duke n
Saxe Coburg-Gotha, aud has beende
I dared heir-presumptive, to the duchy
(y. Prince -Teck, recently marrie*
i to the Queen's nr?t cousin, the Prin
cess Mary of Cambridge) holds
commission in the army of the Ere
peror of Austria, and might, at au
time, have had to leave his bride fe
1 the seat*oi war, to light the King c
Prussia, who has tho Queen's son-n
law, and thejQuyeu's brother-in-law
both officers in Ins army. The sistf
of tin* Princess Mary, the Pritioe*
Augusta of Cambridge, is married t
the Grand Duke of -Mecklenburg
Strebt/., who espouses the cause
Prussia.
7. Two of the Queen's first eotisil
on her mothers side, ar?; married t
member*of the. Austrian family, vi
Leopold II. of Belgium, who is ma
ried to an Arch-duehess of Austri
and the Princess Cariotta, of Be
ginni, married to the Emperor
Mexico, who is brother to the Et
peror of Austria.
Such are the positions in the pr
sent contest in which the near rel
tives of thOiQueen of England stan
To have included in our eatalogi
lb?* nnoe distant relatives of h
Majesty, would have extended it
morti thau three times its prese
length; but it would have exhibit
bow. much the struggle in Germa
has the appearance of being, if it
not in reality, a vast family quarre!
</text>
      </result>
          <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1914-06-23/ed-1/seq-22/#date1=1756&index=0&rows=20&words=Queen+Victoria+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+is+queen+victoria%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>LOYALTY TO ROYAL WIFE GAINS
ROYAL FUNERAL FOR LORNE
vO
royal spouse long since won the ap
proval o'f Queen Mary. By her wish
he was buried from Westminster with
royal ceremonies.
o o
MRS. LLOYD-GEORGE IDOLIZED
AS WIFE OF NEXT PREMIER
&cjchei f Ajgyl
"Poor Lome," lately known as the
Duke of Argyle, lias just been buried
from Westminster with the pomp due
a ducal laird. But the memory of his
"romance" will not die. The Mar
quis of Lome owed the honor thrust
upon him to his masterful grand
mother, the old Duchess of Suther
land, who was Queen Victoria's Mis
tress of Robes time out of mind.
Through her vigilance "Poor Lome"
married the royal Princess Louise
and for many years he was made to
feel the honor thrust upon him. But
of late years the court had grown
kinder. . . .. - ,. .
ftfrsJioyekG&ot'ge?
London, England. Next to Queen
Mary herself, the most popular and
most sought after woman in Eng
land is Mrs. David Lloyd-George, wife
of the chancellor of the exchequer.
Modest and motherly, Mrs. Lloyd
George is not at all an aggressive so
cial leader, but she is the wife of the
man who almost certainly will be the
next premier. Englishwomen, count
ing firmly on this,are assiduously
cultivating her society.</text>
      </result>
          <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn78004468/1917-11-23/ed-1/seq-9/#date1=1756&index=1&rows=20&words=Queen+Victoria+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+is+queen+victoria%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
          <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045389/1920-10-03/ed-1/seq-64/#date1=1756&index=2&rows=20&words=Queen+Victoria+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+is+queen+victoria%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
          <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85047084/1903-01-09/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=5&rows=20&words=Queen+Victoria+Who+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+is+queen+victoria%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>King Prefers the Bishop of Winchester
Who Comforted Queen Victoria in Her
Last Illness Succeeds Dr. Frederick
Temple.
(ASSOCIATED PRESS CABLEGRAMS.)
LONDON, Jan. 8. King Edward today appointed as Archbishop
of Canterbury, Dr. Randall Thomas Davidson, who has been Bishop
of Winchester since 1895.
The appointment of the aged Bishop to the highest office in the
Church of England is the result of the King's good feeling for the
prelate who attended and comforted Queen Victoria during her last
moments. The Bishop was a favorite of the Queen and King Ed
ward wished to advance him as a fitting reward for his untiring de
votion to the throne.
There were three candidates for the position, the Bishops of
Ripon, London and Winchester.
The Bishop of London, a radicalist in church matters, known
as the Phillips Brooks of London, was a favorite of Queen Alex
andra for the See of Canterbury, and court gossip declared that the
Queen's influence would elect him. During his illness a few weeks
ago the Queen sent one of her own nurses to attend him. In mak
ing the appointment of Bishop Davidson, the King is said to have
been influenced against the Bishop of London because of his youth.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85047084/1899-08-19/ed-1/seq-3/#date1=1756&index=18&rows=20&words=Queen+Victoria+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+is+queen+victoria%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>KISSED THE BABY QUEEN.
Miss Eleanor Jeffries, an English
woman, died in Paris last month, aged
96. She was the only surviving mem
ber of the Society of the Kiss Royal,
formed by forty-five school girls, who,
when Queen Victoria was a baby, gave
her nurse a shilling apiece to be al
lowed to kiss the little Princess.
"Calumet" Does Not Belong to a
Baking Powder Trust, but Con
sumers are Rapidly Learning
to Place Their Trust in
Calumet."</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-race-south-pole/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1909-09-19/ed-1/?sp=47&q=expedition+Pole+POLE+Scott+South+SOUTH+expeditions</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NOW TO PLANT A FLAQ UPON THE. SOUTH POLE;!
Shall It Be the Stars and
Stripes First, or John
Bull's Union Jack.?
And now all eyes are turning to the South Pole.
An international race to capture the last great
geographical prize and to clear the mystery of the
Antarctic has every prospect of being started next
year A British expedJtlon led by Captain R. P.
Scott Is already assured, with $35,000 subscribed for
expenses within a few days and seven thousand
applications from as many persons •willing to share
In the glory of discovery. Dr. W. S. Bruce plans
another Scottish expedition. In this country ex
plorers, scientists and common people vow that the
Vnlted States must have the blue ribbon of the
South as well as the North. There Is a possibil
ity that Commander Peary and his crew, without
watting to settle that little question about who
nailed the flag to the North Pole first, may sail for
th« frigid antipodes. Captain Bartlett of the Roose
\»lt pays he would like nothing better. The ship,
the dogs and the equipment could be used right
away for en Antarctic dash. Other countries are
vet to be heard from, but there seems to be little
doubt that the fever will spread and that next
summer will see a formidable array of expeditions
bearing down en the Southern Cross. Especially
the Panes, the Norwegian*, the Belgians and the
Germans are unlikely to be absent from the last
irreat pole bunting sweepstakes. For there Is only
one pole left for man to find and he cannot find it
more than onee twice, allowing for disputed
claims.
A movement among scientific societies in this
country to send out an Antarctic expedition has
received treat stimulus from the achievements of
Cook and Peary fti the North. Within a few weeks
the American Geographical Society, seconded by
other scientific bodies, will probably endeavor to
have the United States government dispatch an
official expedition South Poleward. Other countries
are In the habit of sending official expeditions.
Why not the United States, It Is argued, especially
after her great achievement through private en
terprise la the North The following resolution,
urged by such rr en as Rear Admiral Melville, Ed
win Swift Batch and Henry O. Bryant, and ap
proved by the American Geographical Society, was
passed last April by the American Philosophical
Society: "That the American Philosophical Society
requests the co-operation of the scientific and geo
graphical societies of the United States to urge on
the United States navy and the general government
that It make sufficient appropriations to fit a gov
ernment vessel to thoroughly explore and survey
the coast of Wilkes Land and other parts of Ant
arctica." It, Is expected that when the executive.
council of the American Geographical Society
meets next month a committee will be appointed
to go to Washington and confer with government
officials concerning the project of a national ex
pedition.
FAVORS POPULAR SUBSCRIPTION.
Regardless of governmental action, something is
cure to be done, if the opinions of prominent men
Interviewed by a Tribune representative are ac
curately drawn. A fruitful suggestion was made
by Robert C Morris, president of the Republican
Club, that a popular subscription be opened for
carrying the Stars and Stripes to the southern
axis of the earth. It ought to be easy at this time
to raise a fund that would at least give the Unlud
States an equal start In tne forthcoming Interna
tional contest. The British expedition a*ks $300,090
for whip and equipment. Such a sum should be
speedily raised in this country and without going
outside the American metropolis.
On the scientific Bide, the South Pole Is a ripe
Truit that will almost surely be plucked by one
or more of the Intrepid bands of explorers goin;
r ft^r it. It is not a question of slow conquest and
I loddlnar'progreEs, as in the corrh. A few mon»hs
*-
Bag; stood within 111 miles of the Southern axl«,
srtrich is much nearer than man ever came to the
North Pole before Its final capture. Shackleton
was alnif within sight of his goal. The nex\
group of explorers may actually get there. It will
he a literal rare between the nations, and a narrow
margin .•f weeks. days or even hours may deter
mine the victory. In view of the Impending bltt*r
rivalry. It may be deemed wise to establish inter
national rules for the contest, forbidding euch
things as "doping" of the dogs, malicious injury
le rival equipments, appropriation of others* caches,
giving false Information and the like. It Is pretty
v*U surmised that gold seekers are not more ruth
\psM and lawless in pursuit of their quest than
Ti]i hunters in the icy wastes of the earth's ex-
WiiUcs.
flism is a possibility that the United States will
be represented by two expeditions if Commander
Pe&ry consents to lead one Antarctic party. In
that case it ie predicted that Dr. Cook, who was a
member f the Belgian expedition ten years agu
and is eipecially ktrtu on the Antarctic problem,
will be cure to. hurry another party Into the flU'i-
Then the two principals in the great North Pole
controversy could fight their differences to a f.nlch
at the southern asai of the globe. Down there
Plenty of white witnesses and umpires among flit
international contestants could be obtuii. d.
SHACKLETON MAY TRY AGAIN.
Cyrus C, Adams, a well known geographer «nd
editor of The American Geographical Society Bul
letin." eaid:
•There is indeed .a world- wide movement begin
ning for th« conquest of the- Antarctic. Pull is
Scott and Bruce. Lieutenant fihackleton. who has
the record for (bo South Pole, is eager to lead an
expedition in the Dei*. He re are many BClentlflc
societies wbo want to see the United Elates repre
CHICAGO BEXF TRUST AfTLR ARGENTINA'S CATTLE
The United States May Be
Importing Fresh Meat
Before Long.
Argentina's slaughter houses and packing houses
which turned out livestock products valued at
more- than flU.tto.aw for export last year have
teen, it is said. annexed by certain meat mar.
nates of the United States, and the people of this
country will ultimately be fed and shod, gloved and
dressed by th« herds and flocks roaming over the
ranges south of the equator. The new tariff ad
raits hides free and lowers the duty on meats.
♦ier*by paving; the way for Americans to sample
immediately Argentine steaks and satoa. It la. of
course, rather hard to contemplate eating and
walking on thing* produced bo far from Chicago.
Patriotism auks indignantly why we should as
similate foreign sausage and the reason aw must
grow our corns and bunions under sub-equatorial
leather. The answer is that the United States
Crazing mi la fast diminishing owing to the
•uperlor value of the land for agriculture, and
H this country's thoughtful magnates did not get
hold of the Argentine ranges we would Boon be
reduced to a vegetable diet on ueekdays and pork
chops on Sundays and holidays. The common
t**ple may aaaasaar themselves fortunate that the
"Big Pour" companies of Chicago have annexed
Argentina* beef machinery at a preliminary cost
and at a final coat that depends on
now hard Europe takes being deprived of her
chilled beef rations.
Many persons had forgotten there was such a
•umry Argentina, of which the geography
told, until the startling news that they
■•Mid have to eat and wear her products evoked
■f»**d and mostly Incorrect Images of Pueglan
••age* and woolly Mamas travelling through a
ij**' 11 the Haclcensack meadows. The Argen
Is sizable country, about one-third the area
the United States, with a population of about
million. Her vast, "fertile prairies are so dry
'j?l -water, for rattle Is obtained only by boring
artesian welt*. No less than tOS.KfcHU beeves,
Mfc horses, ;/;wlnf\ gnats and other domestic
:,*U^ie|hv vaju.-.i at ji^arlyjt'.O'M/y/V'l?, flonrleli uj>on'
SHACKLETON'B SOUTH POLAR CAMP, WITH THE VOLCANO OF MOUNT EREBUS IN THE BACKGROUND.
sented," and are trying to promote a national ex
pedition. Never were so much sclcntifia t!at:\ nU
taln«»d in any part of the polar regions us by the
south polar »xpcditlonji, Belgian. British, German
and Norwegian, or the last nfteon years. Shackle
ton's expedition, from which he returned lust
spring, was the most brilliant of them all, because
he saw more Antarctic territory than any others
and came almost within sl^l.t of the S"ath Polo
from his elevation, t!>e distance being 111 tuatute
miles. This has aroused great ii tcrcst the fur
ther exploration of the Antarctic continent, which
has been proven to exist. The thorough exploration
of the Antarctic; meui:a an examination of a vast
body of land, whose coasts on all sides seem to bo
partly determined, while the «.-i is the prevailing
feature of the Arctic. Peary's soundings between
Grant Land and the pole certainly indicate there Is
no 'land of great extent beyond Grant L*ind and
Greenland In the American Arctic, Just as Nanson
Mas shown the great probability that no large land
mass remains to be discovered In UM Asian nnEuropean segments of the Arctlo between tho New
Siberia Islands and Franz Joseph Land to the polo.
"The climatic conditions, on the whole, are trjoru
unfavorable In the south than la the north. Th*
Antarctic winds In some beasons are t«rr:. and
naturally, over a great land mass, the cold 1* mure
Intense than over a sea area. Just as low tem
peratures art» found la the Arctlo as la the Antarc
tic, but the average annual temperature Is lower In
the south. On the other har.d. *xjAntarctic are rare of their foundation, which is
land. Instead of shifting leo lhat threatens to SO
gulf the northern explorer. The surface Is ■moot
on land and better for travel; there in no no<;s
and hummocks. However, la itoss Sea. east of
South Victoria Land, and on other sta«. the condi
tions In the south are about ti,<- same as thuue
i-> the north. Th«: length of tho season Is the sante,
though the southern winter is the northern summer.
It Is a much greater distance from London or New
York to the southern axis than to the North Pole.
ACHIEVEMENTS OF WILKES.
"The United Suites did a great deal of early
work in 11m Antarctic. Seventy years ano Lieuten
ant Wllkei law much of the periphery of the Ant
arctic continent, discovering bits of land which ar«
undoubtedly projecting parts of it. Hi« discoveries
were discredited in Europe, but it has l«.-«-n proved
that the lands bo nsmri ci rt, with on»s exception.
Since an American made- Ins greatest contribution
to the establishment of the (act that an Antarctic
continent exists, and especially Hino«j his work was
long discredited abroad, it la fitting that American
effort should be unlisted In i-omplvtlns tho gr«at
work which as began. Tl* scientific r>"»«U»lIiti«
are lmpoitant, though n<> greater than In the north,
for tho reason that wo cannot fully understand
phenomena thai we may study In our own lemp< r
ate «on« und»-r present conditions unlrxH we know
the regime itr.d operation of the *:aru<; phenomena in
the polar regions.
•"j !i<: conditions at the K'luth Pole, land Instead
of a sea of nhiftlng Un% would permit a pi rmamut
scientific station to be e«,ta!jli«heand Ars' nth have maintained scientific stations In
the South Orkneys for several years. Commer
cially, Sbackleton has round what scfnis to be vast
bodies of coal msi the South Pole. We don't know
how these deposits ran be made available, beyond
affording t\i-l for the scientific station at tho j*»l«.
The- renewal of Antarctic enterprise has resulted i i
the discovery of whaling ground* in tha South
Shetland and elsewhere, which tl»o Norwegians and
J. OGDEN ARMOUR.
The Chicago beef magnate, who is credited with
a ac-.ire to become a great financier.
the great plains where th« eataJKteroa reinforce
pampas «-rass with alfalfa for fattening the stock.
ARGENTINA TRADE STANDING.
Argentina Is' the fifth among exporting countries
and the second In commerce among the nation* of
the Western Hemisphere. Bhe has fourteen thoii
eaiia-tnll':S of railroads. if;.' exported flast I yesr.
m
NEW-YORK DAILY TRIBUNE, SUNDAY, SEPTI3S[ISER: 30; 1900:
Argcntinoa are developing into a large Industry-
There Is a general lack of animal life In the BOUth
iv.nipared with the Arctic. Of course, there are no
K.s'iulinam or other human inhabitant!!.
A BENEFICENT STRUGGLE.
Robert C. Morris, lawyer, and president it the
Republican Club, said
"No* that American enterprise and em-rKy have
enrrii-d the (tag to tho North Pole, I am oovatoua
of our country also obtaining the laurels of til
fouth. I do not think that such a sentiment, th»»
seizing of a scientific trophy and the advancement
SHACKLETON'B PARTY OVERWHELMED BY HIGH WINDS IN THE SOUTH POLAR
REGION.
frozen beef valued at about r»8.00<).000. about $7,000,
<>oo In frozen mutton and other moats, about $2,000.
000 worth of live cauls and sheep, |S.ooo,yo»» worth
of tallow, $128,000,000 worth Of wheat, $41,worth of corn. $43,000,000 worth of HBOOsd, and
forth. Th« BsTuroa are ilreHumoly big. It might
be worth adding thai the wool amounted to $47.
000,00% ili<- cattl« hides to more than $l5.ouo,«oo and
the sheep Klilim above 15J0Q.000. The goats,
horse and horse I-"-, nut to mention butter
and kid skins, are Important Item* The United
States did a snug little business with Argentina
la»t year, buying 01,000,000 worth of goods 'from
and wiling $31 .0>X),0()0 worth to that country, but
this wan a small rractlotl of Argeatlaa'l total in
ternational trada nearly HaXMMIA
It lias all happened In the last few decades. The
International trade of Argentina has almost tripled
In ten yearn. Wealth ha* coma w» fast to ••ton*
otoroo, lords of th* pampas leagues, that they have
built a new Paris in Buenos Ayres and have begun
to study Plttsburg methods of getting rid of a
surplus. Immigration is bo favored by the govern
ment that Immigrants got free board and lodging
for live or ten days after arrival In the country,
are transported tree to their destinations In the
.nterlor. are cared for during sickness and provided
with Jobs. The larger number of immigrants are
Italians. Ah for its form of government, Argentina
is a republic.
The Argentine guucho— cowboy of the pampas—
descendant of the mating of Spaniards and Indians,
whom Carlyle described with pitying condescension
as a naked centaur draped In a poncho, Is not
what he used to be. He still affects gaudy colors,
silver Spurs and long knives In fancy bolts: drinks
hard, plays the guitar, gambles with ox bone dice,
refuses tips and commits murder in-reta'.iatlon for
an Insult, but he Is disheartened by th* Industrial
revolution which has made the wilderness a factory
annex. Railroads and machinery have tangled
him up and reduced his former importance in the
"camp." Hl« task* of rounding up and "cijUing
i out" thousands of cattle have been largely replaced
1 by patent yards and automatic runways. He Is no
longer able to slay Indians as a pastime, and the
Italian settlers are likely to defend themselves. Yet
the gaueho remains quite natve and romantic. A
physician had prescribed, a sleeping powder,, to.be
taken nt 9 ii.- 111., a Efuicho wh.o-ltad- suffered -a
of knowledge the benefit of which all humanity
must share, can be called Samoa or greedy. This
competition among nations to discover the unknown
Is a most generous and beneficent struggle, for there
can really be no losers, and the winner Is the world
rather than a nation or an Individual. All scien
tific research, however far fetched and abstract it
seems, has Its value. Within a few years our
weather rer«>rts hi Now York may be based largely
on observations made at the polar extremities. Let
tho mystery be raised from the Antarctic as soon
an possible, and may the Stars and Stripes float at
the southern axis of lbs earth as they are now
pulnful injury. The patient went to bed at 7 p. m.
and slept Straight through th«» night. The next
day be wanted to borrow an alarm clock from his
boM SO that he could get up at 9 o'clock that night
and take his sleeping powder.
THE WILD RIDING OAUOHOS.
A rodeo or round-up shows the gaucho at his best.
riding marvellously, taking long chances, steering
a whirlpool of cattle around and around a post, so
thai they will be too occupied to think of escape.
Two gauchos chasten the spirit of a fractious beast
in ii novel way. They rids up to the animal, and
getting on either side gallop at top speed, yelling
ilk« savages. The stupid cow or steer, thinking It
is imprisoned by the horsemen, goes Its limit of
■pood until exhausted and convinced that It Is bet
ter to be good. The gaucho piles a short riding
whip instead of* the long rawhide used elsewhere
In cattle punching. His methods generally are
more coaxing than coercive. In fact. It Is not safe
to Intrust a valuable pedigreed horse or bull to the
care of th« gaueho. for he will almost certainly
overfeed his pet. An interesting competition be*
tween Texas cowboys and Argentine gauchos was
held at Buenos Ay res not long ago, and It Illus
trated the contrasting merits of each. The prise
for nerve and dash went to the North Americans,
while the gauchos scored on their careful treat
ment of the stock. The Texan system of knock
down and drag out with long lawns broke the
horns and limbs of cattle. The Argentlnos, using
short ropes, worked more slowly, but did not malm
their subjects. In bronco busting Texans and
gauchos came out even, for none of the contest
ants was thrown.
By Importing pedigreed stock from Europe Ar
gentina has rid herself of scrubby native animals
and covered her pampas with the best cattle,
horses, sheep and swine." On one ranch there are
17.000 head of fine cattle. 19.000. sheep and 2.000
horses. When ploughing is done on this ranch
there are forty-three ploughs In line, one behind
the other. All the farming machinery Is strictly
up to date. The products of such an estate are
loaded on oars which ;go direct to the enormous
gram elevators, stockyards, produce markets and
endless docks of Buenos Ayres. where the shipping
of the wori.l MMfl Us] United states— watts In
.the. Klv«r Plate to curry away the* rlehneS3 of the
pampas; v,^--.-
:i».
waving under the direct glimpses of the North Star.
I would suggest a popular subscription to equip and
send out an American Antarctic expedition."
All things be equal," said Mr. McOowan.
president of the Board of Aldermen and occasion
ally acting Mayor of New York, -I believe that the
hustling Americnn will be the flrrt to reach the
South Pole as he has reached the North Pole The
•pirn of push and progress, which Is innate in the
American. will compel him to search out the secrets
of the frozen south, and unless some of the foreign
ers get there before the necessary preparations can
be made by American explorers, we may look for
ward to giving a reception to the conqueror of the
Antarctic not long after welcoming the winners of
the Arctic prize. I think it would be well at the
Start to have rule, for discovering the South Pole
so as to avoid controversy as to who gets there
first. An international umpire ought to be sent
ahead of the explorers, it being understood that
his first arrival doesn't count. It seems to me that
this will be the greatest catch-as-catch-can enter
prise In modern history, and. of course, all my
is one.)- will be down on the fellows who carry the
Stars and Stripes with a package of tacks and a
hammer to nail It on to the hypoboreal stick. If
that Is the correct epithet. While it la a good
patriotic and sporting proposition. I confess I am
rather In the dark as ti> the scientific side, what
we will gain by finding that other axis or ex
tremity. I will just have to take the word of the
scientists that U is worth going after. The fact
that other nations are after it is also a good ex
cuse for us to get in the race. After we find It, we
will discuss what to do with it."
A "DOUBLE-HEADER" DESIRABLE.
Justice Francis B. Delehanty of the City Court
remarked
"It to an inspiring project to have the United
ERNEST H. BHACKLETON.
The man who has gone closest to th* South
Pole.
States crown both caps of the world with the Stare
and Stripes. What we have- done hi the north w*
can do In the south, and no harm If we repeat a
double-header discovery. Geographical science 1»
making quick hUtory these years. Within a brief
period the North V->>. the northern and southern
magnetic po'es and the Northwest Passage have
been discovered. an 4 the South Pole will soon be,
added to thea* trophies of science. Everything ia
propitious ;or great ac!'.levement9 in the Antarctic."
"Don't know much about It. but I would be glad
to see Americans ahead on the South Pole," satd
Public Service Commissioner Ma'.tble.
Writing in a bulletin of the American Geographi
cal Society. Kdwln Swift Balch speaks of the dis
covery of the coast of the Antarctic continent by
Lieutenant Charles Wilkes. of the United States
navy, on January 19, IMO. as "the greatest geo
graphical discovery of the nineteenth century."
Captain R- F. Scott, who led the British Discov
ery expedition of 130 1- O4, and ia now preparing
MANCHURIAN POMES HAVE PROVED THEIR VALLE IN iOL"H POLA* EXPLO
RATION.
tor another Antarctic Journey, tried to discredit
the existence of Wllkeo Land. He got oa taa oda»
of It. failed to see It. and steamed away north oa
th* plea that he was short of fuel. Scott says that
any ahip steaming on th* 178 th meridian la th*
month of February could reach th* groat bar
rlwr without encountering pack Ice. It Is string*
to think. he remarks, that there may be a siasiOi
of the year when the enterprising tourist steamer
may show Its passengers the lofty smeke-capaid
form of Mount Erebus as easily as It now does the
fine scenery of Spitsbergen. The same explorer
estimated that the Antarctic region waa sheathed
with an Ice cap nine hundred feet la thlekneo*. He
thought there was water, not land, under the Ice,
because a thermometer lowered Into crevasses
showed a rising temperature.
REMARKABLE DASH SOUTHWARD.
lieutenant Ernest H. Shackleton. who accom
panied Scott, and who later mad* a record oa
hie own account and now wants to try It again,
waa accompanied by three others when ho mad*
his dash for the South Pole last autumn, and
after a sledge Journey of 1.701 miles, lasting 131
days, got within Ul statute miles of the southern
axis, or 364 miles better than Scotts record. Th*
latitude reached was 88 degrees 23 minutes south.
Novelties of this expedition wer* a motor car with
runners, to pull trains of loaded sledges; Siberian
ponie*. Instead of dogs, and light woollen clothtac
la place of furs. The magnetic polo was located
by a special exploring party. KUht m
one hundred mount i
success on ■Booth Ice. and was valuable for dis
tributing supplies at various coast depots. to*
failed on the uneven to* of the barrier. Tsa
berlan ponies did good service. Four of them
were taken on the poleward dash; two were lost
In glacial crevasses, while two were eaten by th* I
hungry explorers. There were lons days of per
ilous travel on glaciers and plateaus from SUM to
10.100 feet In altitude. Constant bliszards and
drifting snow that cut like a razor hampered th»»
intrepid travellers. The wind blew up to* seventy
miles an hour, with "TO degrees of frost." This*
lasted for three days during; the southernmost en
campment, while the men were frostbitten even
as they lay in their fur-lined sleeping bags, From
here a vast plain extended southward, and no
mountains were visible. The explorers stood on a
plateau which immediately surrounds the southern
axis. On the return, "the high winds, which we**}
now blowing at our backs," says ihsiHsfcil
"helped us to travel from twenty to thirty Mttssa
dally." This story of a quick and assy return!
sounds like the narratives of the two discovers
of the North Pole. However, an attack of dysen-j
tery. due to horse meat, caused the oarty much*
suffering and kept them In camp eight days. Th»!
snow blown off the ice by the viol wind mad»!
the glaciers hard to traverse; also, the food raaj
short in the latter stages, and the explorers r«-f
gained their ship only by strenuous exertion^. The)
heavy winds encountered In tho polar vicinity!
show that the so-called "polar calm** Is a mrtt,
The atmospheric conditions doubtless constltst*!
the greatest hardship of an attack on th« souths**
axis. All explorers testify that degree? beiow
sero in a calm is not bad. while 19 degrees below
In a gale makes travelling Impossible.
NO PESTHOUSE FOE Unt m
Jersey Negro Resents Plan to E**
tabluh One Next Door,
James Day. of Madison. N. X. is a negro wit*
well denned Ideas of his rights of person and
property and the ability to lay complaints la writ
ing before the Common Council. He live* aesa>
door to a building which the Council wants to con
vert Into a pesthouse. and he objects very serious
ly. He also says that a brook near his home la sol
luted by the overflow from cesspools, and hi* re
marks on that subject are interesting. This Is t&oi
lettter he- has sent to the Council:
"My name is James Day. I have a wife and)
seven children. Our house Is on the power house*
road. We hear it said that the borough la going to
make a pesthouse of th* borough cottag* standing;
close by our home. We own our house. If you putt
the pesthouse close to us we shall own nothing.
Our home will not be worth anything to own.
'Maybe my wife, the children and I all get th*
pest. too, if you put it close to us. Nobody wants*
a pesthouse close by. A great many peop a goa
past my house to visit the power house and to oso>
the great springs of water. Now they will not aw
by any more. People walking up and down Mat*
street and a great many automobile peopl* will
fca.ve to go by this pesthouse. not far oS the* mats)
street. The automobile people can go around Madi
son and skip the pesthouse, but I and my people;
cannot go around. We have to walk close by ever*
time wa come in or go out.
"People say they do not think any pest pesptot
will ever be ready to go there, because) Maaasem
is healthy anywhere not near the Sprtnc Cardea
Brook. They say th* Board of Health or snip*
body knows two or three good persons willing; ta>
live In the pestnouae and to wait to take care at
anybody who dues not come there.
"Now. I pay tax on my house. I do not want
to have to pay people for being willing: to wait
for pesters to come there. Maybe only on* peso,
person a year, or less, will come, but th* pest
waiters at the house will get good pay all th*
time for waiting. 1 ask you to think whether th*
pay they get for waiting and th* rent of th* nous*
will not pay for the keep of several pesters at
the Morrtstown Hospital? I saw a hospital ther*
with some of it ready for pesters at any time, for
pay.
"I work hard all day through the daytlgnt, aad
I cannot see much about the borough, but I hava
been looking around It some oa »»""»»Hght. jr'gVtti
I as* a great many cesspool* nearly all of
■■■■II right into Sprint; Garden Brook.
"1 one* heard Lawyer mis* say that any con
who would let his' cesspool run Into a liva brook
could a* seat to state prison for It. Ha oaJi that
•Übbiru a brook In this way to kin it was wots*
than stabbing a man and killing hiss, because t»*
water from the sower brook was kUUaa; people all
th* time. Cswa drink the water, and children
drink th* milk. They tell at a cow can stand a
great d?a! without sayta* anything, but ta» doctor
says th* 'milk off thos* cows killed a baby.
"I hear some people say that *nobody living
near the' aostaoua*,' 1 and my family are living
there. We are somebody. If we are not watt*
people. Cod made us black, and I hear He flnlsheri
us off th* sasM as He did the whit* ones. The
difference la only this, that black people h.iv-t
been sweating a great who* for white people, and
they have not had time to learn much. IfbUctt
people Knew more they would sweat" less." But
because th* Stars and Stripes la now th* buck
mans flag It makes m* as good a* a white man—
I mean la a good many ways;. and 'living next to
a pesthoua* Is one of th* ways. Nobody want*
pesthouse for company. *f any whit* man wants
It he can have this on*."
r
THE OLD MAID'S CHANCE.'
you ever lose that umbrella o{ yours? 1
asked the maiden.
"No. 1 1 don't," replied the man, sternly; the per-,
son who takf«,that umbrella will have to take m«.
"Do I understand that to be a proposal of mar
riage or a threat?" inquired the miss sw
Philadelphia" lno,uirw:r.- T-r
n</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1912-03-08/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Amundsen+Pole+Scott</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Pole attained December 14-17, 1911. All well.'
"B0AID AHUHDSJiriV
Details of Capt. Amundsen's feat and the difficulty he had tcj
surmount are not jet to hand.
The cablegram vhich announces his triumph, which is reproduce J
in facsimile by the Chronicle, the Chronicle announces, was sent by'
the explorer's brother, Leon Amundsen, from Christiania. It alscf
announces that Capt. Amundsen's own story will be in hand to-morrow"
SHACKLETOV DISCUSSES ItEPOIlT
Sir Ernest Shackleton. In a later edlUon
of the Dslly Chronicle, writes the foUow.
lng on Amundsen's discovery;
'Analys'ng the somewhat brief cabl
to hand announcing Amundsen s
talnment of the south pole, one from
previous experience would assume that
the Journey was done with extreme rap
idity and under very favorable condi
tions as regards weather.
"Amundsen has attained the geo
graphical south pole, the long-sougbt-for
spot and finish ot record-breaking as far
the ends of the earth are concerned.
Auumlnr that the latitude of Amund
sen's vwlnter quarters were Jp-'TS.M 8,
that la only tK geographical rollts from
thesoufb pels.-- ThUplaee wsf-iamed
the uay ot wnaies oy me on my expeai
tlon and was formerly known as Balloon
Bight.
"If .Amundsen did fifteen miles a day
and reached the south pole on Decern
ber 14 he would have started south
about the beginning of November, but
It Is much more likely that ho did nou
travel at that rate, especially for the
first hundred or two odd miles, so we
may assume that he started for the
pole about the beginning of October.
There is no Indication In the cable
whether Amundsen followed the route
of my expedition In reaching the moun
tains that guard the approach to the
pole. It may be possible that he found
a new route, an easier one, up to the
plateau which lies about 9,000 to 11,000
feet above tbe sea level.
He may have bad good weather, and
the words ot the cable gram "Polo at
tained December 14 to 17." evidently
means that on reacting the geograph
ical polexso that no uncertainty should
exist as to his exact position, he waited
three days, taking; noon observations,
so as to accurately determine his posi
tion
"The advantage of taking three days'
continuous observations at the pole ore
as follows
"Assuming that the explorer took a
noon observaUon of the altitude of the
sun and found that he was at the pole.
a degree ot uncertainty would exist be
cause of the slow movement of the sun
which completes a circle wth hardly any
perceptible rise or falL If the observa
tion Is taken for the second da) at the
same spot and the difficulty of the decli
nation of the sun In Its north or south
path corresponds with his observations
of the dav before, and it does this lor
the third day. he ma safely assume that
his position is accurate A fl)lng snap
shot Is not as reliable as continuous
series of observations. If he were using
a theodotle. undoubtedly tha most accu
rate Instrument, there Is no douot tnat
he couM ascertain the position of the
line 10 one rauc
Conld Return In. Kortr-Ove Days.
lf Amundsen left tho pole on De
cember 17 with a fair wind behind him.
he could return to his winter quarters
In about fort) -five days.
"Wo left our furthermost south.
which was, roughly speaking, about 100
miles north of tho pole, on January 9,
and reached our winter quarters on
February:?. They were 6101 geograph
ical miles from the pole, approximately
the same length of journey that
Amundsen would have to cover from
the polo to his winter headquarters, as
they re 90 miles farther south.
TVe may then assume that If Amundsen
reached the Bay ot Whales, at the end
ot Januar. he would take two or three
da) a loading up and getting under way
with the Fram. -He would then presuma
bly go north and work to the westward
of Cape Adare and then get into westerly
winds and make Hobart. and the Fram.
bUng a slow vessel, doing about five
knots, would take quite a month, unless
strong winds were behind her, to reach
Hobart.
filnd. did Capt. Scott reach the pole be
fore December 117 Is so, the honor lies
with tho British flag, but the same en
durance, same skill In the same need ot
endeavor'mustbe, granted to Amundsi.1
as the Norwegian people would grant to
bcott It the position were reversed.
It would be quite possible that the
two expeditions, having reached Eeard
more Glacier, would be In touch with
each "other or would come across depots
which would indicate the advance or re
turn of either party, and It Capt. Scott
had let a party at the- foot ot the glacier;
they wouM naturally be acquainted with
Amundsen's movements, as Amundsen
would be had he left a party or a depot
In the omex position.
Star Hare? Met at role.
"There may hav a been a more dramatic
situation still- Two parties crossing the
glacier ana conversing toward the- cott
GETS CABLEGRAM
eted spot from different directions may
have met at the pole Itself. Amundsen's)
equipment, though not so large as
Scott's, has peculiar advantages when
you consider the nationality ot tha
expedition.
"The Norwegians who accompanied!
Amundsen are accustomed to tha drivinc
of dogs, and are born ski runners. The
broad stretches on tbe plateau and
the level stretches on tbe barrier
surface would be excellent for ski
ing. The dogs will keep up the rapid
nace wbch ski runners are able to adopc
and this is naturally faster than the slow
plodding foot movements of the ponies.
Amundsen had 112 dogs at tbe start, all
first-claaa and welTbrSken Inland thet
numbersunay ht been susplemented by
births Dnrlnamre"'lonr I$olar nights, to
tha this team may hare oeen considerably
i Increased before he started on his dash
I for the pole.
"Capt. Scott's party In the Terra,
Nova, who found Amundsen at the Bay
of Whales described the dogs as beta?
wonderfully trained, stopping or mov
Ingjpn at the sound of a whistle.
"No matter which party reached tho
pole first, both will have done much
po unveil the mystery of the south.
and to increase'lnterest and desire for
further work In this great unknown;
continent."
Hardest Journey on Earth.
New Tork, March 7. The trip down tha
bottom side of tbe earth In search ot
th coveted rero of exploration offered
the most perilous and desperate Journey
In the world. The explored regions or
the arctic short of the pole before its
discovery by Peary, had no terrors such.
as are offered by the antarctic, and when
the story ot Scott's achievement Is told
It Is expected to relate hardships under
widely different conditions from those
encountered by Peary on his lone marsh.
to uiB norm poie.
In the first place. If Scott found lhe
south pole he almost certainly discovered
It high in the air at the top of a great Icy
plateau where the winds from au tho
seas meet and make sport at least 10,000
feet above the level of the frozen sea.
Colder Thau Aorth Pole.
It has been given to few men to attala
this plateau, and their experiences in a
cold more bitter by far than any other
encountered in the far north. In highly
rarefied air ard buffeted by diabolical
billiards and awed by weird electrical
storms, were forbidding enough to dis
courage any others were It not for the
Irresistible call ot the unknown and the
fact that the hard road led to fame.
A second condition for consideration;
in entering the circle containing- 50,
000 square miles of practically unex
plored area of the earth's surface 1st
that It Is dead country as dead and
unfit for habitation as the moon pro
tected from intrusion upon its soil-
tudes by a great barrier of Ice backed
by mountains that nature seems to
have thrown up to make Impregnable,
the secret of the fashioning of the
world.
But because of these conditions tha
goal of tho south pole became the one
great attainment unachieved of man.
and. In spite of them the last two years
lias seen a. race for the south pole, with;
at last four nations at one time com
peting, which at the end resolved Itself.
Into an actual physical straggle be
tween the expeditions of Capt- Scott
the -head of the English explorers, and
Capt. Roald Amundsen and his hardy
company of Norwegian adventurers and,
scientists.</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1912-03-08/ed-1/?sp=1&q=AMUNDSEN+Amundsen+SOUTH+POLE+SCOTT</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>"Pole at
tamed December 14-17, 1311. All well.
Iloald Amundsen.'
The Chronicle also publishes an arti
j cle from Captain Sliaikelton on Amund
i sen's achievement, saying:
naylzing somewhat the brief cable
announcing -Amundsen's -attainment« of;
the :-south-'-pole; one from previous ex
peri^me would- assume 'theJjoumQy.y'waS:
done, in extreme rapidity and under very
favorable "i 5 conditions as regards
■weather. Assuming that the latitude
of Amundsen's winter quarters was
78.44 S., that is only 676 geographical
miles from the pole. This place: was
named the Bay of Whales on my ex
pedition.
Started About October
"If Amundsen did 15 miles a day and!
reached the pole on December 14 he
would have started south about the
beginning of November, but it is much
more likely that he did not travel at
that rate, especially for the first 100
or -00 odd miles, so we may assume ho
started for the pole about the begin
ning of October. There is no indica
tion whether Amundsen followed the
route of my expedition in reaching tho
mountains that guard the approach to
the pole.
"It may be possible he found a new
route and an easier one up to the
plateau. Which lies about 90,000 to
100.000 feet above sea level.
"Word that the pole was attained
December 1* to 17 evidently means oa
reaching the geographical pole he
waited three days, taking the noon ob
servation, so as accurately to determine
his position."
Fram a Slow Vessel
Continuing, Shaekelton said that, if
Amundsen left the pole December 17
he would very likely, with a fair wind
behind him, return to winter quarters
i in about 45 days.
'"We then assume," continued the ex
plorer, "that Amundsen reached the bay
of Whales at the end of January. He
would take two or three days loading
and getting under way with the Fram,
and would then presumably go north
and work to westward of Cape Adare,
then get into westerly winds and make
Hobart. The Fram being a slow ves
sel, doing about five knots, wouid take
a month, unless strong winds were be
hind her, to reach Hobart.
Was Scott There First
"The question arises in one's mind:
Did Captain Scott reach the. pole before
December 1?>? If so the honor lies
with the British flag, but the same en
durance and skill and meed of endeavor
</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058397/1912-03-08/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Amundsen+SOUTH+POLE+Scott</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>g I Norwegian Explorer, and Not Scott of the British
l Expedition, Is First to Reach the Southern
si I most Point of the Earth
iw -I
W i
II uIoLuVlKi So III wIsilKLII, I mwlAN I


1 r Journey Is Made With a Picked Crew of Arctic
i Men and Siberian Dogs Amundsen Famous
For Trip Through Northwest Passage
1157 f
5 Hobart, Tasmania, March S Cap-
tain Roald Amundsen, the Norwegian
is explorer, denies having telegraphed
ti anything of Captain Scott or the Bilt-
Ish" expedition.
6 Captain Amundsen, up to the pres
ti ent. Is the only member of the Ant
I arctic expedition who has landed from
the Fram. Nobody Is allowed to go
i( on board the vessel under any pre
A text whatsoever.
l f The explorer says he Is pleased with
If the results of his expedition, but oth-
Sj erwise maintains absolute sllenco on
j the subject. Captain Amundsen In-
I tends to stay at Hobart for a few
davs. He will go to Australia and give
Jt a few lectures there, afterwards de-
,Tfi; partlns for Europe.
1 ijj
iHi
S Will Aid Weather Men.
9 Chicago, March S. "The discovery
p of the South Pole, besides being a
ml geographical achievement, will enable-
4g i i scientists to make long time weather
i' predictions, which has been an object
of work for centuries," said Prof. T.
a C Chamberlain, head of the depart-
ril? ment of ecology of the University of
Si I Chicago today.
m .J "Heretofore we have been enabled
3 j to traco the winds and storms up un-
ji i til the time 'they entered the Antarc-
l4 tic circle. At this point wo lost trace
jpji T of them absolutely and do not know
fa if whero to watch for theln reappernce
SjSj It now becomes possible to make a
I complete map of thewlnd movements
5 f over the face 'of tho globe."
1
5i t Comments on Discovery.
Hi New York, March S. Herbert L.
lU; Brldgman, president of the Arctic Club
w of America, expressed little surprise
F? when he received the news that Am
S& undsen's dash to the South Pole had
Sk been successful.
t, "I have been in tho business too
If long," he said. "Nothing can surprise
me very much. Even since I knew
J that anybody was making a serious
try at the South Pole I was confident
I that the discovery would be .made. I
Tather expected tht it would be Scott
nrpj and I shouldn't wonder at U if wo
jgg should hear from him In a fow days
Eli that he had reached the pole also.
-w j "I have a very high opinion of Am
tKJ.: undsen. He has shown that he was
EC a fine navigator, and in earnest As
rte, far as tho comparative difficulty of
ritSf f finding the two poles was concerned,
E&ir there is no question In my mind thnt
i the attainment of the South Pole was
jSj much easier than tho North.
gtH "Europe has looked upon the South
i Polo as her own Held of exploration.
3$: It was agreed at the International con
312,'; ference of 1905 that the North Pole
ip: should be left to the Americans.
pjrijjj. "The most important thing is that
IRS;! the dashes and races are over and
Ifiji hereafter explorers will go out serl
JS5rl ously to discover the facts about the
edjt earth. In time the map will be wlth
juw 7 out any unknown land."
5iJJ Anthony Fiala, secretary of the Ex
o(f lilorers club, and commander of the
gl J North Pole expedition in 1903-05, said.
$5 j "I am glad Amundsen won It Is
lK likely that Scott, too, mar have reach
tjSl ed the goal. If so, he was probably
jJU! a week or two later than Amundsen.
jVpf Scott could hardly fall In his attempt,
$g for his party was equipped as has been
gP? no other party that ever penetrated
gm polar regions."
oJif Believes In Amundsen.
ifi&i Prof- Henry aFirfield Osborn, head
aSr 0f the Amer,CJln MiiBeum .of Natural
im History, which has contributed to tho
3Bt equipment of several American polar
S"pj expeditions, Bald that his study of the
M Pjans of the naval explorers had con-'
TGH vlnced him that Amundsen would win.
J:' r,"0no lUns ls certain." said Prof.
iiSSk Bhorn- "There will bo no controversv
h.iVlS lDQ acci,racy of Amundsen's
I c,laim- H baB a world-wide repnta-
hi& ."v." and ficentlst3 will believe him
J 5g f without hesitation."
?hfij Captain Bradley S. Oshon, former
t k secretar.v f the Arctic club, who Is a
d1 pIm J161"8?"31 fr'end of Amundscv.
Zi 1 M.,d, wncn ho lieard the news:
pm u l' 1 k,l0W he wou,d d It- The
SHi Lhu8(n?r n,ennt anything In my
frfi 1 "!lnd ubut victory for Amundsen. Ho
Tdi1 n.fc ,mosL experienced of the varl
ndll ;;S,rJVttls and he kncw tie Ice packs
B I mer does hlB "elds."
'Wm tn- Cook ,s 'nterviewed.
t noS; e.d.er,ck A. Cook heard the
'll 4 JUu reV,rn;d froiu a lecture tour.
i and v,," nly P088ib,c 1Dal scott
'S f, d WMn crossed each other, b-it
'?5? oLB- 5kK Sat b01 mc "oi at the
01 Si tt .8ald Dr- Copk- wii a snilf,
J to W.0? at th VOr ,alt ought
5S V heard from In ten days."
dM At thC Ple Threo Day3'
101 lnrC;,)r,5t,anla' Norway, March S.-Tvo
W$k' )BtrLnT8,,a,,,erB loda' received l8
iftS S' roi" Captain Roald Amundsen
VgbOg announcing that he reaqhed the South
oatcheB were sent from Hobarl? Tas"
n

mania, where Amundsen arrived yes
terday The dispatcnes read-
"Polo reached fourteenth-seventeenth
December."
This evident- means that he re
mained three days in tho vicinity of
tho polo, probably for the purpose of
taking accurate observations as to his
position.
Saw Scott Jan. 19, 1911
London, March S. Captain Roald
Amundsen states he will submit his
charts and all Information concornlng
his expedition without delay, accord
ing to despatches from Hobart re
ceived by a special correspondent at
"Wellington.
After meeting Captain Scott in the
Bav of Whales on January 1!). 1911,
Captain Amundsen camped with nine
men In longitude 161 west, latitude
7S He has not revealed his subse
quent movements
Captain Amundsen hns settled his
plans to sail from Hobart within a
week for Buenos Ayres. From thero
he will go round Cape Horn to San
Francisco and then on to Bering
I Straits. Then he will drift with the
Ice across the Arctic ocean and ex
pects to emerge at some point be
tween Greenland and Spitsbergen.
Captain Scott's agent In New Zea
land expresses the opinion that Scott
must have changed his plans and
proceeded with new exploring and
scientific work, thus possibly delay
ing his return some week.
The Royal Geocraphlcal society ac
cepts unqualifiedly Captain Amund- j
Pole, and takes It for granted that
he was tho first explorer to reach
the goal, although Amundsen's brief
despatch does not mention that fact.
"Geographers point out, however,
that Captain Amundsen and Captain
Scott may both have been there with
in a mile of each oilier without know
lug it and scientists here are await
ing further details before accepting
definitely the defeat of the British
expedition. Tho messnge received
yesterday by tho London Dally Ex
press from Wellington, in which Cap
tain, Amundsen was reported as say
ing that Scott had reached the pole,
was based on a telegram alleged to
have been sent by the Norwegian ex
plorer but the authenticity of which
Captain Amundsen today denies.
In response to cabled Instructions
to ask Captain Amundsen point blank
whe'her Captain Scott reached tho
South Pole, the correspondent of the
London Evening Star at Hobart to
day telegraphed the following state
ment: "Amundsen refuses to say anything
as to whether Scott reached the
South Polo or not,''
i
Life of Amund6en
New York, Jlarch 8. The confirma
tion of Captain Roald Amundsen's at
tainment of tho South Pole on De
cember 14, 1911, received today from
the explorer himself, at Hobart, Tas
mania, sets at rest tho conflicting re
ports current on the subject yester
dav. A despatch published by ttio
Dally Express -in London yesterdav
morning, dated Wellington, N. de
clared that '.Amundsen .staldd."' that
Scott had reached tho'- South PoVe.
It was assumed that this declaration
Indicated that Amundsen himself had
not succeeded in attaining the object
of his expedition and the, credit wan
given generally to the British ex
plorer. Nothing heretofore has been
heard from Scott and Amundsen now
denies that he said or telegraphed
anything referring to his British rival
or his expedit on. The honor of the
achievement of reaching the South
Pole must now bo clven to tho Nor
wegian explorer until Captain Scott
announces the result of his expedi
tion. Captain Amundsen for many
years has been considered one of tho
most daring and competent of Arctic
and Antarctic explorers. A sailor
from his 'youjh, ho started Polnr re-
search at tho age of 2n, when he par
tlcipatcd in tho Bolgic Antarctic ox- I
pedlllon under commander of Gerlach.
Ho was the first officer of the esscl.'
and the voyage lasted from 1897 to -i
1899. j
Upon his return, Amundsen decided
to continue Polar research, but this
time to go to the north In an endeav
or to discover tho Northwest passage.
Ho prepared himself hv undergoing
a course of study In magnetism, and
mo'eorology. Ho sailed for tho north
from Chrlstianla on hoard the Gjona</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1912-03-09/ed-1/?sp=1&q=AMUNDSEN+Amundsen+POLE+SCOTT+Scott</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>AMUNDSEN TELLS OF
DASH TO THE POLE
Conquering Norwegian Describes Finding of
Antarctic Goal in Wide Plateau After
Final Plunge Through 1er
HAS NO WORD FROM CAPT. SCOTT
Explorer Grown-*? His Triumph bv Naming Vast Expanse
of Frozen South in Honor of His King?Accomplishes
Perilous Journey with Remarkable Speed,
Accompanied by Four Companions.
[By ?'?tile to Th? Tribune 1
Undon, March 9. 'Th? Daily Chronicle" this ?morning punlii-hes
th? first instalment of Captain Roald Amundsen's account of his dis?
covery of the South Pole. The interest excited by the news of this
great feat wa> sufficient to keep thousands of person* out of bed until
copies of "The Daily Chronicle" could be secured early this morning.
There was no spirit apparent of distrust as to the accuracy of Captain
Amundsen's claim. In the dubs men familiar with the Antarctic re?
s-ions pointed to his clear, connected narrative and his exact description
of the care with which the observa-ions at the Pole were taken as
abundant proof of the truthfulness of his claim.
Captain Amundsen describes the long journey over the great ice
barrier and tells how he followed the outline of South Victoria and King
Edward Land. A great mountain range which stretches across this
region, the general direction of which he followed, he named the Queen
Maud Range. The hardy explorer docs not devote many words to
his descriptions of his feelings upon arriving at the Pole, but there is
just sufficient vagueness with regard to details to suggest that he
share?l the great discovery with others. He says that he left his winter
quarters, on the Hay of Whales, on October 20.
After crossing the great ice barrier and following the mountain
mines, he arrived December 8 at Shackleton's Farthest South. Follow?
ing the due southern direction, he came to a great plateau in six days'
march. This plateau, which he reached on December 14, was a vast
plain, monotonous in its appearance, stretching for miles in every
direction.
_ Fixed Position of Pole on Third Day.
Observations showed that the party was in latitude 89 degrees 55
minutes South. On December 15 the party travelled nine kilometres
in as near as possible a direct southerly line. Observations taken at
the point then reached on December 15 and the following day fixed
this as the approximate position of the Pole. A hut was erected here
and the Norwegian flag hoisted. It remained as the only evidence of the
discovery when the trip back began.
The Pole was in the midst of the great plateau, which Amundsen,
in honor of the King of Norway, named King Haakon Flateau.
The expedition was favored by unusually fine weather, and the
party was able to make an average of thirty-five kilometres a day
i:Pole and thirty-six kilometres a day on the return journey.
The distance from the winter quarters at the Bay of Whales to the
Pole was approximately fourteen hundred kilometres. The highest
point of the mountains crossed was 10,750 feet above sea level, at 87
?legrces 40 minutes South latitude.
Amundsen started on his dash to the Pole on October 20 and
returned to his quarters on January 21. The party consisted of five
men, four sledges and fifty-two dogs.
Amundsen's full story of his stirring achievement leaves no noom
for doubt that he reached the South Pole on December 14. He does
not, however, make any reference to Scott, and the judgment of experts
here as to the value of the Norwegian's expedition is supended until
the English explorer's story can be told and the truth can be known
whether both rivals were at the Pole and who was there first. The
Central News will have a copyright of Scott's story when it comes,
and meanwhile Amundsen's narrative, as published in "The Daily
Chronicle," will be mainly interesting as bearing upon the marches of
two explorer?? for the same goal.
No light has vet been thrown on this central fact. All the world
now wants to know whether Scott reached the Pole at all. and if he
reached it whether he reached it before December 14. If he reached
it later the Norwegian can'claim the conquest of the Pole, but if before
December 14. and two or three miles separated the parties, then Eng?
land can claim the prize.
Might Have Missed Each Other's Mark.
Sir Krnest Shackleton says if Scott has reached ?M pole at the same time
or bef??re Amundsen there is a possibility that if cairns made by the respe? me
explorers to indicate the attainment of their object were not more than six or
eight feet high either party might miss the other's mark.
Amundsen, in taking possession and in planting the NofVegian flag at the
South Pole and naming the plateau after King Haakon. was presumably un?
aware that Shackleton had named the same plateau after King ?Edward VII.
Thus there was an error m his part in nomenclature, which he will no doubt
remedy when he becomes aware of the true facts of the case.
In ?letermining his exact position at the pole. Amundsen used a sextant and
artificial horizon, which for actual efficiency in very high latitudes is not ,o.
absolutely accurate as a theodolite, but Shackleton admits that if Amundsen
located his position with no more possible error than two ?>r three mile- ?me
way or the other he has certainly left footsteps on tha>t point from which every?
thing bear** north
Amundsen states that professional men can work out his observations, but
there will be no nee?l for this except for minor corrections. It is obvious that
Amundsen has conquered the geographical South Pole. The march back was
accomplished without difficulty, in splendid weather and in record time
The most remarkable thing about this whole journey has been the spee?!
with which it was made Amundsen returned to winter quarters safe and well,
having experienced during the whole trip generally fair weather. A subsidiary
?party at work at King Kdward Land brought back geological specimens, the
arrival of which in the hands of experts will be eagerly awaited by the scientific
world. Por the summing up of the geographical results, Shaokleton considers
thev are of the highest importance. Amundsen has covered entirely ne*v
ground thr-ni-f-hout the whole journey. He ha? defined the limits of the great
ice barrier which had been unknown to men till now. His work in pure science
will not be so extensive as Scott's, but his geographical work is undoubtedly
of equal importance._
AMUNDSEN 4 DAYS AT POLE
Explorer Stirs Norway with News of His
Antarctic Discovery.
Christiania. March 8.?All Norway is
?flame with enthusiasm over the dlscov
Pole by Roald Amund?
sen. It? great explorer. The news of the
wondn-us achievement stirred the land
as H has not been stirred In years, and
from one end of the country to the other,
fiom tho King to the meanest subject,
hardihood of the Vikings?rewound! In
unstinted measure to-night
It matters little whether Captain Scott.
the British navigator, reached the covet?
ed goal. too. Norwegian?, now that the
fait of discovery by their national h?ro
ha? been definitely established, are con?
fident that he wu the first to reach th?
pral?? i'?>" Nor*???*ian hardihood?the pole, and whether or not Captain ?Scott</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1912-04-01/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Amundsen+SCOTT+Scott+POLE+Pole</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>SCOTT LOSES RACE
TO SOUTH POLE
British Explorer Still 150 Miles
from Goal on January 3?
Amundsen There in
December.
TERRA NOVA COMES NORTH
Antarctic Vessel Reaches Akaroa,
a Harbor in New Zealand,
with Message from
H?ad of the
Expedition.
WILL STAY ANOTHER YEAR
Keen Disappointment Expressed in
England When News Arrives That
Even if Scott F.eaches His Goal
the Norwegian Will Have
Preceded Him.
Wellington. New Zealand. March -".1
Captain Robert F Scott? vessel, the
Terra Neva, which tarried the British
?iredition to the Antarctic, has arrived
at Akaroa. a harbor in Bank's Peninsula.
Kg? Zealand, bul has not brought back
Captain Bcott or the membera ot hla ex?
pedition. TN commander of the Terr i
Noca brought instead the following brief
message from Scctl
"I am re^aiii^a in the Antarctic for
anether winter in order to continue an
comolete my work
The J?test news ?ent hack bj fapt&tn
fjcott to hi- ??ase al MoMurdo Sound
?h^ed thai on Januar?/ 3 be bad
reached a Doint 150 m?les from the South
Pole and was still advane'nq. Amurtd
Mn reached the pole in the third week
of Dacembe-.
It was clear that had the explorer de?
layed ?ending: back notification <>f his
propres? until he actually reached the
pole news from him could not have been
received h> the Terra Nova before she
wan compelled i" leave, owing to the
setting Ir of "inter and the free-zing of
the Ross
All on board the Terra Nova arc well.
Great difappointment vas fell when it
became known thai the Scott par?: had
been left behind. The Terra Nova is pected to reach Ly l tel ton on Wednesday.
(By CaMe 10 Tti.- Trii.unr I
London. April 1.?News has at last
been received from Captain Scott The
Terra Nova hag arrived at Akaroa. New
Zealand, and though the vessel did not
bring the British evplorcr he sent a
message staling that he was proposing
to remain In the Antarctic for another
?inter in order to finish his work.
On Januarv 3 he was only 130 miles
from the ]>o!e. but it is unknown yet
?nether he emulated Amundsen's feat.
At the time his message was dis?
patched he was still advancing, and hit?
oistaner at that moment from the polo
?as Just thirty-eight miles greater than
th* southernmost point attained by Si;
Ernest Shackletoi?.
The Terra Nova left London on ,)une
1, 1?MO. und sailed from New Zealand on
Kov-mher '.ft IfMo. Scott's plan was to
lea. h the Sont). Pole by the route fol?
lowed by Sh; cklcion across the barrier
and up the Beardmore Glacier to the
Polar Plateau. He reached the Bay of
^'hales on February 11)11. and there
found Amundsen'? ship, th*. Fram.
The Tena Nova returned to New Zea
?U.d iron! the South, leaving Scott to
??ae his di-sli fo, (he pole.
teandsen pursuing different route
fan Brott'?, retched the South Pole o*i
Decerr.tn-r Ji Scott planned to rend?
the pole on December 22. but twelve
later, at w- now see, 'ie was still
W miles from his goal
Britiih Hopes Shattered.
?a ion*: and Impatiently awaited
n*?s ?f c?,|,idlll s.ot. will bring the
keenest disappointment lo the cherished
hr,Peaof nil Englishmen that ib.- British
?Apedition might after all prove to by
Ifat in the race for the South Bole.
slnce th? p, us ,,f Amundsen* sue
cettaful attempt Kngliahmen have ?uiilt
?"cat hupe? on Captain Scott emulating,
?urj*as?lng. the Norwegian's
i..< m II was known that Scott
M ?hosen th. longer ionio. and. .?s
Anmndaeiis experience proved. ih<- more
HfikvH route, but. presuming that h<
?as favored by the same exceptional
?eat her cond it lona as Amundsen, few
??"bled his success.
There win now be further weary wait
hi hl It ?an be known whether he
In n aching the- po|e A-
of Captain Scott's inti
?ts fiieiuli? here, however, no surpris?
bt ."it at his de ision to spend an
winter i? the south, this having
fclthir. ti.r original scope of his in
">ns T!.e> suagent that he mav
W*i kar.-ied o! mino-, ir? exploit and
tn*r*U|.. i, T-rnbued t.. attempt K,eat
111. ice na.rle- (-turning
win the ,ii(i(. almost opposite to that
which h? atarte?! hla Journey.
If this i? the Terra Nova probably
instructions t.. meet Captain
ott ai ?on,,, nxed date at a point on
barrier op|0.-?te ?Siaham Land, not
r Hie ?.nth of i ip.rn. It will
??"numbered thai the Coring i
W**, Lieutenant r'llchner, tf o)
1 JWm Hint side, and in that
I *?[*ll,ly ,1'*- t?" punies may m set
*aaio.-. Hail,.,;, when the Tsrrq
an.hoi. i> ,|W. (.ttgtcrl
South bland ?f Nov.
|?Snd. alne st en the forty-fourth parallel
g? rauth latitude/.,!,* degree of latitude
?pher south than H.,i,:iri. Tasmania,
g"h?r? ?aptain Amundsen reponed on
P>*h 7 laut.</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1913-01-11/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Amundsen+AMUNDSEN+Pole</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Amundsen, Discoverer of the
Pole, Given Royal Welcome Here,
Pitys Warm Tribute to Predecessors
Famous Explorer in First Public Lecture in America Before
National Geographic Society, Details Thrilling Dash to
Pole, Before Audience of 2,000 Persons.
Paving eloquent and unstinted tribute to the great work -iccompli'-Iied bv tbosc who preceded him
in their quest for the south pole and mentioning paraticuhrlv the names of (.apt St-ott ind Capt bliack
clton ind concluding with the statement that he a proud to be permitted to stand on the imc plat
lorni lroni which the dicoerer 01 the north pole dnnral I'earv, had addressed the atioml Geo
graaphic ocietv Capt Raold niumlci dthered his hrst public lecture in menca before an audience
01 2 000 persons
I ullv nn hour hetorc the tune set tor the lecture the luditornun hi crowded with "senators md
Representaties members ot the Cabinet justices of the buprenic Court arnn ind m officer-. Ing'i
government omcials- cientit business men financiers, artits societ people and workingmcn who
awaited the arrival of the famous explorer
v llecrlvrn Great Ovation j</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085187/1913-02-10/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Robert+Scott</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THIS remarkable diagram shows the course followed by Captain Scott in his dash for the South
Pole; also the route followed by Lieutenant Shackleton who, prior to Scott and Amundsen's
successful quest of the South Pole, made the Antarctic exploration record. Photographs of Cap
tain Scott and his boat used in the visit to the polar seas.
Captain Robert Scott was an officer of the British navy, the scion of a famous English naval
family. He commanded the "Discovery" expedition in the Antarctic regions, 1902-1904, planting
the British flag at 82 degrees, 17 minutes south.
Sir Ernest Shackleton, who in 1908 reached within 111 miles of the pole, was a member of
Scott's first expedition.
Scott's latest polar expedition cost over $200,000, subscribed by British people and government.
Scott sailed from London on the Terra Nova June 1, 1910, stopping at New Zealand on his way
to Ross sea in the Antarctic region.
The Terra Nova is the largest and strongest of the old Scottish whalers. It was built at Dundee
in 1884, and was 187 feet long and 32 in beam.
Since 1903 the Terra Nova has been engaged in polar trips, having been in both the Arctic and
Antarctic regions.
MRS. SCOTT ON WAY BY
SHIP TO GREET HUSBAND
(By United Press L»nsed Wire.)
SAX FKANCISQO, Feb. 10.—
Mrs. Kobert F. Scott of l.onilon,
wife of Captain Scott, tlie Urit
ish explorer, who is reported to
have met (leatli at McMnrdo
sound with the other member*
of his Si hi ih .polar .expedition,
sailed from this port last Wednes
day on the Aorangi for New Zea
land to welcome her husband.
Before leaving, Mrs. Scott pre
dicted that her husband would
not reach civilization for at least
BELIEVES SCOTT IS ALIVE
(By United Press INEW YORK, Fob. 10. —"I con
sider It most unlikely that Cap
tain Scott is dead," said Ernest
Shackleton here today when in
formed of reports from New Zea
land that all of the Scott party
had perished at McMurdo sound.
"I was reported dead on one
near Tacoma and the father
got a job in a big shop in the
city.
The family went along just
as other families do.
John Record was a good,
steady workman, but he didn't
save much money and when
Blanche, the daughter, grew
to be seventeen she thought
that she's rather go to work
than continue in her studies in
school.
Then one day disaster over
came the little family.
John Record contracted
pneumonia and within a week
they laid htm away In the quiet
necropolis where he will
sleep till eternity is done.
The bulk of the support fell,
then, on the daughter
Blanche.
She was a winsome, sweet
faced young girl and "took'
with folks.
THE ONLY INDEPENDENT NEWSPAPER IN TACOMA
TACOMA, WASHINGTON, MONDAY, FEBRUARY 10, 1913.
tWO months.
"Consequently," added Mrs.
Scott, "I expect to reach the an
tipodes in ample time to greet
him and hear his story of his
three-year experiences in the
South pole regions from his own
lips. I expect our meeting to take
place at one of the South New
Zealand ports.
"I am confident that while
Amundsen beat my husband's
expedition to the pole, that the
fault did not lie with Capt.
Scott.
trip. So was Amundsen. In any
event, I don't think Scott could
have died in a blizzard. It m
practically impossible for one to
perish in a blizzard if he- is
equipped against it. 1 will not
believe that Scott has perished
until I hear something more defi
nlte."
First she got a job in big
store behind the counter; as
her outside acquaintanceship
grew she had better opportuni
ties.
For awhile she worked as
an attendant In a doctor's of
fice, but later on took an en
gagement in a wholesale house.
In this new place the son of
the "boss" was employed as a
sort of general assistant to hla
father. He was a well-dressed,
polished young chap and knew
the things of the world.
Blanche Record did not.
So the young man, the Boss*
son, and Blanche Record be
gan to go to theaters once in
a while; the Boss's son took
her to a couple of dances and
then Blanche threw up her job.
She didn't tell her mother
—it would only worry her.
She had a lot of new pretty
clothe* and she gave her
PEOPLE PACK CHAMBER;
CITY DELAYING ACTION
COUNCIL CMAMIIKKS THKON (JKI> THIS MORNING TO AWAIT
ACTION OF COMMISSIONKKS OX MUNICIPAL STHKKT
CAH ONE—MANAGER KHAN AItKKNT— MEETING PUT
OFF TIM; AFTKRNOON— PBOPLK OIUKCT TO FItAX
CHISK UJtAMTNti—I'KKFKK MUNICIPAL 11OA1>.
With the council chamber packed with citizens oiiger on the
municipal street railway pro|K>sition for the (idciluts this morning,
M:m.imi Itejin did not show up to present un application for a
franchise.
He sent a request to meet the council this afternoon and the
council set o'clock for the sitting.
"Well, we'll he back," said a citizen who was disappointed at
not getting a chance at the tiling this morning.
The interest in the proposition was very evident from the sen
timents expressed by the |K-ople present when they were ilistippoint
e«l at not having the matter brought up.
"We want this line as a start
er for municipal ownership; It Is
a great chance for the city," said
one.
"We want it extended over to
Dash Point/ insisted a property
owner in that section.
j There is little likelihood that
I any settlement will be reached
with the street railway company
for some time.
.Commissioner Mills told the
cftUens this morning that for one
he .was for getting a line onto the
flats at the earliest moment and
that he would-insist that any
franchise granted the old com
pany had a common user clause
mother more money .every week
than she had ever earned be
tpre.
I True, the mother was wor
ried and thoughtful occasion
ally. Blanche didn't come home
qii the evening interurban
once or twice a week, but al
ways telephoned that she
would stay in town that night.
"Don't worry about me.
piamnia," she said. "I'm go-
Ing to the show tonight and
stay in town with one of the
other girls at the office."
j And bo things went on.
But one fine day, the Boss
found that his son was spend
ing altogether too much money
for a young chap.
He asked for a check oftener
than the old gentleman thought
should be necessary.
And when the Boss looked
into things he learned that his
boy wa» racing along the
HOME EDITION
in it and Mint the city might take
it over at any time.
This did not make a hit. The
people present seemed to warn
no franchise in it at all. They
want the line.
Mayor Seymour suggested that
it was largely a matter of
finances.
It is believed the finances, how
ever, can be raised if the peojite
want the line.
Commissioner Nick Lawson is
absolutely for the municipal line.
"It is the only way to bring
the company to time on other
matters," says Nick.
wrong path—and as usual, tbe
Girl was blamed.
The Boss sent his son away
a few week ago—sent him east
"on business" and the young
man wasn't a bit sorry to go.
for that matter..
And this pitiful little letter
came to the mother from her
little girl: '^..v-
"Dear Mamma:
sS "I can't bear to tell you how
I. have been deceiving you all 1
this time.;,; Him I have Rot. to
tell yon good-bye now, anyway,
for I am going to go j away
somewhere and forget all about 1
everything. l»«.n't j. blame any
body bat me-Mt Is all my fault.
IJ am i sorry—l would die: If I
had the courage, 's, Good-bye,''
dear mamma.. o BIjANCHB."
Rather ian ordinary, sordid i
story, you My. i Jl v.>
4 Surely so, surely so. v,-.';^jiv'
EDITORIALS tersely and plainly
written on the great throbbing
topic of the day—by men who
have a peculiar gift for penetrating
these subjects—are exclusive daily
Times features.
BLIZZARD IS
CAUSE OF
DISASTER
(IHI;I;KTIN)
(Ry Vnited P(«M Leaned Wire.)
LONDON, Feh. I(l.—<'apt. Hubert K. Null, Hritish explorer
and four of his il."> companions m an e\|»edltion to the Houtli
|K>le, are dead. This, so far as run be learned hy fragmentary
dispatches from New Zealand late tonight, is Uie truth sifted out
of a mass of reports rcretveil today which at tir-i were taken u>
declare that every mnn with Scott had met death in an antara
tic bli/./.ard at MrMurdo sounii.
LONDON', Feb. 10. —According to dispatches r
ceived here today, Captain Robert P. Scott and fAk
entire exploration party of 66 men perished in a
blizzard on their return journey, after having at
tained the South Pole.
According to the advices which have been con
firmed. Captain Scott and his party reached the
South Pole on January IK, 1012, and were on them
return journey when a terrible blizzard overtook:
them.
Before shelter could l>e thrown up, the entird
party was frozen to death.
The tragedy was learned today
when the antarctic rescue sh:p
Terra Nova returned to Oamuru,
New Zealand, and cabled the In
telligence to London.
A second Central News dis
patch said that Captain Scott and
his companions did not die until
they had a6coniplished the object
of the expedition. Records found
at McMurdo sound show Scott
reached the South pole January
IS, 1912, but on his return to his
base of supplies, the entire party
was overtaken by a fierce bliz
zard and frozen to death before
sufficient shelter could be pre
pared.
The Central News' had a con
tract for the exclusive publication
of Scott's account of his expedi
tion and the agency's reports of
the exploder's death are gener
ally credited here.
It is believed GC scientists and
6ailors lost their lives.
News liy Wireless.
This information, flashed by
wireless from the relief ship Ter
ra Nova today to Wellington,
Now Zealand, reached London
within an hour afterward and
created a sensation exceeding
anything the city has experienced
within a decade.
Only a brief outline of the
polar tragedy has so far been re
ceived. The Terra Nova wire
lessed, however, that records
found with the dead bodies of the
explorer and his men told the
story of their achievements ana
of their fate. After reaching the
pole, these records declared, Scott
and his party returned to their
depot at McMurdo sound but ar
rive there In the midst of a howl
ing blizzard with the temperature
so low that human beings could
not long survive the cold.
No ilcliiils have jet l>ecn
learned of who wrote the last few
v»-orlittle infoi'inution liiik been
gleaned as to how the liodles were
found. Only laconic mcftKnges
from tlie Terra Nova tliat she was
returning nftcr "i\ great caliwii
ity" and the unsatisfactory In
formation that Scott and all his
companions were dead tian yet
reached the world its n (trim fore
tnste of one of the greatest of
polur tragedies.
Messages reaching Wellington,
New Zealand, later, gave scatter
ing details of the Scott disaster
which, while not positive, make
it almost certain that G6 lives
were lost In the bitter antarctic
cold.
It has been learned, however,
But In a little town a few
miles out of Tacoma there is
a mother with a great ache in
her heart.
She watches every inttrnr
ban train as it stops near her
windows every day, and every
night she keeps a light burn
ing in the front window for her
little girl.
She doesn't care what has
happened; she doesn't care he
cause her child was just a
daughter of old Mother Eve
and was tempted—and fell.
She wants her back, though,
to cuddle up on her broad
breast and comfort and cher
ish—and to help her forget.
So tf you read this, Blanche,
wpn't you please, go home to
mamma?
And if you happen to know
Blanche—or any girl like
Blanche —will you not tell her
to go home, too?
that the records found with tne
dead bodies of the explorer and
his party show that Scoti reached:
the exact spot where Captain Is
l!o:ilNorwegian flag at the South pole
and that the British party tner«
made use of a hut erected by tn»
Norwegian explorer.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025121/1913-02-11/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Scott+explorer</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Explorer Dies After He
Reaches His Goal
in South.
Hung er and Exhaustion
Overtakes Devoted
Scientists.
LONDON, Tobruary 11. (By Associated
Press Oablo) Following tho report
from Oaraaru, Now Zealand, of tho
death of Capt. Eobert F. Scott, commander
of tho South Polo expedition,
tho Eoyal Geographical Society, or
which Captain Scott was a distinguished
member and under tho auspices of
which ho was engaged on his voyago,
issued an official announcement of his
doath and that of several of his party.
Beside Captain Scott, tho names of
who perished In tho South Polar
snows Include Dr. E. A. Wilson, tho
physician of tho expedition; Lieutenant
H. B. Bowers, Eoyal Navy; Capt.
L. E. Gates and Petty Officer Evans.
It is stated that Captain Scott, Bowera,
Wilson and Gates died as tho result of
hunger and exposure, while Evans was
tilled by a fall.
Other members of the party aro reported
to bo in cxcollcnt health and
to have recovered from the terrible experiences
through which thoy passed.
The rescuing party discovered the
bodies of the dead on November 12,
last. Thoy also recovered all of the
records and paraphernalia of thoso who
perished.
Captain Scott's Bhlp, tho Terra Nova,
ta expected to arrive in her New Zealand
port tomorrow, when complete do-tails
will bo sent to tho geographical
-society of the last workjnd the death
of Captain Scott and his party.
News of tho Disaster.
OAMARU, Now Zealand, February
10c (By Associated Press Cable to
Star-Bulletin) Capt. Kobcrt Scott,
i i-" Wi n ,mr m m i urn i m h win wi. 'v i:
MKBBQEfflsm&mBBBnnBK ilfrlPiEgfiFav6 Ba..M';;i..i Hghrt.jJ
t limil i tBMpMrliW 1 F3iLBUL !wr Captaiktcott (at HEAD OF tablejW
mUmmSBBSSSi' JmKA lm. jzmfflmmP
WWI'ffTTWtJHW mi MLjtfGfimP, ,VI jffiJBTVL' luiuM artfifiirilV I Ml.' YWk flRfllK?HW
vt mi I'WBk Wf IByi fr wyl ip2r
CftPL SCOTT WRS sBBBBBMSSi
ANTARCTIC PIOHEEB ORDERS GQUISER
niiMtTilffT ffl I TFT in I iilPUP'1"1 B...Bw
British Royal Wavy, ami on ining tho C0Iltincnt oi tho nntarctic.
the scientists nnd picked men who Cnj)tam Scott in iSO0 i,nea at tho pole,
-dared with him the dangers of the South Unt j tho Smckct0n jash
Volar regions in a brave dash toward ie ,ia(, thc recor(i lor roaching the
pole, are lOBt, overwhelmed in a tliest point south. His discoeries wcro
terrible blizzard. of tho greatest importance, both to
This is the report that bhacU.oton nnd Amuuilsen, and. without
amo to Oanmru today when Terra detracting fro'm tho s'orJ' ot their
Nova, Captain Scott's ship, coming nehieiements it is only fair to award
from tho remote port of Cardiff on her to Captain Scott tho lunor of Lo ng the
Teturn to civilization, signaled to this pioneer.
port that Captain Scott and the men Captain Scott was horn in 1808. Ho
had perished in a blizzard on tho South was lour jears older than Amundsen,
Polar Continent. although ho appeared younger from
Twenty-eight officers and scientists thoir portraits. Ho was twelve years
and picked men from tho younger than Admiral Peary. His
British navy, according to tho signals birthplace was Dovonport. Ho entorod
from tho Terra Nova, wero lost with the mny in 1882 and sened first on
Scott. tho Hover, became a lieutenant and
The same signals brought tho trunsieired to the Amphion in 1889. In
mation that Captain Scott had reached g98 aa j890 ho serlC(i on tuo
South Pole a few days after Cap- tlC) tll0 jiagaip 0t the Channel
Amundsen, of the Norwegian ox- r0Ui n 1900 roso to lho rank of
pedition, hnd reached the goal toward commall,ier nnd tho garao vear BaiIoil
which both wero racing, bcott found t0 Dll)Covery on hig firBt antarctic
Amundsen's hut and "cords. By ms
oxrieuition iIo was mado a captain in
own statements ho confirmed the report 190, 0JJ uig roturn
of Amundsen's prior discovery. j ri,C0Rnlt on of ,lis acbievcmcnt he
Tho last message of toft rf t0 Vlctorian Order and Locame
plow was delivered on March 31 1DU, fcIlow of tho Koyal fTeographical So-to
tho captain of tho Terra Noa. It an'
Up wag honorary doctor of
j am remaining another winter to ciBl:o tf, Cambridge and Manchester
nn'1 n RoIJ n""10'"1' of half a dozen
complete mv worn. I
geographical societies. Captain Scott</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1913-02-11/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Scott+explorer</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>CAPTAIN SCOTT PERISHES
ANTARCTIC EXPEDITION WIPED OUT
Captain Robert Scott caught by the camera on the eve of his departure from Lyttelton, England, for the antarctic
in November, 1910. In the background is the Terra Nova.
Blizzard at South Pole Overwhelms Brave Officer in
Charge and Many Members of His Party
LONDON, Feb. 10.—News reached the world today that Captain Robert F. Scott, the Antarctic explorer, and
an unknown number of his companions perished in the Antarctic while on their return journey from the south pole.
They reached their goal on January 18, 1912, about a month after Captain Roald Amundsen, the Norwegian, had
planted the flag of his country there. They then turned back toward the bases they formed on their outward jour
ney, but were overtaken, overwhelmed and destroyed by a blizzard.
The news of the death of the explorers was brought to civilization today by the captain of the Terra Nova,
the vessel which had taken Scott's expedition to the south and which had gone again to bring them back after
the accomplishment of their task. A searching expedition recovered the bodies and records of the party."An independent Newspaper"
overtaken Captain Robert F. Scott's
Antarctic expedition, resulting in the
death of Captain Scott, Dr. E. A.
Wilson, Lieutenant H. R. Bowers,
Captain L. F. G. Gates and Petty
Officer E. Evans.
TENT .AND RECORDS FOUND
Captain Scott's party, said Douglas
W. Fresh-field, vice president of the
Geographical society, found Captain
Roald Amundsen's tent and records at
the south pole. On the return trip,
about March 29. 1912, 11 miles from
One Ton depot, a blizzard overwhelmed
them. They had suffered greatly from
hunger and exposure, and the death of
Scott, Bowers and Wilson virtually was
due to that. They died soon after the
blizzard swept down on the party.
Gates died from exposure a few days
later. The death of Evans resulted
from a fall.</text>
      </result>
    <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1918-03-06/ed-1/seq-23/#date1=1756&index=0&rows=20&words=Conquered+conquered+Pole+pole+south+South+Who+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+conquered+south+pole%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Amundsen, the man who conquered the
| south pole, has gone to America at the i
; invitation of the Washington govern- J
j merit to address American audiences.
I and especially those made up of per- j
"'sons of Norwegian descent, on his im- i
i pressions of the war. Before leaving i
| for the United States ("apt. Amundsen
! 11 nI.shied a tour of the entire western
j front.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88076525/1918-03-06/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=1&rows=20&words=conquered+Pole+South+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+conquered+south+pole%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Amundsen the man who conquered the
South Pole, has gone to America at
the invitation of the Washington gov
ernment to address American audinec
es and especially those made up of
persons of Norwegian descent on his
impressions of the war. Before leav
ing for the United Skates, Capt. Am
undsen finished a tour of the western
front.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1959-02-22/ed-1/seq-147/#date1=1756&index=2&rows=20&words=conquered+Pole+South+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+conquered+south+pole%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
    </results>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1930-03-10/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=4&rows=20&words=conquered+Pole+Poles+South+who&searchType=basic&sequence=0&state=&date2=1963&proxtext=who+conquered+south+pole%3F&y=0&x=0&dateFilterType=yearRange&page=1</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>

</topics>
