<topics>

  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-radium/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-04-19/ed-1/?sp=36&q=Joint+Discoverers+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Radium+Metal</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
        A WONDERFUL WOMAN AND HER HUSBAND WHO ARE JOINT DISCOVERERS OF A WONDERFUL METAL -RADIIM
PROFESSOB AND MME. CURIE AND DAUGHTER SEATED IX THEIR GARDEN
(Photograph by Hurry C Ellis, Paris.)
ably bo beaten in the vicinity of the Pouth P< le,
which is believed to be surrounded by land. No
such severe cold has been found on Arctic seas,
iven in the highest latitude reached. By un
hianned balloons Bent up last winter in Europe
a temperature of 87 below zero was recorded.
With this preface one can partially under
stand a communication recently published in
"The Monthly Weather Review" and "The Na
tional Geographic Magazine." both <>f Washing
ton. R. C. Mossman, meteorologist of the Scot
tish Antarctic expedition, now exploring the re
gion southeastward of Cape Horn, mentions
his preparations for sending up instruments
wit>, kilos, but adds: "There is some possibility
of losing a record by the freezing of the ink, as
we have not tin newly Invented ink containing
tonsol."
As to what "tonsol" is the dictionaries do not
tell. Mr. Mossman is at present inaccessible.
Leading chemists in the metropolis have never
heard <>f it; and this is the waj in which Pro
fessor Willis 1.. Moore, chief of the United
States Weather Bureau in Washington, answers
a query concerning it
We regret th.it there has been .some delay
in making this reply, occasioned by our efforts
to ascertain, if possible, some particulars con
cerning the substance "tonsoL" The only in
formation in the possession of the Weather
Bureau concerning the particular ink mentioned
in Mr Mossman's letter is that con
tained in the letter itself. An Inquiry of chem
ical experts and a search for references to the
substance "tonsol" fail to develop any further
particulars. Dr. Wiley, chief chemist of the
Department of Agriculture, informs u.s that in
very old climates it is customary to add a cer
tain portion of glyc«rol or calcium chloride to
rtiks to secure fluidity, and it i.s possible the term
•"tonsol" may be a trade name for some of these
todies.
RADIUM DISCOVERERS.
Professor and Mme. Curie Are In
deed Helpmeets.
Paris, April 10.
The most striking and interesting personages
It ill' present moment in Paris are Professor
Pierre Curie and his wife, his Invaluable co
«their lives to an astonishingly brilliant series of
experiments in the extraction and isolation 01
radium, the most mysterious and most costly
metal kntwn to the scientific world. M. and
Mme. Curie have provided science with a new
and most powerful weapon. The mineral, which
ha* become the great talk of the day, was dis
covered in 1898 by If. and Mme. Curie, who,
after long and complicated chemical researches,
succeeded in extracting from a ton of the pitch
blende mineral of Joachinistal, in Bohemia, two
decigrams of radium. The operation cost over
which is at the rate of $10.1100 a gram,
or $10,000,000 a kilogram.
To borrow ihe definition <>f Sir William
Crook* s radium possesses the "extraordinary
proportj continuously emitting heat without
combustion, without r-hemical change of any
kitpl anit without anj rhang* 3 in its molecular
structure, which remains spectroscoplcally
Hl'ii:. 1 aftPi- many months of continuous
i,i--i. n Radium salt emits, without
r- pi ii'i< diminutioi of its own •i i l''i'\
NEW YORK TRIBUNE ILLUSTRATED^SUPPLEMENT.
sufficient heat to melt more than its own weight j
of ice every hour. Radium en. its r,i\s of its own
which have the qualities of X rays and of
cat hod ie rays, and is as active in vacuum as in
air. Uranium and thorium throw off analogous
rays, but of an intensity a millionfold less than
the radium rays. The rays "i emanations from
radium penetrate through certain opaque bodies
and make impressions on sensitive films m
closed wooden boxes. For instance, if a coin or
a key or other object be placed in a leather
purse and the purse put ii 'he dark on a sensi
tive plate, and a little radium be placed near at
hand, it will be found that the development of
the plate will produi c photographs of the coin or
key, just as is the case with the Rontgen rays.
The radiations of radium rea< I chemically upon
certain bodies; for instance, they transform
oxygen into ozone, and they change the colors of
glass or porcelain t.. dark violet or brown.
Another extraordinary property of radium is i
to throw off rays not only of heat, but of light
like those of the plow worm or firefly. Indeed, j
th*» li^ht rays of radium are so powerful that it
has been suggested liy French scientists that in
this mysterious metal may some day lie found a
means of lighting cities without loss of energy
or waste of force. The rays radium dash and
explode like minute artillery projectiles upon
sensitive surfaces, and '.heir phosphorescent
properties are astounding. The most puzzling
property of radium is that, as far as has yet
been ascertained, it.- properties of emit) heat
and light are inexhaustible. The great Mys
tery is how and where the ambient forces
needed to produce heat and light are absorbed
by radium. According to the laws of the con
servat'on and correlation of forces, heat, light
end motion are convertible, and neither Profes
«or nor Mine. Curie, nor Sit William Crookes,
nor any of the scientists of France. England or
Germany who have followed in Professor Curie's
footsteps, have yet been able to prove that the
incessant continuity in the emission of rays of
light and heat from radium causes any exhaus
tion, expenditure or diminution of the prop
PROFESSOR AND MMI CURIE AND DAUGHTER.
AViilking in their garden in front of their little cottage at inilly. Fr?n.«»
(Photograph by Harry C. Ellis, Parls.J
erties bo mysteriously stored In apparently fcj,
finite quantities in tail extraordinary metal.
Radium, rr»>r'- has startling effects cpai
the nervous centres of hum;;n being?) and ..-,!nf
animal.". A glass tube containing one or fsij
milligrams of radium \*h'-r. carried f n tha
waistcoat pocket causes a painful wound in tile
flesh that will require six month- Jo heal. A
glass tut"'- containing a few mfllisrrairs
radium when introduced beneath the skin «s? a
mouse near the vertebral column produced «!»at&
by paralysis in three hour*. Tut^s of r^uia
placed in contact with the back of the nerks ef
guinea pigs kill or paralyze the animals ta a
few hours, according to th« length »,f *jpoto its fatal radiations. M Curie say? that d^ari
to man would probably ensue upon '•nfrin? a
room containing a pound of radium, liaf'mm is,
indeed, an unknown quantity. F^nh we***
brings to light startling addition to its mjs
terious properties, which, as far as i* ;-»-t known,
emanate and originate in itself, and nu-e sci
entists to ask the rjuestiosi. "Can it (XMtsltli
that Professor and Mn»*\ Curie have i<. r.i.ttas!
discovered perpetual motion?
Professor Pierre Curie, whom it ha.s be«-n my
good fortune to meet on several a?:or.s, bod
at his little cottage, near tlentniy, and In xtt
laboratories of the >orbonr.<>, v. her- h* work*. ;j
a man of impressive individuality. Th<-re is
Irresistible, fascination in he soft bat pene
trating gTance Oi bis large hazel whicll
seem to emit rays of intelligence akin to those
of the mysterious metal which he and his tal
ented wife have di?:overed. M. Curi-i is forty
years old, tall and well formed. He with the artistic negligence that is often char
acteristic of men of genius. His beard and hair
are luxuriant, and his placid e.xpr-.5.-;kn of
beatitude, together with the pure antique lines
of his head and face, suggest the portraits oJ
Christ as depicted in the paintings of Albert
Diirer. Professor Curi^ disdains worldrj mat
ters and lives high up in th-i clouds, rapt is
the of his mystic radium.
He and hLs wife are by no mear.s in ,;f!2j*r.t
circumstances. Th-y live in a small ottage
with a green lawn and fruit tr^es in the most
inaccessible southern district of Paris, over
looking the fortifications, far away from the
I^itin Quarter, and also a long distance froa
the. intellectual and fashionable centra of tie
capital. Professor Curie is an early riser. At i
oclock in the morning, ufrer having given hi 3
little daughter a lesson ta arithmetic, h^ jurr.fa
on his hieyele and pedals briskly thre* miles to
the l;\borator> of the Sorbonr.^. in the Ku*
Cuvier, near the Jardin dcs Plant-<, to t!:«
laboratory of the Kcole de Physi-iue. i:i th« Rue
T-honiand, behind the Pantheon. It was the
Fatter laboratory that Profet^.jr Curie ft- M le
fore me a small glass test tub- containing a
gra>lsb white powder resemi'lhig table said. You see. this is radium: The pri.fVssflr,
:o illustrate the fact that carrying radiurr. about
produces flesh burns or wounds, good nat ;r<«li7
bared his left arm arid showed me a d^*p *unJ
that had been four months healing-.
The professor i- extremely fond of hi* little
cottage, with lawn and fruit trf-e= and ki?> h»S
garden. It was in his little garden that re
ceived me last Sunday, and presented me to his
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1903-07-19/ed-1/?sp=37&q=Radium+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Metal+Universal+Light+Bringer+Blind</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>UT
J?
V
y
Doctor London placed a box of radium behind a screen and the blind child Bprang excitedly toward it.
He could see the light.
Bptdal Correeponlesee ef The Euno&y Republic
St. Petersburg. June SO. I made a blind
boy see by means of radium, and the fact
Justifies a detailed discussion of the new
element's properties and the hope It holds
out to suffering mankind.
The radium preparation placed at my dis
posal for experimental purposes looked, at
first Eight, Ilka a bit of ground tobacco,
resembling tho same In substance, and
color.
After I had satisfied myself to that effect,
my assistant, a chemist, asked permission
to plato a black bandago o er my eyes.
I -wore the same live or seven minutes,
when he came tow ard me with, a small box
containing tho ery radium I had creiously
examined.
Holding the box before my cohered eyes
at a distance of from four to six and one
half Inches, tho following sensations mani
fested themselves:
My blind-folded right eye had a distinct
perception ot light, growing stronger as
tny assistant advanced upon me, at cen
timeter stages. (Three centimeters equal to
ens Inch.)
It seemed as It my right eye had entered
Into a light Ephere. yet there were no sharp
pontours or outlines.
J'ei.t tho boxed radium was advanced
toward jnS left eye, which up to then had
but scantily profiled by Uie Ught-brlnger
''and Immediately following the light eensa-
j Hon in my right ee became dim. while that
in my left materially Increased.
I asked tho assistant to place the radium,
paste-board cover and olL into a. small
metal match box, whereupon the experi
ments were renewed, the result being al
most similar. The light sphere observed
was but a shade less bright.
Then I placed my hand oor the blind
folded e e and saw as much as before.
Two friends put their hands over mine.
Result the game.
Here, then, was a light-bearer for the
more or less sightless, tho degree being
hardly of any consequence.
Still blindfolded, I asked my assistant to
point the radium toward my forehead.
Then, too. I perceived the light sensation
described: that is. I saw tho radium rays,
not the boxes holding them prisoner.
Some time later a friend called, who has
a peculiar, nervous head.
Wo held the box several Inches away
from the back of his head, his eyss being
blindfolded. According to his description he
experienced the same light sensations that
had astonished me.
At tho time of writing the above experi
ments have been tried on a dozen or more
reliable men and women, with the results
j' noted.
STARTLING DISCOVERIES
HADE IX DARK ROOM.
We next experimented In a dark room,
dispensing, ot course, with the blindfolding
business.
As expected, the same results were had.
Still later a person possessed of one sound
tni one unsound eye was experimented
with. It developed that the light Impres
sions conveyed by radium on the sound eye
'i'iiI'
ill
were stronger than those on the other.
The left eye of another young person In
vestigated Is minus a retina. The radium
rays made no impression whatever on that
eye.
Every optician will tell the reader that a
perfect crystaUIne lens Is necessary to In
sure good sight. Our experiments fIiow that
a good, healthy crystalline lens diminishes
the Impressions of radium rays on the eye.
It seems to repel them.
The question arose: Can a blindfolded
person, or a person In a dark room, per
ceh o articles on which radium ra a are re
flected? Experiments proved that such Is Impossi
ble, for radium rays penetrate the article,
and. In part, ore swallowed up by It.
With respect to the experiment of holding
radium above the line of the eye. It was ob
served that the lower half of the retina
caught the rays; myself and others had
been under the impression that the light
came from above.
We did not know the assistant's position
till later.
We continued experiments In the way that
tho assistant described, with his radium
box, various flgureB, representing numbers,
letters, diagrams and words before tho
blindfolded persons. All these figures were
Instantly recognized. This latter fact still
more strengthened my belief that radium
may he placed in the service of the blind
with most beneficial results.
With this end In view I thought at first
of playing tho radium raj son tho retina di
rect, but that was an error of theory as
well as practice, for, in the first place, not
one retina of sightless persons resembles the
other, and. again, radium rays play havoc
with living tissues. 8o we were forced to
resort to mechanical apparatus.
LIGHT COULD RE INTENSIFIED
OR DIMINISHED.
To this end we tmployed barlum-platln
cjanlde, and holding sime at a certain dis
tance from the box with radium saw It light
up with subdued yellowish-green fluores
cence, the peculiar appearance presented by
certain substances on being viewed by re
flected light.
The light, moreover, could be Intensified or
diminished by moving tho radium box near
er or farther away.
To the apparatus, figures, writing, dia
grams, eta, may be attached, and after It Is
lit up by radium, tho blind can perceive the
meaning cr characters, the only condition
being that the attachments are of nontrans
parent material, black paper, lead, etc.
Our experiments further show that under
such conditions the sightless eye Is easily
educated.
Remember, though, there must be no side
lights, none other but the fluorescence.
The principle, let me add. Is not new. It
Is the same that enables us to' see the stars
at night, and to see them the better the
darker It Is.
Next w txpertmented with a box of ra
dium placed behind the screen, with the re
sult that on the opposite side an intense
light spot appeared.
The several blind people, under my. obser
THE REPUBLIC: SUNDAY. JULY 19. 1003.
r
foffsd
vation wero able to perceive that spot and
to follow its movements. The radium box
described a circle behind the screen and
the blind man Imitated the same with a pen
cil on a sheet of paper.
Letters and whole words were convoyed
to those previously educated In schools for
the blind in the same way.
I therefore maintain that It will be pos
slblo to teach the blind to read and write
by way of radium, also to draw figures,
etc.
Among others I Introduced an 11-year-old
boy to the new method.
In tho first )ear of his life this boy had
become blind, owing to an affectation of
both nerves of vision.
Tet his eies were still capable of receiv
ing a certain amount of light Impressions!
he can distinguish between light and dark
ness BLIND BOX LEARNED TO READ.
After a week of experimenting the blind
boj learned to make out letters that were
radlumgraphed on the screen.
The letters wero about three Inches high
and some three Inches apart.
To-day my little pupil can read words
composed of letters.
That much demonstrated, tho physiologic
al aspects ot radium Ehould be examined.
According to my own observations. Its
Impress on organisms has three different
periods
The first Is more or less latent, at least
I could perceive of no visible changes.
During the necond period the organisms
teem to be In a sort ot Inflamed state, not
always patent to the eye, yet requiring
close examination.
Tho third period Is that ot destruction
more or less farreachlng, according to the
Intensity of the radium-rays employed.
This Indicates that radium-rajs, when we
completely understand them, will lend
themselves to Various medical purposes In
asmuch as a gradual scale of exposure may
be established, the result depending upon
time and tho quantity and quality of the
radium used.
Furthermore, I ascertained that the In
fluence of radium rays on organisms de
pends. In a large measure, on the natuse of
things coming In contact with the metal.
I have not Vet found a thing, organism
or object that Is not. In some way. Influ
enced by an exposure to radium ras. Our
experiments embraced Seed, bacteria, cells
of animal eggs, frogs-spawn, guinea pigs,
rabbits and human beings.
The latter, ns weU as the rest, showed
considerable Irritation under tho rays. We
have reason to believe that certain plant
and animal seed does not develop under
radium rays; leaves lse their healthy, green
color, etc
I subjected the skin ot a, guinea nig, of
a rabbit and a young man to radium rays
and durlhg the first three days observed
no change; on tho fourth dav the skin
looked inflamed, a swelling appeared and
finally an open wound of the kind known
In. medicine as ulcus necrodlum.
rn
Ji.1 .III., In J
This latter hu so far defied all attempts 1
at healing.
WHITE Mien DIED
FOIl LACK OF BREATH.
A most Interesting observation was mads
on a dozen whlto mice, placed In a glass
Jar -Kith liberal provisions. On the top of
the Jar I put a small'box ot radium, en
cased In pasteboard and metal.
The mice enjoyed themselves for twlos
twenty-four hours.
After that they exhibited signs ot 41
tress. lying .listlessly on their back On
tbo fifth day all were dead,.
Investigation proved that every one of
tho-rodents died of paralysis of the breath
ing ctntorB. "?;X
Itadlum'e Influence) on the skin suggests
that It may be a powerful aid of medicine
m curing Biun oiseasea.
Several of my medical friends, are exper
menting on, the lines Indicated, and on
Lupus tho results eo far have been very
encouraging.'
Another Interesting fact: I subjected the
unfmctilled egg cell of a lower animal to
radium rays, .and It began to develop.
In the case of rabbits I observed that
their coat Improved on the Bide subjected
to radium rayft. In short, I am all together
hopeful that radium may do for us many
things heretofore considered Impossible.
Too bad that It Is bo scarce and expensive
as to be without reach for the poor blind
especially.
Perhaps the State will help them, now
that their futuro begins to look bright.
I certainly think that the blind man's
chances for getting back his sight, or ac
quire It, hae unmeasurcably Improved
since the discovery ot radium.
In this respect let no one be discouraged
by reports of experiments that failed.
Those described by the writer were aa
tlrely successful, and the minutes of the
case axe at the disposal of all Interested.
Eye specialists of all nations should at
once begin experimenting with radium.
C. S. LONDIN. M. D.
L AND MRS. HENRY
M1
lYft NORTHEAST
mkvBBBBBmBSB
IISBkw1kwMbbsbsbwwmwmmmbbbWsSkwwwwwwwwwwwwm
mm WPKMrT'1- r:J &BBB L X4CiH-
Hr k fcJiii. trBbIBm i--!-! z itfi m 9BVaS-4ifKHiiBvM
jVjVM XA t Mi .ssBlL 3m JMMBMMPBtalE ,.'MWry i J AHwVHRBHIBnBBHHHHHHHHHHHH
Hl' i -iBiiffMHsiSMiB-? all iF flFi tIi1rw"m"m"m"BiW
-VaW Haa3HtKBiiwaaaaaaaaaaaaal
BnBHLHBiVaVaiVar JPJBBWT'' r IsVAijViSaiVAVAVAVAVl
iVaBBiVAiVftiVaVi t''-W?KB-itiimiBSaBPBKM
MR. A2TD MRS. BIER AND THEIR FAMILY.
No. 1, Lizzie; 2, Tliomas; 3, George; 4, Alice; 5, William; 6, Henry; 7, Mr. Bier; 8, Mrs. Bier; 9, Joseph;
10, Nellie, 11, John; 12, Frank, 13, Edward; 14, Marguerite.
Boeclal Correspondence of The Sunday Republic.
1 Palmyra, Mo., July IS. There Is proba
bly no man better Known or more 'respect
ed In Marion County than ifenry Bier,
who has the distinction of being the fa
ther ot the largest family of llvltg chil
llli. ..,r
mezn
WW KM
BIER ARE PARENTS OF
MISSOURI.
dren in this part of Northeastern Mis
souri. 1U and his wlfo have twelve chil
dren at their table, all In the best of
health, happy and assured of a com
petence for years to come.
When President Roosevelt made his, re- 2
l"l B
!AS MADE
PWi
m
I
LARGEST FAMILY IN
markabla address on race suicide Marion
County people Immediately thought of tha
fine example which Mr. and Mrs. Bier had
given to their neighbors.
This couple have succeeded In becoming
the owners of several hundred acres ot
-sz
H
LIND
SEC.
F
r
lift
fine Marlon County farm land, and arse
now resting content, while their children
are taking their full part In the activities;,
of the community. won
Mr. Bier was bom In Shelby County, it
Missouri, June 17, IMS, being 67 rears old'
at present. His parents were natives of-
Oermany, who brought hint to Palmyra hv
H87.
He was raised on a farm, educated fn
the common schools, and previous to buy
In a grocery In this town in 1S74 worked!!
at shoemaklng. plastering and bricklay--Ing.
After conducting tho grocery for a'
number of years he turned the business'
over to his son Frank, and his daughter -Lizzie.

He was married to Miss Mary Flnnefaa
of Qulncy. I1L. on September 20, 1873.
With most of ttelr children they noW
Jlve on one of the best farms hereabouts.
Fourteen children were born to thtm,r:
twelve of whom are now Uvlng.
Tho picture of this family contains tha
parents and the Uvlng children, as fol t
lows:
Henry Bier, aged 67: Mrs. Mary Bier,
aged 49; John." 23; William, 5; Lizzie, Si f
Thomas. 22; Frank. 20; Margarlte, 13; Hen
ry. 17: Nellie, IS: George, 12; Edward, 10;
AUce. 7; Joseph. 2.
TOLD IN FIGURES.
TTncle Sam's annual Income Is Jjo8.SS7.US.
Russia has fifty-seven warships at Port
Arthur.
Florida's orange and pineapple crops Is es
timated at K. 50O.O0O.
The birth rate among the foreign born In
Massachusetts Is 52 per 1.000. Among the
native-born It Is 17.
Nearly one-half of tha mortality In the
United States Is from diseases of the
lungs, and 73 per cent of It preventable.
The postal receipts for the fiscal year end
ing with June wero J1,60S,SCT. an Increase
over tho previous year of 3125,632.
Thero are 227 lead pencil factories In Ger
many, which employ 2313 persons and ex
port each year 1,611 tons of pencils, worth
$2,000,000.
Mr. Cernegie's gifts to countries other
than the United States are recorded to the
amount of JS.S61.230. making Mr. Carnerl'Vx
total gift to libraries $44,365,950. j
At present there are about sever Iasn
firms engaged In gem-cutting In the t mak
States, with not far from $3,000,000
Invested. There are probably ah'1
skilled lapidaries at work, earning ai
age, r $1,00) apleco a, year.
8jfet,-;a .-xgy 5gafy.
Tf 't.t-
fr-?-.,. tl
V. -J3
.54 Ai,
-y .H
i'
y.y A
jej j. JiSy-.iAj,</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-12-27/ed-1/?sp=29&q=Radium+Effects+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Metal+Experiment</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
RADIUM'S EFFECTS ON ANIMAL LIFE.
The Metal Arrests Growth of Microbes, as Shoivn by Experiments Now
Going On in Paris.
Paris. December 17.
Radium, that precious ni^tul discovered by
the joint research's of Professor Pierre Curie,
of the scientific faculty Of the Sorbonne, and
his wife, and of which only five grams have
ever been obtained, becomes more mysterious
arid phenomenal with each successive scientific
Investigation. It was Mme. Curie who, by her
own experiments, first succeeded In isolating
radium and olkcting it in the form of a pure
salt From ten tons of pitchblende. LroUKht
from Joacbinstal. in Bohemia, two de.i
grams of radium were extracted after a long
and delicate chemical process. The cost of ob
taining radium was estimated last year at
LSO.OOO franca, or MJOO. a gram. This would
be at the rate of 150,0U0.<-HA> francs, or $30,
000.000, a kilogram.
I called upon Mme. Curie at her quaint little
house, near Montsouris Park, the other day.
Her husband had gone to London to attend a
scientific meeting. I asked Mme. Curie if she
had any additional revelations to make regard
ing the extraordinary metal which perplexes
FOUNDATIONS OF THE LOUVRE.
"SKtrsr jrar-a asawatf rs bs-bs
burled out of sight for two hundred years.
and balMes the scientific world and which defies
all the hitherto accepted laws of physics. Mme.
Curie replied that in addition to the exhaustive
paper that her husband read before the Royal
Institution of Great Britain on June 19 last
there had been no further important develop
ments to disclos?. Mme. Curie is a woman of
a purely and thoroughly scientific temperament.
She positively declined to be drawn out into
any expression of opinion or conjecture in re
gard to any of the practical results or benefits
to humanity that may eventually be obtained
from radium. She refused, for instance, to say
whether she thought that radium might some
day stive as a cure or prevention of cancer.
In response to such questions Mme. Curie
simply said: "Why, I do not know. How can I
tell? I am not aware that anything in that di
rection has been actually demonstrated!" Sir
William Ramsay's announcement that radium
gives off a heavy gas, which slowly changes
into helium and then vanishes, was mentioned,
but Mine, Curie, with cast iron devotion to
truth, would not venture upon any assertion
not supported by absolute scientific demonstra
tion. In reply to my question "whether efforts
were being made to procure radium in larger
quantities than heretofore," Mme. Curie replied
"that the Austrian government was taking pos
session of the pitchblende deposits In Bohemia,
which were by no means inexhaustible, and tha
result of this would be that the future cost of
obtaining radium would be very much greater,
than hitherto— perhaps twice as much." This
would put the price of radium at $GO.OOO,OO<> a
kilogram. The fact is of great importance in
connection with the statement made to me last
spring by Professor Curie, who said that the
probability of extracting radium under favorable
conditions from the pitchblende deposits in Col
orado was most promising.
1 asked Mme. Curie what experiments just
now going on In Paris were of the greatest in
terest. The emphatic reply was: 'By all means
those conducted at the Pasteur Institute by BL
J. Danysz, who is investigating the pathogenic
action of rays and emanations emitted by
radium upon various animal tissues and sub
stances."
At the Pasteur Institute, in the Rue Duthot, I
found M. Danysz hard at work in his labora
tory. M. Danysz is a Polish scientist, and han
for the last few years assisted Professor Curie
in many of his experiments with radium. Pro
fessor Curie supplied M. Danysz with titty
milligrams of radium in the bromure form, and
it is with this quantity of the metal that the
investigations at the Pasteur Institute are being
proceeded with. M. Danysz is a wiry little nan
of highly strung, nervous temperament. II.
dark, dreamy eyes have that searching brill
iancy peculiar to abstruse scientists, lie la aa
Indefatigable worker, and derives frequent in
spirations during his laboratory experiments
from fragrant cigarettes containing the purest
Russian tobacco. On the table he had a large
glass jar half filled with soft, powdered sea
weed, containing a dozen mice of different
sizes, varying from two months to two yean i.i
age. The animals and insects subjected to the
radium rays and emanations by M. Dai
comprise rabbits, guinea pigs, caterpillars and
butterflies. Tests have also been made m Its
microbes of charbon.
M. Danysz stated that "the nervous centre 3
of the animals or insects were extremely ten
sitive to the effect of the radium rays or
tions. The intestinal organs were, on the con
trary, only slightly sensitive to the affects of
radium." It will be recollected that the effect
of radium upon the skin was first not!< bj
Professor Curie during his earliest experiments
with the metal. M. Curie, one morning alter
delivering a lecture, put a glass tube contain
ing fifty milligram:; of radian in his waist' oat
pocket. No particular leiwattSß was felt at
the time, but a fortnight afterward his s kiii
at the point corresponding with the wal
pocket became highly Inflamed and painful, i
wound broadened and deepened, and could not
be cured in less than live months. It was this
incident that suggested the epidermic ezp >ri
ments with animals and Insects. It was then
discovered that the action of radium on i..«i
nervous centres produced paralysis or death, ac
cording to the particular organism and depend
ing upon the length of exposure to the i
emanations. A remarkable character!
til- action of radium upon animal! an I Insects
is the period of incubation— twenty day:; In case
of human beings— which baa not yet been satis
factorily explained by scientific resean b, and
which furnishes still another mystery to thosa
f..r which radium li already responsible. Fifty
inlUlnrains of radium in a glusa tut"- placed
for twenty-lour hours In contact with t:i- Skin
of a guinea pig causes the complete destruction
of the epidermis and of the deimis. Th>- skin
was^lercsd with boles, and the tissue protruded
iv hernia fo.in. M. Danysu elated that Uu»
5</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89066489/1904-05-12/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Radium+Liquid+Sunshine</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99065839/1921-08-19/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Radium+Mine+Hospital+Marie+Curie</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>PADIIJIMI ra
ILJI s?- wijL -JjLil
.oh Piaspaisiili j
IO -wxx s v.3, v .wXw urn ir 1 1 i 1
oir rtl, P.'
V
1 W3akid V-P'fSJ
--agll -a- -II
By JOHN DICKINSON SHERMAN, i
ONCERNING Mme. Marie
Curie and her discovery
of radium, her recent
visit to the United States
and the presentation to
her by American ,omen
of a gram of radium In
recognition of her serv
ices to science and hu
manity the reading pub-lie-
is sufficiently in
formed. Everybody knows that she
was made much of by our dignitaries
that tea degrees were conferred upon
her by our universities 'that. Presi
dent Harding himself made the pres
entation to her in the White House
with appropriate words In the pres
ence of a brilliant gathering of nota
bles, and that a tired and happy wom
an finally sailed away with her precious
gram of radium stored in a mahogany
case lined with steel and lead. She
said she was going to take a real rest
ttnA that aha hnnri In Senteniber tQ
I1UU Mil mmv f w S
go back to her work In the 3arie in
stitute In Paris now that she again
has radium to work with. The insti
tute Uiviaes US wurit wvujjvinw
Nnoa Ana haa ti (In wiL the study
of radium and radioactive substances
purely f rOm the viewpoint of the phys
icist; the. other deals with their appli
cation to the treatment of human ail
ments. She will also carry on an ex
tensive Investigation of mesathorium,
another radioactive substance enough
of this was presented to her to bring
the value of the combined gift to $165,
000. But where this American radium
came from and how it was produced
la another story, which may profitably
be told In this connection. It is espe
cially Interesting, Inasmuch as the to
tal world's supply of radium Is esti
mated at only 140 grams (a gram Is
one twenty-eighth of an ounce). The
Illustration by comparison sshows how
small is this amount. The lower sec
tion represents that made by the prin
cipal American radium refinery,, the
dark section that made by ther Amer
ican refineries and the upper layer
that produced abroad. So, though
radium was not produced in the Uni
ted States till 1913, this country now
has made about five times as much as
the rest of the world.
Whue Mme. uurie, Dy aiscuvenus
radium, introduced a new conception
Into the fundamental problems, of ex,
istence, she actually produced very lit
tle radium, since she was denied the
ores with which to work. Moreover,
she gave It all away to the medical
profession of Europe. A very small
portion found its way to New York.
In 1911 the late Joseph M. Flannery
of Pittsburgh, who had made a success
"with vanadium as an alloy for steel,
devoted his attention to the produc
tion of radium. The ores of other
countries being out of the question,
he turned to the carnotite deposits
of southwestern Colorado, Prior to
the World war this carnotite ore had
been shipped to French and German
producers of radium.
Thfr mining' and handling of carno
tite ore In southwestern Colorado Is
attended with difficulties. The region
Is desolate and practically uninhab
ited. Water Is scarce. Flannery had
his troubles. He had to train new
men. He finally established headquar
ters at the only spring of clear water
within 100 miles; here the Standard
Chemical company maintains all the
offices for Its mining work, transporta
tion and supplies. Eighteen miles
away the company built the largest
radium concentration mill in the
world, through "which has- passed the
ore from which has. been refined more
than balf the world's supply of radi
um. Burros carry the ores from the
mines to the mill, and wafer and sup
plies to the miners. i
Mme.' Curie worked on European
ores which contained about one gram
of radium to every five or, six tons.
Ia the Colorado ores there is about
P
8
IBS
Mm
I is? I IEO. s Tni
'ft" i i I y&fea! -I
f m 'AS I 4 Vri
one gram to every 500 tons. More
over, the carnotite miner is a pocket
hunter. Sometimes the ore appears
on the 8-face and along rim rocks;
then extraction Is easy. More fre
quently the ore is found under a heavy
overload of other material; then reg
ular mining tunnels are run and dyna
mite is used to break the rock for
transportation to the surface.' The
pockets vary widely some contain
only a few pounds, while exceptional
pockets have contained 1,800 tons,
First, of course, the Tcoeket must be
found. Prospecting Is done by drill.,
ing in likely spots with Jack hammers
and with diamond drills. Where the
overlay Is not more than 25 feet deep
the Jack hammer, operated, by portable
gasoline compressors and compressed
air, is the cheapest method of wont
ing. Under other conditions the dia
mond drill Is used.
Hamilton Foley writes for the Pan
American Union an Interesting ac
count of the operations of the com
pany and of the production of the
radium presented to Mme. Curie; the
pictures used herewith are among the
illustrations. He says in one piace:
"Let us follow the various opera
tions from the extraction. of the ore
to the nnal recovery of the radium.
At the concentration mill in the wilds
of Colorado 500 tons of ore are re
duced to about 125 tons. In a pow
dered form this quantity is shipped
in 100-pound sacks, by wagon and,
where possible, by motor trucks, the
65 miles to Placervllle,' Colo. Here a
narrow-guage railroad takes It to the
transcontinental railroad at Salida,
Colo. From Salida it travels the 2,300
miles to Canonsburg, Pa., Just outside
of Pittsburgh, .where the company
maintains its concentration plant, No.
2.
"It should be noted that at the mill
In Colorado, and In the operations
pertaining to it, some 300 men. are
necessary to carry through all the de
tailed work. Also, that when the ore
Is taken up by the Colorado mill,
there is only 1 part radium for every
400,000,000 parts of the ore; but when
the ore reaches the mill, at Canons
burg the proportion ia 1 part of radi
um to 100,000,000 parts of the ore.
"The task, ofthe Canonsburg men
is to reduce this mass of ore to less
than a quarter of a ton, and" In such
a way that whatever radium may have
been In the greater mass will be found
in the small residue. This Is done with
regularity and precision, notwithstand
ing that In the elimination of the 100,
000,000 parts of undesirable material
the Canonsburg plant has to use 10,
000 tons of distilled water, 1,000 tons
of coal, and 500 tons of chemicals.
It should be noted in this connection
that whatever small quantity of va
nadium and uranium there may be
In this material Is saved while this
final reduction Is being made.
"The actual recovery of whatever
radium there may be In the tons of ma
terial handled at these two great con
centration plants is made elsewhere.
When the 125 tons of material that
reached Canonsburg from the mill in
the, West have been reduced to 'less
than a quarter of a ton, this residue
is sent to the radium research labor
atories of the company in the form
of radium barium chloride By suc-
cessiye fractional crystallizations, of
the radium chloride and, at a later
stage, of the bromide, most of the
radium Is obtained In a salt contain
ing over 95 per cent of pure radium
bromide. By still further chemical
treatment the bromide is converted
into the sulphate or the' chloride, and
in th therapeutic use of radium these
two salts'flnd the largost use."
Mme. Curie, several years ago by
general request fixed an int'ernatloiial
radium standard. This is deposited
in Paris and the leading cities of "the
-iporld have replicas of i It. So now
$Ihnn, preparations are measured by
t-omparlng the electrical energy 'car
ried by their gamma rays with that
of tire international standard.- While
radium has still many mysteries, it
may be said for the benefit of the
general public that its energy appears
to be given off In three rays, which
are known as the Alpha, Beta and
Gamma rays. It Is stated thaf the
Alpha and Beta rays are-electrical
and that the Gamma ray is rather a
vibration than a ray. The Alpha ray
is 'believed to comprise 85 per cent
of radium's activity; it travels with
about the speed of light 4nd has no
penetrative power. The Beta, ray is
about 10 Der cent of the activity,
travels with about 1-15 the speed of
light and can penetrate about an inch
and one-fifth of lead. The Gamma
ray can penetrate more than three
inches of lead; when It strikes a hard
substance it breaks up Into two rays
corresponding to the Alpha and Beta
rays..
It Is the Gamma ray that is used
in bloodless surgery. The Alpha ray
does not burn. The Beta ray Is kept
from the patient by a screen that alv
sorbs it. The Gamma ray seems to
have the peculiar quality of picking
out "useless or harmful-tissues for its
first attack; it will harm useful tis
sues only after -harmful tissues" have
been burnt away or dissolved. Radi
um is handled in lass tubes incased
in lead containers. Those who handle
It constantly usually get pretty badly
burned sooner or later.- Flesh burned
oy radium cannot be healed it simply
disappears and Is gone. One of Mme.
Curie's hands has been affected and
her general health has been under
mined by intensive wartime work with
radium.
VA gram of radium makes a' small
thimbleful. Its current price Is $120,
000. A gram is divided Into' a thous
and parts, each of which Is called a
milligram and sells for $120.. Physi
cians who use it have from 50 to 250
mlllgrams." The state of New York
has recently purchased 2 grams for
use in the treatment of cancer.
With radium worth $120,000 a thim
bleful, how is it that the' dials of even
cheap watches can be made luminous
by Its use? It's this way: The lum
inous material on the dial is a com
bination of a most minute portion of
real radium and a special zinc sul
phide. These atoms are so small that
it would take hundreds of millions
of them to cover an inch. As each
atom explodes, a projectile too small
to be seen under a microscope flies off
andl strikes a crystal of the zinc ox
ide. The heat' generated by the im
pact makes a flash visible to the eye.
As these explosions occur at the rate
of about 200,000 a second on the watch
dial, their combined flashes make th
dial luminous.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030273/1920-05-30/ed-1/?sp=76&q=Radium+Rarest+Element+Danger</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Radium Becoming
a Household Aid
Rarest Element Adaptable in Scores of Ways
to Eliminate Danger arid Inconvenience
of Groping in the Dark
By DORIS' E.
RADIUM, tho rnrest clement In the
world, la rapidly becoming an r
tlclo of ordlniry housohold use. It
Is the most valuable metal .in tho world
ono gram, which Is ono-twcnty-clghth of
an ounce, costing $120,000 yet It Is used on
more than four million watches nnd on In
numerable 25 cent Indicating tacks. It Is
so powerful that if any ono1 were to. .live In
the same room with one pound of It the
flesh would be torn from his bones. But
there Is not a nound of It in existence, and
If there were It would not exist In such
rorm. Ynt despite Its power nnd value,
children soon will play with its by-products
ns toys, while their elders use It In a hun
dred different ways.
There Is more than uno youngster already
who will not go to sleep nt night without
having his pet bear with radium eyea beside
him. And corners of rocking chnlrs will
shine out warningly nt night, poison bottles
vll' glow In the dark of the medicine cest,
night marksmen will sight their rifles by
the aid of it, mariners will riu'. more safely
because of It and the late returning house
holder will 1)0 able to find his keyhnlo moro
readily in Its light. Motorists, miners, fish
ermen, theatregoers, hospital orderlies, trav
elling salesmen and what Is generally
known as the great public will use this
rarest of substances as casually as they
wind their watches.
In MilU and Mines.
ilow much commercial progress Is to, owe
,o radium can be measured by Its rapidly
'ii'Teaslng use In fnctorles. mills and other
plants. Many mining corporations have
adopted radium danger signals and guiding
arrows. Radium indicators are not affected
by atmospheiii oniiillon.s in i ic ulni
whlch would make gas, oil and electric
lamps useless. As long as there is darkness
radium is visible. And In addition danger
of explosion Is minimized.
The tr.nrlner has already discovered many
invaluable uses for radium. Especially is
this true in tho case of the man nt the
wheel. Electric lights, oil and gas are dis
turbed by sudden motions and by the cut
ting off of current or breaking of contacts,
but when the compass card Is Illuminated by
radium Its visibility is reliable. In the en
gine nom, too, the telegraph control ist
serviceable on foggy nights and In times of
emergency.
But it is the ordinary householder, per
haps, who ivlll find tho greatest happiness
In conveniences made possible by more com
mon use of the mo. valuable substance In
the world. A minute particle of radium
used In a tubful of solution will make thou
sands of articles visible In the dark. Ra
dium may be used in cellars raisin cellars,
Enlist to Save Fruit Crops
balance to help turn It In favoi oi a success
ful harvest by becoming farmerettes. No
experlenco Is necessary. A fairly healthy
body and the will to work are the main In
gredients of rfne perfectly capable farmer
ette. Don't forget to throw In the overalls,
for they are the unofllclal working badge ot
both the male farm helper and the farmer
ette. These young women who want to aid the
short-handed farmer are part of the 6,000
men and women city seasonal workers who
Lave enlisted at tho recruiting headquarters
of the American .Land Service, In tho Lex
ington Theatre, 571 Lexington avenue, with
the Intention of devoting their slack sumlier
time to farm work.
Early vacationers are especially requested
'o emulate tho example of this growing force,
many of whom are already available for
farm emergency labor. The organization is
fast completing Its service camps at pofnts
where labor shortage is greatest and where
city workers aro to be sent so they enn be
FLEISCHMAN.
booze collars or Just ordinary cellars. Fur
niture that has ft habit of standing Just in
tho path in a dark room can havo u little
radium tack on it and bo signal danger to
unwary shins. Press buttons for lights or
bells nro Illuminated with a dab of radium,
Telephones can bo Illuminated, and countless
other things for which tho householder Is
always groping In tho dark.
.What tho sportsmen will do with radium
is especially Interesting. Fishermen have
found that n radium bait Is especially effec
tive. Radium sighted rides nnd pistols
make It possible to shoot with accuracy In
tho durk. Motorists have discovered sev
eral ufles for radium, including tho Illumi
nating of gusoleno gauges, timepieces,
speedometers and other things. The motor
cyclo speedometer Illuminated with radium
Is practically the only one that Is possible
to rend nt night, slnco a motorcyclo does
not curry Instrument lights. As to air
plane Instruments, practlcnlly nil of them
during tho war were Illuminated with
radium.
Radium Uied in War.
Radium received Its greatest impetus as a
commerchU nnd generally useful article dur
ing tho war. The popularity of radium
Illuminated watches needs no mentioning
Its usefulness to army surgeons Is a chapter
In Itself. RndlUm is used in the treatment
for cancer, tumors nnd other diseases It
also Is'establlshed that the curative propert.,
of radium was recognized even before ra
dium Itself was known to bo tho source nf
the cure. Those great baths of Europe to
which people from all over the world Hooked
to gain relief from nil sorts of miseries were
In reality radium baths, for It is now known
that spring waters contain radium and that
to this fact Is due a great part or then
curative properties.
Predictions as to tho future usage ot
radium border on the fairy tale, for In spite
of the fact that it costs more than $3,000,
000 an ounce and there Is less than a pound
of It in the world, the marvellous 'property
of radium makes this small quantity stretch
limltlessly In usefulness. For not only Is
the radium Itself used, but the radium
emanations possess all the radio- activities
of radium, although without Its permanence
So great Is the power of radium that ac
cording to Sir Oliver Lodge "the power
emitted during the dlsappenranco of a grain
would be enough tfi raise the temperature
of a ton of water from tho freezing to the
boiling point. But this would take about a
year'
He' also says "once an hour ono out of
30.000,000 atoms goes off with violence," and
the speed of this is ho great that a particle
could travel 3,000 miles In one-quarter ol
u second. If we could utilize all the energy
that is inherent in radium there would
probably be no more use for coal, electricity
or any of tho other heaters or energizers
ucd in this world.
distributed to the neighboring farmers. But
in the meantime, which means right now,
scores are being placed each week by direct
correspondence or personal Interview at the
recruiting headquarters.
And In this respect It is also "up to the
farmers" to get In touch with the American
Land Service at once. Tho organization has
a long list of people who are ready to go as
soon as called on. These recruits have teen
carefully selected and their recommendations
Investigated.
Most of these workers are sent to Northern
New Jersey, adjacent New England and the
small fruit growing, codnties of Westihes
tor, Putnam and Dutchess in New York,
where the situation ean be summed up by
quoting a statement made the other day by
ono of the farmers of this labor-bereft sec
tion: "Tho fruit Industry will go down and out
unless wo get outside help and get It
quick!"</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063539/1910-03-25/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Edison+Puzzled+Radium</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1913-10-26/ed-1/?sp=57&q=Miracles+Medicine+Radium+Gamma+Rays</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Leading Physicians and
Surgeons of the World
Report a Surprising
Number of Cases of
Cancerous Growths x
Cured, Stomach and
Liver Trouble Relieved,
and Even Arterial
Hardening Checked A
WREN radium was originally
discovered public Interest
was greatly excite by the
merely curious properties of this
substance -Its power of emitting In
visible rays which penetrated solid
substances, of rendering various
bodies phosphorescent, taking photo
graphs In the dark, of expending en
ergy without apparent loss and so
forth.
Then came the discovery that ra
dium possessed certain curative
powers. The first results were not
very convincing.' and popular inter
est waned.
Now, we learn suddenly, that
physicians and scientists have for
several years been patiently con
ducting experiments which finally
prove that in radium we possess the
most wonderful curative agent In
disease ever discovered.
Radium has cqred many malignant
growths which''were hitherto hope
less. It has brought back destroyed
body cells to life, It has exercised a
beneficial effect in diseases of the
liver and lntestlner?. nnd It Is now
even said to bafillng disease, hardening of the ar
teries'.
In the early days of radium the
effects of treatment were very con*
tradlctory. Sometimes a marked
aggravation of the disease was ob
cerved, sometimes the radium pro
duced serious Injury on healthy tis
sue. But in many cases there was a
surprising and unaccountable cure
of a malignant gTowth.
The reasons of this uncertainty
are now understood. Radium emits
three kinds of rays," which have very
different properties. It also emits
emanations, but that is another
story. The three kinds of rays arS
called alpha, bets and gamma rays,
after the first three letters of the
Greek alphabet.
The most distinguished scientists
In the world, including Madame
Curie, the discoverer of radium, Sir
William Crookes, Sir William Ram
say, Professors Soddy and Ruther
ford as well as many physicians and
surgeons have been absorbed in the
task of studying these three kinds
of rays and establishing the differ
ences between them.
The alpha rays are the shortest,
having a length of about an -Inch!
They have a destructive effect on
healthy tissue. That -was why, In
early experiments, radium often
caused such Injury. The beta ravs
came next in length. They are about
an inch nnd a half long. They have
a stimulating effect on cell growth.
They are, therefore, very dangerous
when applied to cancers and abnor
mal growths, but they are useful in
other ways.
The gamma rays are the longer,
having a length of three Inches or
over. These are the rays that have
effected marvellous cures of can
cerous growths. They check the de
velopment of abnormal cells and
gradually re-establish a normal cell
balance.
The alpha rays are stopped by
glass, aluminum and other metals.
The beta rays are stopped by lead,
hut tho gamma rays penetrate lead.
A thin sheet of lead will, therefore,
protect the tissues against tho in
jurious alpha and beta rays. These
rays are also eliminated by holding
the radium at rbout two inches. Fil
tration through lead requires many
more applications than distance fil
tration, aB the lead cauEes a loss
e\en of much of the gamma rays.
Radium also produces a kind of
gns, known as an emanation, which
fills a receptacle In which the metal
9 kept. This gas causes bodies with
which It comes in contact to become
radio-active for a limited time. This
f 11 rnishes a basis for another kind
medical treatment. The radio
may be Induced In water,
hich is then drunk and exercises a
valuable curative effect in many in
tractable internal diseases. The
radio-activity may also be trans
erred to solid substances and used
In the treatment of abnormal
Srowth As fhe usg of the
costly radium is minimized by
this method it becomes an important
economy in treatment
The alpha rays are charged with
particles of positive electrlcitv, the
u-hn/A?'6 W,th negative electrlcitv
charged'af\TamenPrr?ntly DOt
radium ray. thro?
flc"B^hrgrMwh"0
ith an Instrument called tho
The" bnamhC0He U 13 posslb,e to watch
the bombardment of countless t n
fhp?S produced b>" radium. When
these are put under the influence of
let thrJS-m*finet, U 18 ')0sslbhe
j.i?V.hi'^bZ
tPriHdaai1Pbaartr|nVf hah6 a 8tr?D^ haC"
lenciaai action when thev ar?
ir*"?"? contact with
disease germs. This is why radium
"hen held too near, destrovs healthv
"SnshS 3'hYhen a th,n sheet of
it eld hetween the radium and
appeal1'th6 bacterlc,dal action dis
cutrat,Vfi effect of radium on
gnafi growths is not due to its
ThteHth or eerm-killing power.
Thhl the opinion of Dr. Robert
0tuer hlgh authorities. In
teHrin/i ?a"&nant growths the bac
tericidal action of the alpha ravs
rp?fit bS *!ln?inafed lo secure good
Their curative value la at
tributed to some Imperfectly under
stood power of restoring the bal
ance of normal cell growth.
The gamma rays have a decided
effect in checking life. When mea>
worms were radlurnized they went
on living as meal worms indefinitely,
veritable Methuselahs," while their
sisters and brothers, unradiumized,
progressed for generations, complet
ing cycles of beetles, eggs and meal
worms over and over again.
There are many ways of applying
radium. One method, shown in the
large illustration at the head of this
P^fu' c?nsists in preparing a paste
with radium bromide and spreading
it upon a metal plate having a long
handle. The operator, wearing a
rubber glave. applies this to the
tumor. The alpha and beta rays may
be eliminated by keeping this at a
distance of about two inches or by
interposing a sheet of lead.
The length of application varies
witn the case. Dr. Abbe speaks of a
case where he applted radium for
thirty minutes to a malignant growth
and it began to retrograde in ten
days. In another case he applied It
for twenty-four horn's.
Two other methods of application
consist in placing the radium in a
leaden tube, open at one end. and In
spreading it on a cloth which is at
tached to the surface ro ne treated.
Sulfate of radium injected into th?
Scientist in the Radium Institute, London, the Chief Centre
of Radium Therapy, Using a Scale to Weigh the
Millionth Part of a Gram of Radium.
veins increases blood production, im
proves the digestive functions, stim
ulates the liver and strengthens the
nervous system. Radiuinized water
has a similar effect.
A piece of radium placed against
the head of a blind person, or the
head of an ordinary person in the
dark, will i-ause him to see light in
which solid objects may be distin
guished.
It is from Ix>ndon th.".t the definite
announcement of the efficiency of
radium in curing malignant growths
has come, although Americans have
had a large share in the achievement.
Sir Frederick Treves, the noted
6urgeon, who made his reputation
by treating the late King Edward,
announced recently at the Radium
Institute in Ixmdon that the emana
tions of radium could be used in
place of the original substance. The
Radium Institute is a philanthropic
institution founded by Sir Ernest
Casael for treatment with this ma
terial. It possesses more radium
than auy other institution.
"Radium gives off this emanation
constantly," said Sir F. Treves.
"The amount of the emanation de
pends on the amount of radium used.
The emanation practically never
weakens. The radio-activity of the
piece of radium from which it exudes
is inextinguishable."
As a matter of fact, It has been
estimated that an atom of radium
sheds one-half its radio-activity in
2,500 years. The emanation prob
ably lasts for something approximat
ing that time, although its duration
l'j.a3 not yet been calculated.
Radium emanations contained in
sealed metal applicators are now
sent out to doctors tnroughout Eng
land for_patlents who cannot obtain
radium or go to the Institute. A
gram of radium costs $100,000, but
the emanation is given almost for
nothing.
At the Radium Institute many
cureB of inoperable cancers or ma
lignant tumors "were announced.
One woman had an enormous sar
coma of tho collarbone. She had
been informed by surgeons that tho
only remedy was removal of the en
tire right arm and shoulder. A tube
containing 116 milligrams of radium
was imbedded In the tumor for
twelve hours on two cojisecutlve
days. "Within a month alf signs of
tho growth had disappeared. Now,
after tho lapse of six months, there
is no recurrence.
A school teacher, aged thirty-five,
Copyright. 1913,
How Radium Is Used in the Treatment of a Malignant Tumor. The Radium
Bromide Is Spread Upon the Metal Disc Which Is Held by the Surgeon with
a Rubber Glove. The Alpha Rays (Indicated by the G-reek Letter for "A")
in Lighter Circle Around the Disc, Reach an Inch and Would Do Harm if
They Touched the Tissues. The Beta Rays (Indicated by the Greek Letter
for "B"), Shown in the Lighter and Darker Circles, Would Be Equally
Harmful, as They Stimijlate Growth.* The Gamma Rays (Indicated by the
Greek Letter for "G") Shown in Both Circles and Beyond, with a Range of
Three Inches or More, Have a Destructive Effect on the Tumor, and Must
Alone Be Permitted to Reach It. The Distinctive Signs of These Three
Kinds of Rays Are the First Three Letters of the Greek Alphabet.
radium. The tube is placed in., a
porcelain receptacle containing a
gallon of water, which becomes ra
diumlzed. The patient takes three
glasses of this water a day.
At the Middlesex Hospital, in Lon
don, a great institution for the treat
ment of cancer patients, reports
show twenty-five cases of cancer
cured by radium. Sir Alfred Pearce
Gould, senior surgeon of this hos
Dital, says:
"By the use of gamma rays in
cancer of the breast 1 have seen foul
ulcers cleaned; some ulcers have
healed up entirely; I have repeated
ly seen small secondary nodules in
the skin and fascia disappear; I
have had several cases where larger
and deeper secondary growths in
volving muscles?, ribs, rib cartilages
or sternum have disappeared, and in
other cases such growths have re
mained qtiiescen! and stationary for
such long periods that I could only
think the radiations bad at least an
inhibitory effect on the growth."
Dr. Robert Abbe, seuior surgeon of
St. Luke's Hospital, New York, one
of the most noted operators of the
metropolis, before the recent Inter
national Congress of Medicine in
London described an amazing series
of cures of malignant growths by
means of radium.
"During ten years," said Dr. Abbe,
Diagram of a Cancer Treated by Dr. Robert Abbe, of New
York, with Radium. The White Dots on Black Ground
Show the Cancer Cells Degenerated Under the
Influence of Radium.
From the Medical Ilecord, Xerr York.
had an inoperable cuycmoma of the
thyroid gland of the neck. After
three series of treatments with ra
dium the enlargement and hardening
of the thyroid disappeared. The pa
tient has now returned to work.
Most striking results have been
obtained from drinking radiumized
water. Out of 100 per cont of ad
vanced rheumatism cases -10 per
cent showed marked improvement,
30 per cent derived benefit, and the
remaining 30 per cent remained un
changed.
Walter A. Brady, the seventy-year
old clerk of Part V, Supreme Court
of New York, reports that he has
been cured of, a hopeless case of
hardening of the arteries by ra
diumized water. He was told that
there was no prospect of a cure.
Threo months ago he began tak
ing a preparation of radiumized
water put up by a Berlin physician.
"The results havo been amazing."
says Mr. Brady. "From an artei lal
pressure of 230 pounds, which is a
terrible one, my pressure has been
reduccd to 150 pounds, not far above
normal, and I feel twenty years
younger. My regular physician has
been keeping my chart, and ho is as
enthusiastic as I am."
The apparatus used consists of a
tiny tube containing a particle of
"I have been able to study the effi
ciency of these specimens of Madame
Curie's radium on more than 75ft in
dividual cases in private, including
250 epitheliomas of all parts; 180
carcinomas of the tongue, throat,
oesophagus, breasr, intestines and
other visceral organs; aO sarcomas
of the skin, parotid gland, bones, etc..
besides goitres, tumors of the liver
and mediastinum and a variety of
naevi, moles, papilloma, etc."
In all cases where he ha/l not ob
tained beneficial results "Dr. Abbo
said it. was due to error in using
the radium. There were three types
of results (1) destruction of tissues
too closely in contuct (2) stimulation
and harmful results, and (3) effi
cient retrograde degeneration of
malignant growths, with lasting
benefits amounting at times to a sur
gical cure.
Since he had understood that the
gamma rays were the cause of the
degeneration of tumors Dr. Abbe
said he had never failed to .obtain
beneficial results.
Here is an example of one ot Dr.
Abbe's many ca.ses:
"A young man had the upper three
inches of the right humerus entirely
replaced by a myeloid tumor ex
panding in lemon shape. Under co
caine anaesthesia a portion removed
by the Star Company. Groat Britain Rights Reserved.
showed mixed giant-cell and spindle
cei! sarcoma. I embedded in the
mass four tubes of radium (total 150
milligrams) for three days, so as to
irrad-ra-te and cross-fire It. During
the eight weeks following gritty bone
began to form in the soft tumors,
and then a bony shell formed. Dur
ing six months a marked increase in
bone and simultaneous shrinkage
has occurred. Notwithstanding some
central necrosis of the soft tissue, it
bids fair to recover Its bone solidity
and strength."
So wonderful was the regrowth of
normal tissue previously destroyed
by a tumor that Dr. Abbe put for
ward a theory that radium has the
power of restoring the balance of life
forces:
"In what does the beneficent ac
tion of radium reside? .This ques
tlon, with many others, still awaits
solution. We know only that we
have a subtle force, which, as far as
we discern, is a stream of rays
charged with negative electricity
with intense penetrating power,
capable of traversing stone, human
flesh, or solid steel with facility,
which plays upon the vital cells
(animal or vegetable) and alters
their rate of growth or kills them
altogether.
"What the vlt^l spark is in a liv
ing thing no one knows. It has been
surmised that life itself may only be
an embodiment of electric force. It
has been supposed by some that a
living cell continues its normal ca
reer owing to a balance established
within it between positive and nega
tive eleqtric force, and that an ag
gregate mass of colls in the body,
such as constitutes a tumor, may
result from their erratic growth
owing to a loss of balance of elec
tric equilibrium. May it not be rea
sonable to suppose that a mild ap
plication of radium emitting its dis
tinctive rays is thereby capable of
restoring the electric equilibrium,
while on the other hand a prolonged
and intense application carries the
balance to a destructive terminal
tion?
?"Consider for a moment that re
markable case you have seen of the
tumor of the eyelid. It had displaced
the normal skin and mucous mem
brane, and grown In bulk many
times the size of tissues that had
been lost in It. There was no sem
blance of an eyelid in the. mass
whose tuberous growth rose in
heaped-up masses on the skin, and
within, and on the edge.
"A cross section would have
shown no vestige of former tissues
which were destroyed or lost in the
mass. Yet, when retrograde was fin
ished under radium action, behold
the normal skin structure, the nor
mal glands and eyelashes! The orig
inal cells were not destroyed. There
was a reassembling out of the con
glomerate diseased mass. Whence,
then, came the diseased cells? This
can be answered only by the as
sumption that an intercellular Invis
ible and ultramicroscopic system of
particles had existed with a life of
their own, constituting a network
holding the visible cells together.
This system, then, had itself taken
on an erratic growth and become a
sarcoma mass, engulfing the regu
lar occupants of the ground."
Dr. Joseph Mulr, of New York, has
elucidated a theory held by many
physicians now that the curative
properties of natoi'al waters, hith
erto attributed to the minerals they
contained, are really due to their
radio-active qualities. Whenever these
spring waters have been examined,
they have been found to be radio
active.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053157/1914-03-04/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Wonder+Workings+Medical+Radium+Experiments</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>United States Has
Now a Radium
Institute.
BY MEDICAL WORLD
Scientists Are Busy
Conducting Novel
Experiments.
1
R
i ADIUM. radium—more radium!
This is the latest cry of the
surgeon, for the curative pow
er of radium, especially for
cancerous growths, is now exciting the
medical world. But radium is ex
tremely scarce and wonderfully valua
ble. Gold can scarcely be called a
precious metal in comparison. Gold is
worth but $20 an ounce, while a simi
lar quantity of radium would com
mand the vast sum of $4,000,000.
What is more, there is every proba
bility of the price of radium rising
higher if some of the beneficent work
it has already done proves to be last
ing. Reference is made to what it has
accomplished so far in battling with
sinister cancer and to what it has
wrought toward a return to health in
lesser maladies.
Radium fetches today at least $120,
000 a gram, and the world over during
the last year probably not more than
a total of sixteen grains were extract
ed from the hundreds of tons of raw
material worked for that purpose. Of
this amount about three-fourths had its
origin in the United States, and yet
today relatively little of this new found
curutive agent is in the possession of
American hospitals, physicians and
laboratories. Foreigners draw the vast
bulk of the mother substance from
the mines in this country.
How to produce more radium is ono
of the burning questions of the day,
and this country is particularly inter
ested in conserving its resources in
this direction and producing radium
for home consumption. Secretary of
the Interior Lane proposes to with
draw all lands of the public domain
believed to contain radium that their
precious deposits may be secured for
the public good and not become the
subject of private speculation.
He has urged the passage of a joint
congressional resolution empowering
the president to make the withdrawals.
By the terms of the proposed résolu
Photo by American Press Association.
MARIS CURIE, DIBCOVERQlt OF RA
D1UM, IM HER LABORATORY.
tlon the secretary of the interior would
be authorized "to conduct exporations
and researches with a view to deter
mining the practicability of develop
ing from such ores a supply of radium
and to provide for the mining and
treatment of radium bearing ores in
such manner as would best secure a
supply of radium for the use of the
government of the United States and
the hospitals of this country."
Secretary Lane points out that there
are only two grains of radium in the
United States at present and says:
"Radium is fouiid in ores carrying
oranium and vanadium, which are
used extensively in the arts, and proc
esses by which it is extracted are se
cret A process has been invented by
the chemists in our bureau of mines
which promises, from the laboratory
experiments thus far made, to be suc
cessful. Under the endowment of two
Americans, a building is now being
erected in Denver (which, with its
equipment will be opened for work in
the coming February), in which an
effort will be made to prove the com
mercial possibility of this American
process. If successful this process will
be given to the world, and all of the
radium secured over and above a small
minimum will be the property of the
United States and will be put into the
bands of the United States public
health service for public use.
"Under all these circumstances, it
seems to me that the only prudent
course that the United States can fol
low is to withdraw such of its lands
as are supiiosed to contain radium
from public entry. This will guard
agalnBt these lands being taken up by
those who would not put them to their
highest and most beneficial use."
The building being erected in Den
ver referred to by Secretary Lane is
that of the American National Radium
institute, which has been incorporated
and endowed by Dr. Howard Kelly of
Baltimore and Dr. James Douglas of
Aew York city, together with, as an
incorporator and president. Dr. Charles
L. Parsons of the United States bu
reau of mines and chief of the division
of mineral technology. The institute
is co-operating with the bureau of
mines. It was Dr. Kelly who treated
Representative Bremner of New Jersey.
Dr. Kelly has expressed himself as not
believing that radium will eradicate
cancer, at least in the near future, but
he is satisfied that it will be an excel
lent helpmate for surgery and that In
some cases radium, as it is now ap
plied. may suffice to bring about cures.
The American National Radium In
stitute, if the hopes of its organizers
be realized, will be richer in radium
than any other institute of the sort.
The Radium institute of Vienna owns
about two and one-half grams of radi
PIECES OF BADIUH BEARING ORE.
um salts, obtained well nigh exclu
sively from the famous pitchblende of
the mines at Joachimstbal. In Paris
Mme. Curie's laboratory boasts some
thing like one gram of radium, and
this will be transferred to the new
Radium institute, and the Radium in
stitute in London bas at its disposi
tion somewhere between one and two
grams of radium chloride. And yet
wonders have been worked already
with these extremely small quantities.
For instance, the Loudon Radium in
stitute treated during a period of near
ly sixteen un nths a total of 61U pa
tients. Out of these fifty-three were
apparently cured, twenty-eight were
declared cured and 245 were pronounc
ed improved. There were, however,
seventy sufferers not improved, eighty
eight abandoned the treatment, and flf
ty-flve died. At the time of the report
the remaining forty-one cases had been
too recently treated for the announce
ment of definite results.
The patients were afflicted with a
large number of diseases, but the ma
jority of them were suffering from ul
cers, tumors, cancers and oilier ma
lignant maladies, and iu the light of
recent information it is probable that
of the 245 "improved" many might
have been classed among the "cured"
or "apparently cured" had the resi
dent physicians had at their disposi
tion a larger quantity of radium.
It was Mme. Marie Curie who, in con
junction with her husband, Professor
Curle, since dead, discovered radium
In 1888. She is now at the head of the
Radium institute at Paris.
The discovery of radium led to the
finding of thirty-eight radio-active bod
ies. Some disappear so soon that they
cannot be examined; others can last a
billion years, in spite of all efforts,
such ab beating it to 1,500 degrees of
warmth and cooling it to minus 180
degrees, Mme. Curie says she has not
NEW BADICM INSTITUTE AT PARIS.
been able yet to break up radium into
other component elements. She is still
trying.
The experiments of scientists with
radium brings us to one of the most
interesting aspects of the vital ques
tion of supply. The physicist knows
that uranium, the parent of radium,
disintegrates in 12,000,000.000 years
and during this incomprehensible pe
riod of time produces, through various
intermediate substances, the precious
mineral we now seek. What the wiz
ard of chemistry is now trying to do
is to convert uranium into radium
within an interval of only mouths
If he can do this—and there are ex
perts that believe it possible—then, in
stead of having to wait for the ages to
work this metamorphosis, man may
transmute uranium into radium and
produce in much larger quantities this
marvelous healing agency.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024827/1918-09-08/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Radium+Paint+Scarce</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>RADIUM
MAY
SOON
New Yorks Latest Successes-Pretty Girls-Class Costumes
OWN JASS ORCHESTRA
Change of Program Wednesday and Thursdays.
BE MORE SCARCE!
Everything New But the Pretty Girls
IN
REV EW WANT ADS BRING
RESULTS.
A shortage of radium was forecast
t-.y Dr. Richard B. Sloore of the United
.States bureau of mines in an address
I he deiivc red at Cripple Creek, Colo,
Wednesday, before the annual meet
!in of the American Institute of Min
ing Engineers. Radium is largely be-'
i in-, use J on the faces of watches and
clocks and other similar purposes, the
TWO SHOWS EVERY NIGHT, 7 AND 9.
i
(Including War Tax)
LOWER FLOOR, SGc; BALCONY, 35c
1 w,
tiffirt
113 jr. r-i S
Give the
miners
a Chance to
ia of
MR. BUSINESS MAN
go to the booth when you come to work in the morning. Then send your clerlc3
to the polling places during the morning.
MR, PROFESSIONAL MAN
don't wait until mid-day before voting. Take advantage of the early morning
when the polls are net rushed.
MR. AND MRS. CLERK
ask your employer to release you early in the day so you can vole. Then get
ycur bullet in the box as soon as possible.
i.'iRZ. HOUSEWIFE
when your breakfast dishes are washed and the house is dusted, go to the pells.
Dor.'t wait till afternoon. If possible go with your husband, or son, or daughter, wher.
they Ipave early in the morning.
EVERYONE
remember the boys in the mines. Make the work a3 fasy for the election offi
cers S3 possible. The rush hours at the polls are from 4 to 6 o'clock p. m. Get your
vols in before that time.
REi'viEMULR THE BOYS ON DAY SHIFT
clear the polling places bctcrc 4 p. m.io the day shift can vote.
V iJ tij jiJf JUL I j
ote Early
WARREN DISTRICT SUTTER CLUB
sj caker said, according to Associated
j I rrss reports.
j "It is a great pity that our supply of
radium is being disseminated in this
'manner." said Dr. Moore. "Hut as the
physicians and surgeons of the country i
re not pun basing enough radium to
make the industry a financial sucees-i,
it is n itnra'. that the manufacturers
.should take other means of creating a
duiia:i(l. The day is n! far distant,
i:i my j'idsmnt When we shall gr atly
rr-ret ti:e radium that has been lost
i?; this way.
"liixdir.m has a most decided useful
ness at the present time. Nine instru
m n;s used on :iirplan"s have dials
made iumincus with radium paint; it
is emphned in th same manner for
compasses and gunsiuhts. The tfi'i
clenry of niht firing, with both nia
(tiir.r1 t:nns and enillery has been
greatly increased by the use of these,
1 niiKii's si:,-!;;s. Oih'T use cannot he
r" i;-i. at the resc.it time, in pub
lic papers.
"It Is 'iilficu't to estimate the ex-i
!t a-.:cun; .f radium i?i existence at'
ti e nt time, probably it is some
wh'T" around three ozs. of radium ele
mnt. Consid'.rahly more than half
the amount of radium now in existence
has com,, troin Colorado and f'ah
cartiotite ores. t
"S'x ye;.r.; ago, the c njanc-'rrs (if iho
bureau of mines estimated that at the'
current rate of production the depos-'
its niiht l:n.t, iiinimr rcinlly, ten or
twelve years. At the present time it'
vry tii'.-'i't ;to ii.t nrc Most
r.f t'! (ieptioit arc owned by live op
einsin; ra(ii;-.i companies. The pro
i( t:'i.n has i.u raised ery greatly
i;i' the v.ar, and I mi very douht
J"-'Vr v cr,:i r -"m upon our
r tv c i s to yield cnmnierci il
cu.m:!'!".-, of its tor core t'.nn six or
sctt! vi" o":cr. It is n-.y judg
n.' n; th ir f'le fields will no' produce
i'"'" Ki.'i au.liUnnal grams of
tadium element at the most if that,
mil"1- T'Mi otild abo'it double the
v.r.rlfi's prpsor.t supply, but, on ac
t'itt rf rim v-r?rr uso of radium In
cviirrr trrtmT.t. such ait amount. t,'
It; r'-irfiti-lllv, would be
'n.i'l in prrrortim to tli probable
(i 'ii:ir.d.
j.r, v-Ui ;2 t!- (!i. :l'-l.
pf ta-ii.ii I; to pro-
r r.MiM'i't.'r.'. Mi -otiuriuin i.; an
xcllriit su' il 1 in ma.iy wavs. Ilr.
hiiif 1 pr;1i d is uvu h sdiorter than j
'hat ot i ,'i'ii'i'".. !i"ii first pt par'-lj
i iii'lnl! in'-rc ip-s In ;ictlvil.;
i :.i,innm ;ind lien begins i
io 1":." it;-, in i ily. A II. r 'ripening' i
1'iv 1 i':ir al: I in:; pif"p:ii'l
i' i i:i l.i- i I i' r I'li.iiinii,;: p;iint just
is f !tr :".:tl- as ra-iinnj. Its usful-!
in -s lor bUih purpose will iut lor
CENTR</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-queen-victoria/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-race-south-pole/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>

</topics>
